<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Panala medica vel sanitatis et longævitatis alumna catholica: = The fruitfull and frugall nourse of sound health and long life. Per Guil: Folkingham Gen: Math. &amp; Med. studiosum.</title>
            <author>Folkingham, W. (William)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 197 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 74 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01019</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118470</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853677</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853677</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19071</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01019)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19071)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1202:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Panala medica vel sanitatis et longævitatis alumna catholica: = The fruitfull and frugall nourse of sound health and long life. Per Guil: Folkingham Gen: Math. &amp; Med. studiosum.</title>
                  <author>Folkingham, W. (William)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30], 117, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Miles Flesher,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ale --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19071:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19071:1"/>
            <p>3 PANALA MEDICA; VEL SANITATIS ET LONGAEVITATIS Alumna Catholica:</p>
            <p>The fruitfull and frugall Nourſe of ſound Health and long Life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Per</hi> Guil: Folkingham <hi>Gen: Math. &amp; Med. ſtudioſum.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Principiis obſta; ſeró Medicina paratur,</l>
               <l>Cum Mala per longas invaluere Moras.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Miles Fleſher.</hi> 1628.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19071:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19071:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>To much enobled Wingfeild my Magnifique</l>
                  <l>Moecena's, and The Worthies who deſigne</l>
                  <l>Stanfordian Celebrates of Meets, munifique</l>
                  <l>Accommodates to animate th'Enſigne</l>
                  <l>Of Englands Patron great, for royall Standard</l>
                  <l>To th'Rendezvous of their endear'd Regua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d;</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>An it bee conceiued (Honorable and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Spirits of ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous magnificence) that the yet continued Fame that the firſt <hi>Brittiſh Bowers</hi> for the <hi>Muſes</hi> were built vpon the bancks of <hi>Welland,</hi> ſprung meerely from the bold Fiction of a Phanatique idle Braine? Muſt it be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted that the bright Pillar of ſuch a flame could with ſo long-laſting du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance towre-vp from an empty Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace,
<pb facs="tcp:19071:3"/>
that neuer was fraught with the foizon, nor euer felt the feruor of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall fewell? Shall meere coniec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture make ſlight the authoritie of yet extant Records (<hi>Chronique writ and Aulique foundation</hi>) conteſting that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollos Daughters</hi> honoured <hi>Stanfordian Cells</hi> with theit <hi>Mayden-immurage</hi> and firſt reſidence in this Iſle, long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Northerne Academiques</hi> (falne by diſciſion from the <hi>Southerne,</hi> and flitting from the <hi>Occidentall</hi> to the <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entall Foord</hi>) ſeconded their ſetling here, in their endeared Reflex to the former? Howſoeuer, whether the firſt foundation were diſſolued through <hi>Malingene</hi> or no, <hi>Townes, Honours,</hi> and <hi>Times,</hi> we ſee, haue their <hi>Tides, Turnes</hi> and <hi>Periods:</hi> the <hi>Muſes</hi> by Regal] writ commanded to be banned and reman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to their forſaken Foord, this their deare Delight, thus depriued of their Cordiall Muſicke, and after demoliſht by <hi>Mauors</hi> (maugre Caſtle and begir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:19071:3"/>
Wall) could neuer yet lift-vp her obrute head from vnder the heauy rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh of ruinate depreſſure, threatning her with obſcuring pouerty to interre Ancient Renowne in eternall obliuion. Such yet is the accommodation of the place, both for action and contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as may well induce preſent times and poſterity to approue of the atteſts of Antiquity, touching the affections of the <hi>Camaenae</hi> caught with the ameni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the ſite of this Towne, within whoſe confines <hi>Six Couents</hi> of <hi>Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiques,</hi> for the ſingular ſalubrity of the <hi>Soile, Water,</hi> and <hi>Aire,</hi> choſe their Cels of commorance. Yea <hi>Nature</hi> her ſelfe, hauing moulded this Plat-forme for ends of more eminence, than yet are ſeene to ſucceed her ordinance, breathes forth inceſſant cloſe murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings againſt the iniurious neglect of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate or ſlow-footed Fate, that this <hi>Center</hi> to ſo ſweet a Country (ſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified with ſo many magnifique Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices
<pb facs="tcp:19071:4"/>
and Towrie Structures) ſo accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate for <hi>Nauigation</hi> (of Import and Export) and affluence of concourſe, ſhould not be honoured with the right of a <hi>Portable Riuer</hi> for Mart, and of an Act for <hi>Shire-Towne</hi> to competent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, and to incompaſſe <hi>Rotell.</hi> For matter of <hi>Exerciſe</hi> and pleaſurable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations, and of Chaſe and VVing, in ſuch ſweet mixt Earths, interlaced with <hi>Brookes</hi> and <hi>fordible Riuers, Heath, Forreſt, Light Tilths,</hi> large <hi>Champaine</hi> variegated with coole ſhades of ſome ſcattered Woods and <hi>gentle-riſing Hils</hi> of <hi>Eaſie Climbe</hi> to <hi>Plaines</hi> of no redious dimenſions, leading ouer delightfull <hi>Downs,</hi> ſhallow <hi>Dales</hi> &amp; Valleys of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended diſcents ſecure from break-neck <hi>precipitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> it affords ſuch variety of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable venarie (<hi>date veniam verbis</hi>) to aggrate and ſatiate the eager queſt of the moſt ranging appetite, that <hi>Horſe, Hound</hi> and <hi>Hawke</hi> hardly find any place to parallel this Plot in the diuerſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars
<pb facs="tcp:19071:4"/>
of <hi>Race, Game</hi> and <hi>pourſuit, viz, Hare, Deere, Fox, Otter; Partridge, Phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, Mallard, Heren</hi> and his Prey. The noble conſideration and iuſt prizing of the premiſſes, hath inuited and ſtirred-vp the magnifique thoughts of many Honourable Perſonages to endeare this Place, and by ſundry wayes and means to endeuour its readuance to Repute, ſuiting in ſome reaſonable ſort with its true deſeruing worth. Amongſt which laudable purpoſes, I muſt euer magnifie your munifique noble Aymes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Stanford</hi> the <hi>Rendezuous</hi> to the frequent <hi>confluence</hi> of good <hi>company,</hi> with your gracious reflect vpon my great Disburſments (ouer and aboue the Magnificent Bounty of euer-hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Exeter</hi>) to gratifie all friends with contentfull intertaine, and vpon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurious expoſure to vniuſt ſufferings, in my wel-willing to the weale of Towne and Country, by deepe wading in the <hi>Nauigation of Welland,</hi> which is long
<pb facs="tcp:19071:5"/>
ſince (through credulity of ſome ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendents, permitting vnſeaſoned and improuident Agents, without controll to abuſe Noble Intentions, and burie bounteous contributes in ill-pondred purſuit of fond addle Plots) caſt into a profound Sleepe. A Sleepe wherein deepe wronged <hi>Welland</hi> is like to wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and lye forlorne (howſoeuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailed) till ſome ingenuous <hi>Mercuriall Hand,</hi> with the quickning <hi>Spirit</hi> of a <hi>Golden Elixir</hi> (more potent than the Care-charming <hi>Caduceus</hi>) diſcuſſe her ſoporiferous <hi>Spirits,</hi> rouze and raiſe-vp her torpid head, and right her rude diſſheueld Locks, which ſhut forth the Sunne beames of <hi>Beautie, Life,</hi> and <hi>Action,</hi> from giuing bright ſplendor to deſerued renowne. Which good ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of wiſhed C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re and Cure hoping propitious Heauens will in due time maturely produce with other helpes of happy conſequence, I haſte to the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dique part of Panala,</hi> with intenſion of
<pb facs="tcp:19071:5"/>
the <hi>Dietetique,</hi> if, by Dignoſtiques of the Reliſh of this, I conceiue any hope of diſpenſing that Compoſition, to pleaſe the palate of ſuch <hi>Worthies,</hi> my euer honoured <hi>Patrons</hi>: to whoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble magnificence, deſiring the indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent fauour to be deuoted a moſt zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and obliged <hi>Seruitour,</hi> I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your inceſſant true Obſeruant
<hi>William Folkingham.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19071:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19071:6"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot much amiſſe ſurely is the Aſſertion which averrs The <hi>Optimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Bene Valere; Secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, formoſumeſſe; Tertium, Diuitias habere nulla fraude quaeſitas</hi>: for <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> without <hi>Health</hi> can neither haue ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led continuance of Abode, nor any true Beeing; nor a World of Wealth any right reliſh of <hi>Pleaſure.</hi> And though the true extent of this comparatiue <hi>Tenet,</hi> in the ſuperlatiue Praiſe of <hi>Health,</hi> muſt admit of confinage (<hi>Quoad ſummum Bonum</hi>) not to out-reach the Ring or Limb of the loweſt Orbes, but deſigning limitation
<pb facs="tcp:19071:7"/>
euermore to <hi>bona mundana, Health</hi> doubtleſſe, in due eſteeme of true worth, is a greater bleſsing than that <hi>Courted Beauty,</hi> or this <hi>Cordiall wealth.</hi> For in reguard, that <hi>Man</hi> being in <hi>Dures,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the heauie Arreſt of fettring <hi>Sicknes,</hi> cannot, in any due performance, tend vnto or attend the end &amp; office of his creation, for diſcharge eyther of the duty of his <hi>Calling</hi> vnto the world, or of his <hi>Beeing</hi> vnto the worlds Creator, becauſe the ſoule though of <hi>Coeleſtiall Of-ſpring,</hi> whileſt it is ſeated in this our Earthly Pallace, (or Priſon much the rather) neceſſarily Sympathizes with the body, and is ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the expenſe of precious ſpirits (Natures beſt Treaſures) and with paines, diſtractions, and other ſufferings of the ſame, that her Animall Faculties are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praued, and miſerable hee depriued of the ſweet ſolace and happy comfort of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Contemplation, and other both Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine offices, and humane Obligations, this in valuable <hi>Iewell</hi> of <hi>Health</hi> becomes
<pb facs="tcp:19071:7"/>
a Heauenly Bleſsing in due Eſtimate, far tranſcenaing the valuation of all terrene Traſh, how treaſurable ſoeuer, extending its due priſall beyond the dimenſions of this <hi>Baſis.</hi> But how takes this <hi>Tenet</hi> with the world? Sinckes it into all our thoughts as it ought, and would if we did duly reflect them, as we ſhould, vpon the <hi>Diuine Deriuation</hi>? Surely it ſeldome or neuer ſounds the <hi>Center</hi> of that heart which holds the fruition of that ſelf-Gem, or boſome friend, ſound and well ſetled <hi>Health</hi>; For <hi>Bona carendo magis quam fruendo agnoſcimus,</hi> who neuer felt the diſgust of the bitter cup of <hi>Sickneſſe</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not rightly reliſh the ſweet taſt of <hi>Sani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</hi> But <hi>contraria juxta ſe poſita ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis eluceſcunt,</hi> Contraries are beſt illuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated and diſtinguiſht by their contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; and he, that after long durance or ſharpe Torture of a grieuous <hi>Diſeaſe,</hi> happily recouers ſome reaſonable meaſure of healthfull ſtate or relaxation from lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guor, well knowes and will acknowledge
<pb facs="tcp:19071:8"/>
with me, that <hi>Bona valetudo maximè Diuinum longe<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> blandiſſimum eſt vitae condimentum,</hi> that ſanitude is a Celeſtiall moſt delicious condiment, and the beſt ſeaſoning to reliſh the Nectar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweets of a happie naturall <hi>Life.</hi> For <hi>non vivere ſed valere vita eſt, Health</hi> is the Crowne and Life of <hi>Life,</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Health</hi> is no <hi>Life,</hi> but euen a lingring <hi>Death,</hi> where both Animall Powers and Corporall parts ſuffering, produce but lame and depraued Actions. For <hi>Sicknes</hi> being an affect againſt Nature (<hi>ex Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metro Sanitati oppoſitus</hi>) ſeated in the Bodie by intruding ſeiſure, and of it ſelfe primarily vitiating the Naturall State and Conſtitution of Mans fabricke, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbs and peruerts both corporall and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimall function, with diſordred exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance confounding the conſociable <hi>Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomie</hi> of the body, and with diſcordant larrings diſtuning the <hi>Organs</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbing the happy <hi>Harmony</hi> of the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> thoſe ſacred <hi>Opifices</hi> accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:19071:8"/>
our <hi>Microcoſme</hi> to all commendable actions. Now the moſt generall <hi>Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of <hi>Sicknes</hi> is ſuperfluous <hi>Repletion,</hi> with which the ſtrongeſt bodies are many times ſo ouerborne, that, like ouer ballaſted Ships they ſuddenly fincke vnder the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie load of abundance, but the <hi>Cacho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chymique corps</hi> fraught and craſed with crudities, is euermore expoſed to all the iniuries of the Six <hi>Non-naturals,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that euery ingruent diſtemper of <hi>Heat, Cold, Diet, Labour,</hi> or other Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in th'uſe of any of them, plunges it into one <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> or other, euen like a cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie <hi>Ship</hi> which is prone with euery rough Sea to ſpring Lecke, and bee dilacerated and ſplit with euery Tempeſt. And who ſees not, that the full and foule feedings of this Nation (aduanced through the vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous liuing of theſe times, which hales and drawes downe from Heauen a heauie curſe vpon all Creatures both Aliments and Elements) heape vp many crude and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure ſuperfluities which ſo vitiate the
<pb facs="tcp:19071:9"/>
               <hi>temperature</hi> of the continent veſſels and depraue the harmonious <hi>frame</hi> of the whole <hi>Bodie,</hi> that daily-new broodes of inſolit and ſtrange <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> (tranſlating <hi>Plinies Trecenturiall Number</hi> or ſorts of infirmities to infinite) aſſault mans Bulwarke of <hi>Health,</hi> with inſolent freſh batteries till they ſacke it with inſulting Demoliſh? Knowing then, that <hi>Repleti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is cured by Evacuation, and being by long &amp; infallible experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wel confirmed in good approbation of my <hi>Panala</hi> (for fit munition againſt ſuch <hi>Machines</hi>) whoſe Medique part is bred and brought forth by Infuſion of a wel-diſpenſed <hi>Fund</hi> or <hi>Bag</hi> of ſpecifique Ingredients in ordinary <hi>Ale</hi> (the Ancient drinke of this Iſle) than which there can hardly be excogitated or inuented a more generall worthy Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, that ſo cheape and choyce, without any curioſity of Preparation or vſe by the Patient, doth <hi>Tuto</hi> ſans hazard, <hi>&amp; ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundè,</hi> nor grieuing with ingrate reliſh of Phyſicke, nor ouer-lading with too
<pb facs="tcp:19071:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
much, <hi>&amp; ſat ſcito, quia ſat bene,</hi> good ſpeed is beſt ſpeed, both conſerue the ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie ſtate of the body, and preuent and cure moſt morbid affects and diſeaſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to the ſame (by clenſing and recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying all parts and members thereof) whether deriuable from indigeſted ballaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings or otherwiſe contracted, I could not diſpenſe with an abſolute concealement of it's moſt precious worth, but in ſome ſort, (<hi>Quoad medicationis diſpoſitionem, non medicaminis Compoſitione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi>) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to the world, the manifold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits flowing from the familiar &amp; fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full operation thereof. But ſhould I bee ſo fond, to promulgate to the <hi>Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> and <hi>diſpence</hi> of the <hi>Fund</hi> or <hi>Bagge</hi> itſelfe, I ſhould too much derogate from the due eſteeme and true dignitie of the <hi>Secret;</hi> and <hi>miſcendo ſacra prophanis,</hi> by lauiſh <hi>Publiſh</hi> much prophane the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <hi>Myſteries</hi> of <hi>Apollo.</hi> Though <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> her ſelfe then ſhould plead her beſt in approuement of the <hi>Diſcouery</hi> with
<pb facs="tcp:19071:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Bonum quo communius, eo melius;</hi> yet would neither the Empericke, nor the Methodist let mee paſſe without a Blow or a Brand; And worthily too, for <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum minuit Maieſtatem, qui divulgat Myſtica,</hi> and with what deliuer Paſſage or commendable poſture could I fairly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyd the vile and odious venue of beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Broods</hi> of <hi>Mountebanckes,</hi> and ſo breed the baine in ſtead of the Balme both to priuate and publique <hi>Health,</hi> if Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darizing to ſo deere a Progenie, I ſhould vnnaturally &amp; baſely proſtitute ſo virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and worthie a Virgin, and ſo intimate and gentile a <hi>Handmaid of diuine Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke</hi> to vulgar gaze, and the artleſſe baſe abuſe of euery <hi>Horch-leach, Quackſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> and <hi>Sophiſticke?</hi> Pardon there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my yet reſerue of further Publicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: I am not ſo ambitious to caſt-bout to make this <hi>Magiſtrall</hi> a Caſt net to catch Shoales or promiſcuous Schooles of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pils without diſtinction of worth or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. I pity both this popular ſilly-poore
<pb facs="tcp:19071:10"/>
Ambition of Profeſſors, and the penurious fond conceipts of many <hi>Patients,</hi> who, to ſaue the leaſt conceiued trifle-charge of Cure, will vpon any ſmall Hint of a <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall</hi> helpe, bee either raw or more than ripe Medlars in Medicines, and like blind Byards raſhly and rudely ruſh into the vnſounded <hi>Deepes</hi> of the <hi>Sacred Myſteries</hi> of <hi>Medication;</hi> Faith and workes are neceſſary <hi>Cooperants</hi> for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the <hi>Soule,</hi> but, to redeeme the body from Dures of diſeaſes and repaire the ruines of impaired <hi>Health,</hi> it were to be wiſht that Patients would rather bee conſtant, ſtrong <hi>Solifidians</hi> in obſequious conformitie to the counſell of the <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian,</hi> than buſie bold <hi>Phyſmicaries: Tactant fabrilia fabri</hi>: let not Patients turne Medicine Mungers, but contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning themſelues within their proper <hi>Spheres</hi> of <hi>Prayer, Confidence</hi> and <hi>Regularitie,</hi> referre each Cure to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt care of the Rationall Artist, who knowes how to keepe the <hi>Golden Meane,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19071:11"/>
betweene the ſuperſtitious <hi>Empiricke,</hi> and the ambitious <hi>Methodian,</hi> both which doe many times make the beſt <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes</hi> no better then preſt and fiat <hi>Deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes.</hi> For the obſtinate <hi>Empiricke,</hi> groſly holding it a religious Tye, <hi>Iurare in verba Magiſtri,</hi> ſo ſuperſtitiouſly and wilfully weds himſelfe to experimentalls, that he will not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for a world of reaſon, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline or be drawne, <hi>ne latum quidem vnguem,</hi> not the breadth of a Haire, from a <hi>Probatum,</hi> but ſtill in all his practice propines one and the ſelfe ſame (ſecret for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) <hi>totidem verbis &amp; herbis,</hi> both in <hi>Doſe</hi> and <hi>diſpence,</hi> to euery man promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly. Now the capritious <hi>Methodian,</hi> out of curious ſingularity to tranſcend the ſpurnd repute of <hi>Empiricie,</hi> and by his witty wanders to impregnate and beget good wits with wonder of his learned worth, without cauſe or cautele, ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands ouer well approued Medicines with his Protean <hi>Quid pro quo,</hi> that for moſt part he diſables the <hi>Medicine</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:19071:11"/>
commanding ouer the <hi>Malady,</hi> and ſo not ſeldome fails of finding that good ſucceſſe to attend his Pragmatique permutations, which often crownes the conſtant courſe of the leſſe literate, but more humble Practitioner. But the true Artist, well knowing the pernitious iſſues of <hi>Empi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall</hi> pertinacie, and the fruitles vanitie of the <hi>Methodian</hi> his ſeeming all ſeeing perſpicacie, nor peremptorily confines himſelfe to his <hi>Probatums,</hi> nor deſignes change thereof but in rationall and iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious reſpect for proprietarie accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the caſe of the cure in Quest<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This is <hi>The Phyſician,</hi> the man that will for no cauſe (much leſſe in politique cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to vindicate ignorance from cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) abandon and leaue his Patient in deplorate diſeaſes, but be they paſt the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod</hi> of <hi>Cure</hi> before he be cald to counſell, or eſſentially or caſually incurable, will yet continue his carefull endeuours to recall and congregate the wandring <hi>Spirits</hi> to their <hi>Centers</hi> there to become quieſcent
<pb facs="tcp:19071:12"/>
and calme, carminate and compoſe the <hi>Animall Faculties</hi> in caſe of needfull exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, the better to enable the Patient to call vpon God, and recommend himſelfe to the <hi>Redeemer,</hi> &amp; to mitigate and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliate the <hi>Agonies</hi> and <hi>Pangs</hi> of <hi>Death,</hi> that they may not interrupt the cheerfull Anhelation and erning of the immortall Soule for <hi>Abrahams boſom-Imbrace;</hi> which heauenly happy end of diuine Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, imploring the Author and Actor of Phyſick (<hi>the endleſſe Deitie</hi>) may crown thy Cataſtrophe and mine vpon this mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dane Stage with conſolable cloſe, I end,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine vntill and after that End.
<hi>W. F.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:19071:12"/>
            <head>Panalaes Etymon.</head>
            <l>ANd why Panala? Is't cauſe all meere-Ale</l>
            <l>In ſight and taſte I ſeeme ſans other vale?</l>
            <l>Not ſo confin'd; I ſerue for Bread and Broth,</l>
            <l>Fell Thirſt and Hunger keene I cure them both.</l>
            <l>What's nutritiue, what t'Health or Dyet tends</l>
            <l>The little bulke I beare all comprehends.</l>
            <l>The languid Appetite I recreate,</l>
            <l>Famelique ſpirits richly ſaturate,</l>
            <l>Tracts fibrous for'th Mechanique t'operate</l>
            <l>With vap'rie Nutriment, I reſerate,</l>
            <l>The corp'rall parts eſſentially I nouriſh,</l>
            <l>Make th' Animalls effectually to flouriſh,</l>
            <l>Good ſpirits wing with viue and actiue vigors,</l>
            <l>Malefique void or calme diſcurſant rigors.</l>
            <l>I arme Man Cape à Pee gainſt Humor-iarrings,</l>
            <l>Whole troops of Sickneſſe quell or daunt their darrings,</l>
            <l>I cleere the phanſie from fanatique wanders,</l>
            <l>And Reaſon aye redeeme from falſe Maeanders.</l>
            <l>With bleſt Soules I beſt ſpirits ſymphonize,</l>
            <l>With pure ſoile ſeed prolifique ſympathize.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19071:13"/>Nor am I tyde to Ceres plain'ſt array</l>
            <l>Saue when I ſuit my ſelfe to low allay,</l>
            <l>Yet then ſometimes my habit I doe varie,</l>
            <l>And faire Pomona dights me for her Fairy.</l>
            <l>When Truage vnto courtly Dames I render</l>
            <l>In due habiliments my ſelfe I tender.</l>
            <l>Imbroydries faire from France and from Canaries</l>
            <l>Make-vp my mantle with what rich and rare is.</l>
            <l>Fraught with choice Indian Plants endeard enchaſe,</l>
            <l>Quaint vinie Trailes my Kyrtle entertrace.</l>
            <l>Flora the Globe rounds, vertues beſt infuſes</l>
            <l>To prime Extracts whoſe pride my Robe diffuſes.</l>
            <l>With Pearles and Iems my Buskins are imboſt,</l>
            <l>My flowry Chaplet round with Beauperes coſt.</l>
            <l>What Tethys yeelds, or pregnant Tellus claims</l>
            <l>Are ſubiects to my ſalutary aymes.</l>
            <l>The Hauen of Health to gaine with erning Sterne,</l>
            <l>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertumnus like my Garb and Gage I Pern,</l>
            <l>My forme, my face, my poſture and my pall,</l>
            <l>My corps contracting to dimenſions ſmall.</l>
            <l>Yet nis my Ballaſt leſſer then my Sayle,</l>
            <l>What's the Diſeaſe in which I not auaile?</l>
            <l>I am not tho, with doubtfull ſpirits fraught</l>
            <l>Which kill in future by impreſſions raught</l>
            <l>From dreadfull Minerals ſuruiuing Ghoſt,</l>
            <l>Though deſp'rate griefes with palliats they accoaſt.</l>
            <l>Ingredients of ſuſpect, each Drug that baſe is</l>
            <l>Abandon'd balke my preſence; Verdures graces,</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19071:13"/>Secure-boon-vertues beauie in my Bower,</l>
            <l>Where tainted Tinctures find nor place nor power.</l>
            <l>Nor am I deſtute of due aequipage,</l>
            <l>Though moſt I make my progreſſe without Page;</l>
            <l>Select Attendants and Aſſociats too</l>
            <l>Are preſt aye to performe what I bid doo.</l>
            <l>My Harbinger with high Herculean hand</l>
            <l>Th' Augean ſordid Stals, each ſtagnant Stand</l>
            <l>(Whoſe turgid groſſe Illuvies doth ſurround</l>
            <l>Mans Edifice with Soakages profound,</l>
            <l>Each Roome, each Cloſet, euen his lofty Turret,</l>
            <l>Taints and infeſts with vapours of ill Spirit)</l>
            <l>Doth clenſe and cleere, eliminating all</l>
            <l>That may my happy intertaine fore-ſtall.</l>
            <l>Both Land and Water-Leech attend my Traine,</l>
            <l>Riuers and Rils or full or foule to draine.</l>
            <l>Vſhers me conduct to each Part each Place</l>
            <l>Apert, opert, to what's of vſe of grace;</l>
            <l>(Not that I need ſuch Conuoy, ſaue for State,</l>
            <l>Sith porous Blinds I ſelfly penetrate)</l>
            <l>All which my choice Concomitants and I</l>
            <l>Corroborate, Repaire and Rectifie.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:19071:14"/>
            <head>Panalaes Encomion.</head>
            <l>WOuldſt thou the ſweets of Corporall Pleaſures reliſh?</l>
            <l>Of Touch, Taſt, Souſes all Delices cheriſh?</l>
            <l>Make coorſe home-fare more guſtfull to the Palats</l>
            <l>Than Feaſts of coſtly Cates with curious Sallets?</l>
            <l>With Banquet Phyſicke wouldſt thou Nature feaſt</l>
            <l>And actiue vigor in whole man inueſt?</l>
            <l>Wouldſt brooke ſecure th' Ayres various affects</l>
            <l>In Bodies foule, ſtraind Labors ſtrange effects?</l>
            <l>Wouldst ſcandalous diſeaſes palliate,</l>
            <l>Th'incurable ſubdue and mitigate?</l>
            <l>Wouldſt ſweet repoſe ſans turbid <hi>vaprie</hi> ſteames,</l>
            <l>Fantaſmaes fond and dire diſcurſant gleames?</l>
            <l>Wouldſt propagate vnto thy progenie</l>
            <l>Rich beautie, feature, health, bleſt ingenie?</l>
            <l>Wouldſt Reaſon, Wit, Inuention, Memory,</l>
            <l>And each power Animal well Rectifie,</l>
            <l>Wouldſt heauenly wiſe cleere, reſerat and poliſh,</l>
            <l>From whatſoere thoſe faculties demoliſh,</l>
            <l>All th'Organs by which their diſcurſiue vigor</l>
            <l>Moues, &amp; the braine imbright like pureſt mirror?</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19071:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>Wouldſt wean thy warping will from wandrings clews,</l>
            <l>Wing Soule to contemplate Seraphique Thews?</l>
            <l>Wouldſt Chimacterique ſeiſures ſuperſede,</l>
            <l>For longer Leaſe of Life produce thy Thread?</l>
            <l>Wouldſt healthfull liue, till almie Nature crowne</l>
            <l>Thy honourd Head with rev'rend Elds white downe?</l>
            <l>Wouldſt gently part-with Soule and Bodies Tye,</l>
            <l>And ſans diſtracting reluctation dye?</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Panalaes</hi> Loars imbrace, and thou'lt agnize</l>
            <l>Their ſeeds produce ſuch fruits; and breed a Prize</l>
            <l>Of more extent, rich vſe true valued worth</l>
            <l>Than my poore Quaeres can at full point forth.</l>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Sine numine nihil.</head>
               <l>MAy then <hi>Paul</hi> plant? <hi>Apollo</hi> water may?</l>
               <l>Nor he nor he, or th'one or th'other can</l>
               <l>If heauenly hand do not their handlings ſway;</l>
               <l>But ſay they can: vaine are the works of man</l>
               <l>If God bleſſe not: he onely giues encreaſes,</l>
               <l>Addle and idle, elſe deſignes all are:</l>
               <l>Say the Phyſician then againſt diſeaſes</l>
               <l>Preſcribe aright, and his preſcripts with care</l>
               <l>Th' Apothecar diſpenſing doth propine</l>
               <l>Vnto the ſicke, whoſe diligence obſerues</l>
               <l>Each due direct from Firſt vnto the Fine</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19071:15"/>And from the tracts of learned rules ne're ſwarues.</l>
               <l>Shall wit of man confine the Lord of Hoaſts</l>
               <l>T'attend his wiſe beheſts, intendments bleſſe,</l>
               <l>Seale with <hi>Amen,</hi> ſigne and make good his boaſts</l>
               <l>Of former Cures and Cans of ſure ſucceſſe?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Toto Caelo errat,</hi> who abſurdly doth</l>
               <l>Means meere humaine confide ſans main (heauens ſtroake)</l>
               <l>Abainleſſe bit, a cup of wholeſome broth,</l>
               <l>Vnbleſſed may man in a moment choake.</l>
               <l>How can great <hi>Galen</hi> then with confidence</l>
               <l>Of Phyſicke, euer ſafe preſcriptions giue?</l>
               <l>The wiſeſt fondly act, learn'd ſpeake Non-ſenſe,</l>
               <l>If Boones coeleſtiall bleſſe not each contriue.</l>
               <l>For without God, Mans wit no whit of good</l>
               <l>Can ere beget for Life or liueli-hood.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:19071:15"/>
            <head>The Contents of this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>OF the Quality and Nature of <hi>Ale,</hi> the moſt accuſtomed and accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date Body for the Baſe of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. <hi>Page. 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That <hi>Ale</hi> is a fit Body &amp; conuenient Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, by Infuſion to extract &amp; imbibe the Qualities, and virtues of Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, and to participate them to the Patient. <hi>6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What Body of Materials are accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date for Compoſition of <hi>Panala. 14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the particular paſſages obſeruable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Infuſion of the Fund or Bag. <hi>21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the praeparation of the Body before ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the <hi>Ale,</hi> &amp; when it is to be drunk. <hi>26</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:19071:16"/>
               <item>Of the Doſe, the manner of Taking, and the Continuance of vſing this <hi>Ale. 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Diet and Order obſeruable in the vſe of this medicinable <hi>Ale. 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the diuerſe and contemporary Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Panala. 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Obſeruations remarkable in the vſe and operation of the <hi>Ale. 56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The excellent Vertue of <hi>Panala</hi> in Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. <hi>65</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the excellent cautionary Virtues of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nala. 75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the cheape and preſt accommodations of <hi>Panala. 90</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A ſummary plaine Direction for the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients preparation and vſage of <hi>Pana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> with the Coſt and virtues thereof in generall. <hi>107</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19071:16"/>
            <head>Panala Medica.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the Quality and Nature of Ale, the moſt accuſtomed and moſt accommodate Body for the Baſe of this Compoſition.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know it is almoſt a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon receiued opinion, that <hi>Ale</hi> is a foggy ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſtuffe, clogging the ſtomacke, ſtuffing the Lungs and puffing vp the body with looſe fat, and flaſhie vnſound fleſh; Nor am I ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the Record of the ancient Poet (<hi>Henrieus Abrincenſis</hi>) who, in diſpleaſure to a Pot of <hi>Ale</hi> that perhaps pleaſed not his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, to caſt a foule aſperſion vpon this out more ancient drinke, falls into this furious rapture.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19071:17"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Neſcio quod Stygiae Monſtrum conforme paludi,</l>
                     <l>Ceruiſiam plerique vocant; nil ſpiſſius illa</l>
                     <l>Dum bibuur, nil clarius est dum mingitur: vndè</l>
                     <l>Conſtat, quòd multas faeces in ventre reliquit.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I know not I, what Monſter's this to th'eye,</l>
                     <l>This <hi>Ale,</hi> Mud-Mix, like Stoepe of fenny Styx,</l>
                     <l>More thicke no potion, more cleere's no Lotium:</l>
                     <l>Much dregs remaine i'th Body then 'tis plaine.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>Nor (to ſpeake the truth) is it altogether improbable, but there might in thoſe ruder Times, be found many Tunnes of ill condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>Ale,</hi> not vnworthy ſuch ſplenique Dictoes, before one Stand or Rundlet of pure ſtuffe worthy the Encomion of a Pot Poet. Haue we not yet euen in theſe daies many Mother-Foulſums, ſcarce worthie the bearing of <hi>Bourne,</hi> much leſſe the admittance for <hi>Brewing</hi> either <hi>Ale</hi> or <hi>Beere,</hi> which wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting both Art and induſtry requiſite for the Myſtery, marre no more <hi>Malt</hi> then they meddle with, and maſh <hi>Ale,</hi> more like a maſh or a medicine for a ſicke horſe then a potable liquor fit for a mans palate, ſtomacke or health? And ſurely, it was the <hi>Normans</hi> ill hap to haue his Cap fitted with a feculent cup of crude muddy <hi>Ale,</hi> to his morning Draught; and were not this able to moue the patience
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19071:17"/>
of a temperate man (much more the fiery choller of an Old <hi>Elderton,</hi> or a new <hi>Ale-Knight</hi>) any way regardfull of health, and cauſe him burſt into as boyſterous a <hi>Peece of Poetry,</hi> or other more vnmeaſurable paſſion? Howſoeuer, were this <hi>Cynicke Paſſage</hi> of the <hi>Poet,</hi> an earneſt Quarrell to a <hi>Pot</hi> of <hi>Ale,</hi> (vncouth, becauſe vnaccuſtom'd, to his <hi>wine waſht Palate,</hi>) or the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ent</hi> of a ieſting <hi>vaine of Wit,</hi> ſluced by ſome <hi>Slaſhes</hi> of the ſame <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> 'tis manifeſt to moſt Obſeruers, that ill brew'd <hi>Ale</hi> is commonly of a puddle ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, abounds with groſſe <hi>Phlegmaticke</hi> &amp; flatulent Humors, is heauie, and hurtfull to the <hi>Stomacke,</hi> ſtuffes the <hi>Ventricle,</hi> obſtructs the <hi>Meſaraick veines,</hi> the <hi>Liver, Lungs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſpleen, Reines, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>reters,</hi> and other inward veſſells and paſſages of the Body, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence puffes &amp; blowes-vp the whole bulke thereof with ſlimie, flaſhie and faeculent <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſts,</hi> ſhortens the Breath, breedes the <hi>Stone, Strangury, Gouts,</hi> and ſends vp to the <hi>Braine</hi> groſſe fumie Vapours, which offend the Nerues, &amp; diſtemper &amp; obſuſcate the Spirits, (the <hi>Mechanique Operators</hi> of and in all the Faculties of Man) with much detriment and dammage to all the Senſes both <hi>Internall</hi> and <hi>Externall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:19071:18"/>But let a neat houſ-wife, or cannie <hi>Ale wright,</hi> haue the handling of wholeſome <hi>Bourne,</hi> and ſound and mellow ſweet <hi>Malt,</hi> and you ſhall find, and will confeſſe, there is Art and Dexterity in this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon buſineſſe of Brewing: and that amongſt thoſe that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume vnto themſelues the Name of skilfull <hi>Ale-Brewers,</hi> there are more that miſſe the marke, for all their ſuppoſed <hi>Artifice,</hi> than with conſtant <hi>Maſtery</hi> make vp the true <hi>Mechanique</hi> of the <hi>Myſtery.</hi> For you ſhall then haue a neat Cup of rich nappy <hi>Ale,</hi> wel boyled, defecated &amp; cleared, that ſhall equall the beſt brewed Beere in tranſparence, pleaſe the moſt curious Palate with milde quickneſſe of reliſh, quench the Thirſt, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mect all the Inwards with rorid Iuice, helpe Concoction and diſtribution of Meat by 'its moderate Penetraction (eſpecially promoted with the Additament of the <hi>Vehiculum</hi> which beſt <hi>Aliſtraes</hi> boil with the <hi>woort,</hi> to wit, ſuch a proportion of Hop as giues no tact of bitterneſſe to the Taſte after the <hi>Ale</hi> growes drinkable) much furthering the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of the Parts, and by its ſubſtantiall <hi>ſucculence</hi> much nouriſh and corroborate the <hi>Corporall,</hi> and with ſpirituall vigour comfort the <hi>Animall Powers.</hi> This <hi>Ale</hi> will be better
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19071:18"/>
than <hi>beere</hi> for extenuated ſpare <hi>textures</hi> of <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> by reaſon of its more nutritiue Qualitie, and that without inconuenience to the <hi>Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lericke,</hi> for that it excretes and voides the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous humor</hi> by vrine and by Stoale; or to the <hi>Phlegmatique,</hi> becauſe it is not Obſtructiue. And for the Sanguine; it may well ſuite with ſuch Complexions, by reaſon of its moderate <hi>Heat</hi> and <hi>Moiſture</hi>; nor can it be incongruent to the Melancholike, in regard it diſsipates and ſpends fuliginous fumoſities and exhile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates the <hi>Spirits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such a Cup of pure Comfort, rich anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Ale</hi> (neither <hi>Lanted, Gummed,</hi> nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe <hi>ſophiſticated</hi>) finde many good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes which <hi>walke ere</hi> they waſh, for their Morning-Draught of true <hi>Darby,</hi> which, I dare be bold to ſay, had beene all ſufficient to haue induced the famous <hi>Baſilian, Foelix Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terus</hi> (had he happily euer plyed that Pot) to recant and retract his vnkinde cenſuring our <hi>Ceruiſia,</hi> for faetid <hi>ſmell,</hi> faſtidious <hi>Taſt,</hi> &amp; languid <hi>Strength,</hi> and to be as forward in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fording ſuch <hi>Noble Ale</hi> the Prize and praiſe of a <hi>Baſilique Beverage,</hi> as we are in giuing it the Attributes of <hi>Meat, Drinke</hi> and <hi>Cloth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19071:19"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <head type="sub">That <hi>Ale</hi> is a fit Body and conuenient liquor, by Infuſion to extract and imbibe the Qualities, and virtues of Ingredients, and to participate them to the Patient.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat Liquors may the more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by meere Infuſion, be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnated with the faculties of Simples &amp; other Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents of impight and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact <hi>ſubſtances,</hi> 'tis requiſite the <hi>Qualitie</hi> and <hi>Quantitie</hi> thereof bee both of them compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent: For the firſt; it muſt be either of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciding and penetrating <hi>Power,</hi> that, by peir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and entring into all <hi>Parts</hi> of the ſubiect <hi>Materialls,</hi> it may cut, attenuate, reſerate, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide &amp; diſſolue their compact &amp; concrete Iuices, and really alſo attract, ingeſt and ſuck into it ſelfe the pure <hi>eſſentiall formes</hi> (in which the chiefe efficacy of Medicinall force and virtue conſiſts) of their ſeuerall <hi>Natures</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from <hi>Earthly Feculency</hi>; Or of ſuch a <hi>Specifique</hi> meet and familiar and pleaſurable <hi>Eſſence,</hi> that by inſinuatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it may, (as it were) allure and intice them to infuſe and poure
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19071:19"/>
into it their beſt <hi>Spirits</hi> ſo oblectated and woone.</p>
               <p>For the ſecond; ſith <hi>Liquor</hi> is euermore <hi>Agent</hi> in this <hi>worke of Infuſion,</hi> it muſt bee of ſufficient <hi>Quantity</hi> to ſubdue and attract the <hi>Radicall humors</hi> and <hi>ſpirits</hi> of the <hi>Ingredients,</hi> becauſe a ſmall proportion is eaſily imbibed by the Bulk of the ſubiect <hi>Matter,</hi> and too much will bee too weakly tincted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, where a fit <hi>meane</hi> doth effectually draw-forth and attract the Iuices of the infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Body to a due <hi>Impregnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>Chymicke Extractions</hi>; the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Wine, Hot waters, diſtil'd waters</hi> and <hi>Raine waters</hi> are held appropriate to make infuſion. For <hi>Potions; wine, Hydromel, Oxymel, Brothes, Whey, Decoctions</hi> of attenuating Simples, are in requeſt.</p>
               <p>Now although <hi>Ale,</hi> by reaſon of its mild <hi>Taſt,</hi> may ſeeme to participate but of ſmall penetration, &amp; by conſequence be eſteem'd an vnfit <hi>Liquor</hi> to macerate <hi>Ingredients,</hi> and extract their virtues by Infuſion; yet by its operation and effects in the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Braine,</hi> and by the piercing and combuſtible <hi>Hot waters</hi> drawne from thence, it may well bee collected and concluded, that it is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>ſubtile</hi> and <hi>perſant Spirits</hi> lurking and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19071:20"/>
lying hid and veiled vnder the mild ſoft <hi>Mask</hi> of its <hi>Oleaginous Succulence,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a <hi>Liquor</hi> no way improper, but a very ſpecifique and fit Body for the <hi>Infuſion</hi> of moſt ſorts of <hi>Ingredients,</hi> both for gaining and retaining their virtues within it ſelfe, and for preſt and effectuall Participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them. Howſoeuer; indubitate <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience (veriſſima artis Magiſtra)</hi> truly tells and teaches, both <hi>Methodiſt</hi> and <hi>Empirique,</hi> that ſtrong right-brewed <hi>Ale,</hi> well wrought vp with <hi>Yest,</hi> and duly tunned vp to fit <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients,</hi> (yea to ſolid and compact <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,</hi> euen to a <hi>Body</hi> impenetrable by <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans</hi> ſharpeſt (not <hi>hotteſt) Tooles,</hi> and more condenſe and obdurate than hardeſt woods) ſo macerates, penetrates and workes vpon their <hi>ſubſtantiall Formes</hi> by <hi>Fermentation,</hi> and <hi>Digeſtion,</hi> through force and efficacy of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate <hi>heat</hi> and ſpecifique <hi>moiſture</hi> (neither diſsipating the <hi>Spirits</hi> nor dulling their <hi>vigor,</hi> but rather fortifying both by ſtirring-vp and reducing their <hi>Calidum Innatum</hi> into <hi>Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Cooperatiue</hi>) inſinuating with <hi>ſupple ioynts, and ſpirituall Iuices</hi> into euery <hi>Cauitie</hi> &amp; Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirable Ouerture of euery of them, that it ſubtilizes their inſpiſſat thicke <hi>humors,</hi> reſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates the recluſe <hi>Cloſets</hi> of their impacted
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19071:20"/>
                  <hi>Spiris,</hi> concocts all <hi>Crudities</hi> reſiding in their <hi>Iuices,</hi> attempers and mitigates <hi>Bitterneſſe,</hi> corrects aliene <hi>Qualities,</hi> digeſts, incides, and diuides <hi>Concretions,</hi> and by disbanding and ſecluding ſome <hi>Heterogenities</hi> to the ſides of the <hi>veſſell,</hi> by <hi>Precipitation</hi> of the feculent, heauie and earthy to the <hi>Sediment,</hi> and by <hi>Eleuation</hi> and lifting-vp the <hi>light Refuſe</hi> or excreat and <hi>dead Remaine</hi> with the <hi>Spumie froth</hi> to the <hi>Swim</hi> or <hi>Superficies,</hi> ſeparates and amandates the ſecluded <hi>Faeces,</hi> and <hi>Impure Purgaments,</hi> couching in their inward <hi>Pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tralia,</hi> quite from the <hi>Region</hi> of its <hi>Depurated Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus in few <hi>Daies,</hi> (ſeuen or more accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>ſeaſon</hi> of the <hi>weather,</hi> haſtning or foreſlowing the <hi>Fining</hi>) it <hi>Clarifies</hi> and <hi>puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies</hi> its owne <hi>Body,</hi> and really and effectually impregnates it <hi>ſelfe</hi> (by alliciating and attrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting) with the pure and ſincere <hi>Tinctures</hi> and <hi>Faculties</hi> of the infuſed <hi>Materialls,</hi> and with it <hi>vehiculates,</hi> caries, communicates and diffuſes their <hi>virtues</hi> and <hi>powers</hi> into all <hi>parts,</hi> of the <hi>Propinors</hi> or <hi>Receiuers Body,</hi> ſecret and remote. And this <hi>Diſtribution</hi> is effectuated and wrought by this <hi>Liquor,</hi> partly through its liquid proprietarie <hi>Body,</hi> ſpecificated by th'acquiſite <hi>Qualitie</hi> of Penetration, deriued
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19071:21"/>
from attenuating <hi>Ingredients,</hi> and partly by the cooperating of oblectated <hi>Nature,</hi> which is euer eager to attract and imbrace whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer participates of a <hi>familiar, ſucculent</hi> and <hi>nutritiue ſubſtance,</hi> as well-brewed <hi>Ale</hi> is well approued to doe, in due <hi>degrees</hi> of good <hi>Proportion</hi> ſuiting with its ſtrength of <hi>Malt</hi> and <hi>Quantity</hi> of <hi>Ale,</hi> according to which the <hi>Extraction</hi> of <hi>Spirits</hi> from the infuſed Maſſe, is euermore made reſpectiuely. For the <hi>Quale</hi> and <hi>Quantum</hi> (ioyntly conſidered) of <hi>Liquors</hi> infuſiue, bound and limit their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptivities</hi> of extracted <hi>Impregnances,</hi> as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore intimated.</p>
               <p>Beſides that; this <hi>Panala,</hi> by reaſon of its apt <hi>forme</hi> and <hi>proprietie,</hi> and conuenient <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration,</hi> together with the <hi>fitneſſe</hi> of the <hi>veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell,</hi> and its owne <hi>Crowning</hi> and <hi>Mantling</hi> it <hi>ſelfe</hi> all ouer with the <hi>Clothing</hi> or <hi>Couer</hi> of <hi>Yeſt,</hi> retaines and preſerues euen the ſubtile and halable <hi>Spirits</hi> of euery <hi>Ingredient,</hi> mixed and fixed with both their <hi>radical Humidums,</hi> intire, exempt and free from <hi>Evaporation,</hi> and its owne <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Quicknes</hi> from euanid <hi>flatnes</hi> &amp; dead <hi>ſowring,</hi> much better than moſt <hi>Liquors</hi> can doe, yea then <hi>Wine,</hi> which, though it be <hi>Patent</hi> in Attraction, is more <hi>Impotent</hi> in <hi>Retention,</hi> by reaſon that the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:19071:21"/>
are <hi>Volatile</hi> and nothing ſo <hi>Glutinous</hi> and <hi>Condenſate</hi> as thoſe of <hi>Ale</hi>; whereas <hi>decoctions,</hi> (though they haue their proper and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable <hi>vſes,</hi> being performed according to <hi>Art</hi> in a <hi>cloſe or double veſſell,</hi> which few <hi>Patients</hi> are curious in) doe commonly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hale, waſte and ſpend the ſubtile <hi>Spirits</hi> of diuers <hi>Materialls,</hi> (moſt of all of moſt <hi>Pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi>) and extract, ingeſt and retaine the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terogene,</hi> flatuous and earthy <hi>parts</hi> of them and of others.</p>
               <p>He that denies or doubts of this <hi>Penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue</hi> and <hi>extractiue force</hi> of ſuch <hi>Infuſions,</hi> by the meere efficacie of their inward <hi>Fire of Nature</hi> without helpe of forraigne <hi>Heat,</hi> let him drinke a <hi>Cup</hi> of ſuch <hi>Liquor</hi> after three daies (or <hi>Wine</hi> after twelue houres) <hi>Infuſe</hi> in <hi>Calice Chymico,</hi> and his <hi>Stomacke</hi> will not ſo much tell <hi>Him,</hi> that <hi>venter non habet aures,</hi> as vellicate them for not being more <hi>Beleeuing Ones.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now if any <hi>Man,</hi> wilfully wedded to a <hi>ſelfe-conceit</hi> or ſingularity of opinion, doe yet ſuſpect or will obiect, that <hi>Ale</hi> (the <hi>Baſe</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> of this <hi>Panala</hi>) more obſtructs the <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages</hi> and puffes-vp full <hi>Bodies</hi> than <hi>Beere:</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit this were granted, tis no impeach to the <hi>Potion,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Ingredience</hi> of the <hi>Bagge</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:19071:22"/>
hath <hi>Power</hi> to transforme <hi>Liquors</hi> naturally <hi>Obſtructiue</hi> to <hi>Deoppilatiue,</hi> which doth farre tranſcend and ſurperſede that of the ambitious <hi>Incoline,</hi> the aſpiring <hi>Hop,</hi> ayming to reach the <hi>Head</hi> of the higheſt <hi>Pole,</hi> (and the <hi>Pole</hi> of the <hi>Head</hi>) and to baniſh <hi>This an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Ale,</hi> which in the 6. of <hi>Edward</hi> the 4. (ſome 147. yeares agoe) was in ſuch requeſt, that the Feaſt for th'inſtallment of <hi>Nevill</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> and Chancellor of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> was conſtantly affirmed to bee furniſht with 100 <hi>Tuns</hi> of <hi>Wine,</hi> and 300 of <hi>Ale,</hi> but not one Barrell of <hi>Beere.</hi> Yet for <hi>Stomackes</hi> that brooke not <hi>Ale,</hi> they may with conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencie make the <hi>Infuſion</hi> in <hi>Beere</hi> (adding more <hi>Raiſons</hi> to palliate the bitterneſſe) which hath worthily gain'd the <hi>Repute</hi> of a wholſome <hi>drink,</hi> aſwel for many medicinable <hi>Qualities,</hi> as for quenching <hi>Thirſt,</hi> inſomuch that the now <hi>Raritie</hi> of <hi>Leapries</hi> here, where they were frequent in former times, is attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to <hi>Beere,</hi> in regard of the <hi>Hop,</hi> which hath ſpeciall <hi>Faculties</hi> both <hi>Diuretique</hi> and <hi>Deoppilatiue,</hi> whereby it cleanſes the <hi>Blood</hi> from all corrupt humours, and by excreting <hi>yellow choller</hi> makes the <hi>Body</hi> ſoluble, and all this without heating it, or offending the <hi>head</hi> with fumes, if the <hi>Beere</hi> be not ouerhopt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19071:22"/>
nor toucht vntill the <hi>Bitterneſſe</hi> bee digeſted and worne out.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wine</hi> alſo (chiefly the <hi>White) Pyrie,</hi> and <hi>Cyder</hi> are very good for this purpoſe, eſpecially at the time of <hi>Vintage.</hi> But gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally <hi>Ale</hi> and <hi>Beere</hi> are the moſt appropriate <hi>Liquors</hi> to theſe <hi>parts</hi> for the <hi>baſe</hi> of this <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,</hi> both by reaſon of their <hi>natiue and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar accomodation</hi> to our <hi>Bodies,</hi> and for that they may be prepared at any time, for actiue <hi>Operation</hi> vpon the <hi>Ingredients,</hi> which is moſt powerfully and effectually performed by the <hi>Ebullition</hi> or reworking of the <hi>Liquor</hi> in the <hi>veſſell</hi> after barrelling or tunning vp, without any that <hi>Loſſe</hi> or <hi>Diminution</hi> of their owne <hi>Spirits</hi> or <hi>vigours</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> would ineuitably enſue in too great a proportion, if theſe or other <hi>Liquors</hi> once digeſted and fined ſhould bee drawne out for <hi>Infuſions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>Hydromell, Mellicrate, Metheglin,</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made-<hi>Drinks,</hi> they may bee accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated againſt any prefixed time like <hi>Ale</hi> or <hi>Beere,</hi> but with caution of what <hi>Materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als,</hi> leſt you croſſe the <hi>Intention</hi> or operatiue <hi>Qualities</hi> of the <hi>Bag</hi> or <hi>Compoſition.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:19071:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <head type="sub">What Bodie of Materials are accommodate for Compoſition of <hi>Panala.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Imples</hi> and other <hi>Subſtances</hi> in generall, which by drying in the <hi>Shade,</hi> or by other due ſiccation, are quit of their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous <hi>Humidity,</hi> but retei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their <hi>Verdures</hi> or naturall <hi>Gloſſe,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſound and clenſed from all putrified and dead parts, and groſly bruiſed or punned, or rather ſmall cut or ſhred, that they may throughly imbibe and receiue the <hi>Liquor</hi> for effectuall working vpon them by <hi>macerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> are fitter for <hi>Infuſions,</hi> than ſuch as ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſuperfluities of <hi>Moiſture</hi> incorporate in them before they be dryed. For the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous and aliene <hi>Humidity,</hi> ſtill inherent in their <hi>Bodies,</hi> ſhuts out and hinders the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary peircing and inſinuating of the <hi>Liquor</hi> into their abſtruſe Inwards; yet the ſhiced &amp; contuſed <hi>Subſtances,</hi> eſpecially the ſtrained <hi>Iuices</hi> of ſome greene or moiſt <hi>Simples</hi> or <hi>Drugges,</hi> are to good purpoſe many times infuſed in this caſe, becauſe they doe eaſily
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19071:23"/>
incorporate and communicate their <hi>ſuccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> and virtues with the <hi>Liquor,</hi> and the ſtrength and <hi>Ebullition</hi> of it doth concoct and digeſt their Crudities.</p>
               <p>But I haue of <hi>Dry Ingredients</hi> (ſo many as may well admit ſuch preparation) compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed my <hi>Fund</hi> or <hi>Bagg,</hi> fully to anſwer the <hi>Scope</hi> and <hi>Drift</hi> of my <hi>Intention,</hi> which is truly to make good vnto the diligent <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,</hi> all the <hi>Attributes</hi> I giue it, how great and exceeding numerous ſoeuer they may ſeeme to bee: Howſoeuer other <hi>Bagges</hi> may <hi>male audire</hi> of many men for Raking, heating, drying and exhauſting their <hi>Bodies,</hi> chiefly if they be of a feeble and weake conſtitution. This fault is in the <hi>Phyſitian</hi> which <hi>Emperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi> &amp; indiſcreetly compounds it of ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Purgers</hi> and intemperate <hi>Simples,</hi> not in the <hi>Bag:</hi> Tis not the outward, but the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Forme</hi> or <hi>Compoſure,</hi> that commends or diſcommends euery <hi>Medicine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some will in no ſort admit the ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of <hi>Raiſons</hi> of the <hi>Sunne</hi> into ſuch like Infuſions, affirming they would to ſmall purpoſe (other than to increaſe the <hi>Bulke</hi> of the <hi>Bagge,</hi> lye ſobbing and ſoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the <hi>Liquor,</hi> but rather approue the <hi>Ingredience</hi> of the ſtrained <hi>Iuice,</hi> drawne out
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19071:24"/>
with ſome of the <hi>Ale,</hi> or of the cloſing of the <hi>Cup</hi> with halfe a ſcore of them, their ſtones caſt away. But though the <hi>Additament</hi> of this ſucculent <hi>Fruit</hi> ſeemes to croſſe the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> or <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Infuſion,</hi> yet may their Eunuch-ſeruice be worthily admitted the <hi>preſence</hi> of the greateſt <hi>Prince,</hi> both chaſt <hi>Dians,</hi> and iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <hi>Ottomans.</hi> For being waſht, diſplayd, and diskerneld, and then cloſed againe and put into the veſſell, the <hi>Ale</hi> doth with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite <hi>Extraction</hi> ſo effectually work-vpon their diſſoluble <hi>Concretions,</hi> that in <hi>three daies</hi> ſpace it eleuates, lifts and caries them vp from its <hi>Sediment</hi> or <hi>Bottome</hi> to the <hi>Superficies</hi> or <hi>Swim</hi> (demonſtrable in a <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ioll Glaſſe</hi>) dead and inſipid, hauing left all their <hi>Dulcor,</hi> and ſweet reliſh, with ſome third part of their <hi>poize</hi> (if reduced to former <hi>Drines) in depoſito</hi> with the <hi>Liquor,</hi> and who doubts, but that together with their concrete <hi>Sweets,</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lementary ſpiſſitude,</hi> their intire <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irtues</hi> are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo extracted and diffuſed in ſolution into the <hi>Body</hi> of the <hi>Infuſion?</hi> I haue not therefore reiected them, but for their manifold and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar <hi>Virtues</hi> preſented in pleaſant ſuccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to the comfort of the <hi>naturall Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> and eſpecially vnto the <hi>Parenchyma He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patis</hi> whereunto they are ſo gratefull, profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19071:24"/>
and ſpecifique (<hi>totius ſubſtantiae propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etate</hi>) that they may be ſtiled the <hi>Life of the Liuer (Epatis quaſi anima perhibeantur,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Sennertus</hi>) giuen them a large <hi>patent</hi> for <hi>place</hi> in my <hi>Panala.</hi> But I oft leaue them forth of the <hi>Bag</hi> for the <hi>patient</hi> to put freſh and looſe into the <hi>Ale</hi> to <hi>three ounces</hi> at leaſt. For the <hi>aſtriction</hi> of their kirnels, <hi>Grapes</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part none to <hi>White Wine</hi>; and what doth this <hi>Infuſion</hi> extract from ſuch vnbroken <hi>ſhellie Cruſts,</hi> more than doth the <hi>Wine preſſe? Et hoc aliquid nihil eſt,</hi> ſo that they may <hi>ſans</hi> ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be whole (but ſlit) caſt into the <hi>Caske,</hi> and ſo much the rather, becauſe ſome proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a binding <hi>Qualitie</hi> doth better ſuch <hi>purging Diet Drinks</hi>: Yet I leaue them to the <hi>patient</hi> to vſe <hi>ad libitum. Myrobalans, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marinds</hi> and <hi>Sebeſtens</hi> may claime like priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for <hi>Admittance</hi> and <hi>vſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>Drugges</hi> commonly <hi>carioſa non cara,</hi> knowne to bee deadly-dull <hi>ſlugs</hi> of doubtfull kinde, but manifeſtly auerſe to the <hi>ventricle</hi> (whoſe dammage in all <hi>Medications,</hi> chiefly in long or continued courſes for cures, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is <hi>totius corporis promptuarium,</hi> both for feeding the body and its ſicknes with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crementitious, flatulent &amp; nauſeous <hi>Humidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> muſt with particular intention be carefully
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19071:25"/>
preuented) eſpecially when the <hi>Humors,</hi> brought into commotion by the <hi>Medicine,</hi> infeſt the <hi>Stomacke</hi> with their <hi>confluence,</hi> I could not by <hi>Motiue</hi> of <hi>Empiricall common vſe</hi> be induced to giue admittance to their <hi>Ingredience</hi> here, where I would not haue the happy <hi>Harmony</hi> of moſt ſalutary <hi>Simples</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned or once toucht with any manner of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach or tact by any the leaſt diſcordant <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terogenity,</hi> let who will magnifie the <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibancke Mixtures</hi> of others, that for <hi>cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> admit them. To <hi>ſuperſede</hi> all ſuch bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Imputations,</hi> the profitable <hi>cheapneſſe</hi> of this dangerous <hi>Simple,</hi> is abandond my <hi>Bag,</hi> and in <hi>place</hi> thereof, I entertaine <hi>One</hi> well approued (by <hi>price</hi> and frequent <hi>practice</hi>) of the beſt <hi>Phyſitians</hi> for excellent <hi>Operation,</hi> exempt from <hi>cenſure</hi> and made famous for <hi>Attributes</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irtues</hi> and good <hi>Effects, Purgatiue</hi> and <hi>corroboratiue,</hi> of <hi>Rheubarbe</hi> and <hi>Agarick,</hi> and this by the teſtimonie of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne Claſſicke Authors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe of the <hi>Heat</hi> and <hi>Drineſſe,</hi> by ſome ſuſpected to bee in <hi>Guaiacum,</hi> I had vtterly diſclaimed it for all its <hi>Sanctimonie,</hi> ſaue that the oyly ſubſtance (<hi>praepinguis &amp; reſinacea</hi>) chiefly in the blacke <hi>Heart</hi> (euen of the old <hi>Stock</hi>) ſaies it participates of a cerain <hi>moiſture,</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:19071:25"/>
whereby it conſerues and nouriſhes the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midum primigenium</hi> of the <hi>Intrals</hi> and <hi>ſolid parts, ventrem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> lubricu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> facit praeterquam dum ſudores promoventur,</hi> and yet with aſtringent drineſſe corroborates the moiſt, looſe and nauſeous <hi>Stomack,</hi> and all other the <hi>veſſells.</hi> For theſe <hi>virtues</hi> and for its further great <hi>Fame</hi> (ſee <hi>Fernelius</hi> and <hi>Montanus,</hi> who neuer had the young tendrels of the two yeere old <hi>Tree,</hi> to which ſome aſcribe the moſt <hi>Vertue</hi>) and <hi>Bezoardique Quality,</hi> in.which it hath the <hi>Power</hi> of an <hi>Antidote,</hi> directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing and oppugning putrid <hi>Contagions,</hi> I haue diſpenſed with ſome proportionable degree of its <hi>Ingredience,</hi> yet but as a <hi>Quarter Maſter,</hi> vnder command of a temperate, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and moſt pretious <hi>ſpecifique,</hi> to mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate all <hi>exceſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But for <hi>China,</hi> the coſtly and trauell'd <hi>Courtier, He</hi> is wholly caſhierd both <hi>Fund</hi> and <hi>Caske,</hi> for all his <hi>Caſh-worth,</hi> becauſe I find <hi>Him,</hi> like many <hi>Auliques,</hi> meere <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement,</hi> rich in <hi>promiſes,</hi> poore in <hi>performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> beſides that <hi>Renodaeus</hi> diſallowes <hi>Him</hi> in the ſicke of <hi>Conſumptions,</hi> and <hi>Hucchen</hi> ſayes <hi>He</hi> is vnwholſome for the <hi>Sound.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for that all ſorts of <hi>Phyſicke,</hi> but moſt of all, all extended <hi>courſes</hi> of <hi>Medication</hi> (as
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19071:26"/>
this is) doe much affect and work vpon the <hi>primarie Inſtruments</hi> of <hi>Concoctions,</hi> the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch</hi> of the <hi>belly,</hi> and <hi>Fountaine</hi> of <hi>Blood,</hi> the <hi>Stomacke</hi> and the <hi>Liver</hi>; I haue for their ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall <hi>comfort</hi> and <hi>Corroboration</hi> furniſht the <hi>Fund</hi> or <hi>Bag</hi> with ſingular and moſt ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique <hi>Stomatiques</hi> and <hi>Hepatiques.</hi> Nor are the <hi>principall parts</hi> any way neglected; <hi>Here</hi> haue you a ſpecifique <hi>Bezoardique</hi> to coole and corroborate the <hi>vitall ſpirits,</hi> and an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Cephalique</hi> to fortifie the <hi>animal,</hi> ſo that nor <hi>Heart</hi> nor <hi>Head</hi> want their <hi>munition</hi> to maintaine valid and conſtant incoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters againſt <hi>diſeaſes</hi>; not that the inherent malignity of any <hi>Ingredient</hi> neceſſitates ſuch fortification, but to accommodate and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temper <hi>Heaters</hi> with <hi>Coolers,</hi> and <hi>Reſoluers</hi> and <hi>Openers</hi> with ſtrong Roborators and mild Aſtringents, according to <hi>Quercetan</hi> from <hi>Galen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:19071:26"/>
               <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the particular paſſages obſeruable about the Infuſion of the Fund or Bag.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue now enlarged and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned the <hi>Bag</hi> of <hi>Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients</hi> to <hi>Panala</hi> for two <hi>Gallons</hi> (or twelue wine quarts) of <hi>Ale,</hi> that it may furniſh <hi>man</hi> and <hi>wife</hi> for one weeke, or one <hi>patient</hi> for two. This is a <hi>bottle</hi> more than former vſe, and I hold it the meane and beſt proportion for moſt part to be obſerued, both for extracting, preſeruing and participating the <hi>Qualities</hi> of the <hi>Ingredience.</hi> But this <hi>quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity</hi> of the <hi>Liquor</hi> may be ſomewhat augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or diminiſhed, &amp; the <hi>potion</hi> made ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger or weaker of <hi>Medicinable Qualities,</hi> to fit the <hi>affections</hi> of ſeuerall <hi>Stomackes,</hi> the <hi>Cuſtome</hi> of little or larger <hi>drinking,</hi> or other intendments.</p>
               <p>An ordinary <hi>Stand, Steine</hi> or <hi>Ale Can</hi> with a <hi>Tap-hole,</hi> will be an apt <hi>veſſell</hi> to ſerue well for the <hi>Infuſion,</hi> prouided there bee alwayes <hi>care</hi> to keepe it cloſe couered: but a ſmall <hi>Rundlet,</hi> fitly bungd for <hi>Receipt</hi> of the <hi>Bagge,</hi> will beſt of all retaine and conſerue the <hi>Life</hi> and quicke <hi>Reliſh</hi> of the <hi>Liquor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:19071:27"/>The <hi>Fund</hi> or <hi>Compoſition</hi> of <hi>Ingredients,</hi> neatly made vp and included in a <hi>Bag</hi> of fine <hi>Bolter ſtuffe,</hi> muſt be ſuncke into the <hi>veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell,</hi> with a <hi>Peble ſtone,</hi> or with ſome other <hi>Poize,</hi> or conſtantly kept downe with forked ſtickes (<hi>Oake</hi> and <hi>Ivie</hi> much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue the wholſomenes of the <hi>Drinke</hi>) or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther force, to preuent its riſing vp to the <hi>Breaking</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> of the <hi>Yest,</hi> becauſe ſuch a <hi>breach</hi> in open veſſels, would bee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious to this <hi>Panala,</hi> as the taking of <hi>vent,</hi> or <hi>winde</hi> is vnto <hi>wine</hi> or other <hi>Liquors</hi> by venting out and evaporating their <hi>ſpirits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ale</hi> or <hi>Beere</hi> muſt be well mixt and wrought vp with good ſtore of <hi>Yest</hi> to crowne and keepe it from expenſe of <hi>ſpirits,</hi> and the <hi>yeſting</hi> in open <hi>veſſells</hi> is requiſite to be renewed once in 7. <hi>Daies</hi>; for the ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the <hi>Yest</hi> turnes the <hi>Drinke</hi> with its tartneſſe, but ſhift of <hi>yest</hi> preſerues the <hi>ſpirit</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> of the <hi>Liquor</hi> intire, and the <hi>Ale</hi> freſh and quicke for a <hi>Month</hi> or more <hi>Time</hi> of <hi>Drinking.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fitteſt and only <hi>Seaſon</hi> to make this <hi>Infuſion,</hi> is the vſuall <hi>Time</hi> of the ordinary <hi>Tunning-vp</hi> of the <hi>Drinke,</hi> that by <hi>Ebullition, working</hi> and <hi>digeſtion</hi> in the <hi>veſſell</hi> through its inward <hi>Heat</hi> of the <hi>fire</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> it may ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19071:27"/>
worke vpon, macerate and ingeſt the concrete <hi>Iuices</hi> and <hi>Faculties</hi> of the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect matter</hi>; and for better libertie of <hi>working,</hi> the <hi>Rundlet</hi> may haue ſome houre-<hi>Vent</hi> after the <hi>Liquor</hi> is tun'd into it, but then it muſt be bunged vp cloſe. For placing the <hi>veſſell</hi> of <hi>Liquor</hi> where it may receiue the <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit</hi> of accidentall or <hi>forraigne Heat,</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the <hi>Operation</hi> vpon the <hi>Ingredients,</hi> the <hi>force</hi> and <hi>efficacy</hi> of the inward and <hi>ſelfe</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained <hi>Calidum Innatum</hi> or inbred <hi>Heat</hi> of this <hi>Liquor,</hi> is all ſufficient for production of perfect <hi>maceration</hi> of the infuſed <hi>Materialls,</hi> ſo that <hi>Cellars</hi> which preſerue <hi>Wine</hi> &amp; <hi>Beere,</hi> ſerue aſwell for this as for them; the like doe other <hi>cloſe Roomes,</hi> which are exempt from the <hi>Extreames</hi> of diſtemper'd <hi>Seaſons,</hi> no leſſe from the <hi>ſpirit</hi> exhaling <hi>Summer Heats</hi> and others (though they clarifie the <hi>Remnants</hi>) then from the chilling and killing <hi>rigour</hi> of <hi>Winter,</hi> although a qualified <hi>cold,</hi> congregates and preſerues the <hi>Spirits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the continuance of the <hi>Infuſion:</hi> The common <hi>practice</hi> in like <hi>Operations,</hi> is neuer to ſtraine nor ſtirre the <hi>Fund</hi> or <hi>Bag,</hi> vntill all the <hi>Drinke</hi> be ſpent; but it is full ſufficient (for matter of evacuating <hi>Operation</hi> eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) to infuſe it, till there bee made a perfect
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19071:28"/>
                  <hi>Fermentation</hi> or <hi>Digeſtion</hi> of the continent <hi>Maſſe</hi> of <hi>Ingredients,</hi> that the <hi>Ale</hi> being ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impregnated with the <hi>proprieties</hi> illiciated or ingeſted from them, there may in the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> of the <hi>Liquor</hi> be bred and brought forth a new <hi>Nature,</hi> fully participating, in one <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogene</hi> and intire <hi>Body,</hi> of natiue and acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite <hi>Qualities,</hi> its owne and the <hi>Ingredients.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Three Dayes</hi> continuance is a competent <hi>Time</hi> for the <hi>Infuſion</hi> to extract the <hi>purgatiue Faculties</hi> of the <hi>Bag,</hi> before which ſpace to begin <hi>Drinking</hi> thereof, to auoid ſowring and pricking, is a poore tricke of <hi>preuention.</hi> But if you deferre the broaching <hi>thrice three daies</hi> or more, the <hi>Drinke</hi> will bee better depured and much more pleaſant both in <hi>Sight</hi> and <hi>Taſte,</hi> without impeach to the <hi>Evacuatiue O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration,</hi> beſides that it thereby becomes more impregnate and imbibes its whole <hi>Dimenſum</hi> both of <hi>Evacuatiue</hi> and <hi>Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Virtues:</hi> therefore the beſt <hi>Index</hi> for <hi>Broaching Panala</hi> is the <hi>Teſt</hi> of perfect <hi>Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My <hi>Cuſtome</hi> and <hi>Rule</hi> for curious <hi>palats,</hi> is to direct, that after foure or fiue <hi>Dayes Infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> the <hi>Ale</hi> bee all drawne into <hi>Bottles</hi> and <hi>Corkt,</hi> and kept like vſuall <hi>Bottle-Ale</hi>; for by this meanes it is neatly preſerued fortie
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19071:28"/>
dayes, and more if need, coole, perfect and intire in <hi>Taſt</hi> and <hi>Virtue</hi> to the laſt <hi>Cup.</hi> This is the beſt courſe for frugall <hi>keepe</hi> and huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding the <hi>Potion</hi>; for ſo the <hi>Bagge</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes free for a <hi>ſecond Infuſion,</hi> either by <hi>Dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the <hi>Ingredients</hi> againſt <hi>halfe</hi> or <hi>two thirds</hi> of the <hi>Ale</hi> be ſpent, or by immediate <hi>Stray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> and reinfuſing the ſame into freſh <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor</hi> for <hi>Meal-drinke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To make it drinke coole, freſh and quicke in the hotteſt <hi>Summer,</hi> hang it <hi>bottled</hi> in a deepe <hi>Well</hi> a little aboue the <hi>Water,</hi> twelue or foureteene dayes, and you haue your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. For the <hi>cold vapour</hi> of the <hi>water</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues the <hi>Ale</hi> from <hi>Exhalation</hi> of the <hi>Spirits,</hi> and alſo <hi>irritates</hi> and makes them vigorous, whereby they incorporate all parts of the <hi>Liquor</hi> in more perfection: The like may be done at any time and that in the <hi>Rundlet</hi> it ſelfe to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:19071:29"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the praeparation of the Body before taking the Ale, and when it is to be drunke.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Anala,</hi> together with its <hi>Purgatiue Quality,</hi> doth ſo reſerate and open the <hi>Ports and Paſſages</hi> of the <hi>corporall <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſſels,</hi> ſo m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turate and make fluent the <hi>Humours,</hi> and ſo ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually performe all the <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ces</hi> of a good <hi>Preparatiue,</hi> that, before the vſe thereof, there ſeldome needs any other <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> in that kinde; yet in caſe the <hi>Patient</hi> be accuſtomed to morning <hi>ejacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations or ſprings of watry Humors</hi> or vitious <hi>Contents</hi> floating in, or diſturbing the <hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach,</hi> it is expedient, before the <hi>drinking</hi> of this <hi>Panala,</hi> for <hi>praeparation</hi> of the <hi>Ventricle</hi> (to receiue, not of the <hi>Humours</hi> to obey, the <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine</hi>) by gentle prouocation thereof with a <hi>ſprig</hi> of <hi>Roſemary,</hi> or a feather, agitated about the <hi>roofe</hi> of the <hi>Mouth</hi> and <hi>roots</hi> of the <hi>Tongue,</hi> to cauſe eiaculation, or at leaſt ſome expuition or fluxe of liquid <hi>Humors.</hi> Thoſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19071:29"/>
                  <hi>Patients</hi> which doe not affect this practice, although the affections of their <hi>Stomacks</hi> craue the like, may doe well, ſome halfe houre before the Potion, to eate a ſmall <hi>Toſt</hi> of light houſhold bread, rubd-ouer with a little <hi>Table Salt,</hi> to remedy the fluctuating of the raw <hi>phlegmatique recrements,</hi> and to digeſt and conſume the <hi>crudities</hi> of the <hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For other <hi>helpes</hi> of <hi>conuoy</hi> into the <hi>Body,</hi> and all the inward <hi>penetralia</hi> of the <hi>pallace</hi> of the <hi>Microcoſme, Panala</hi> is ſo gratious and ſo potent an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> (a <hi>Vehicle</hi> to <hi>powders, pills, electuaries</hi>) there needs no forraine <hi>vehicula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> where euery <hi>recluſe,</hi> with ready expanſe, inuites her welcome <hi>entrance</hi> and intertaine into each <hi>preſence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Touching the <hi>time</hi> for ſelect <hi>vſage</hi> of this <hi>potion:</hi> The <hi>Spring</hi> of the <hi>yeere</hi> is the fitteſt <hi>ſeaſon</hi> of all other, for this and for all other <hi>courſes</hi> of <hi>medication,</hi> becauſe it is the moſt temperate and moſt wholeſome; beſides that, then the <hi>blood</hi> moſt encreaſes, (as <hi>ſap</hi> in <hi>vegetables</hi>) and the recreated <hi>ſpirits</hi> are moſt <hi>actiue</hi> in <hi>vigorous rotations,</hi> and moſt apt and able and preſt with their <hi>Opifique powers</hi> to cooperate with <hi>phyſicall meanes.</hi> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, <hi>Euacuations</hi> are then moſt requiſite,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19071:30"/>
becauſe groſſe pituitous <hi>Humors,</hi> heaped-vp in winter (which condenſates them and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtipates their <hi>Meatus</hi>) now diſſoluing, with hotter <hi>ayre,</hi> will eaſily, if they be not euacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, be diffuſed into the whole <hi>body,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get grieuous Diſeaſes. And in the later end of the Spring, the <hi>redundance</hi> of hotter <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors</hi> are ready, if <hi>obſtructions</hi> be not remoued and they auoided, to inflame and to putrifie and produce <hi>Feuers.</hi> The <hi>Spring</hi> therefore (eſpecially that which next precedes the <hi>Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>materique</hi> yeare) ſhould neuer paſſe-ouer a prouident <hi>Mans head</hi> without ſome <hi>helpe of phyſicke</hi> equiualent to <hi>Panala,</hi> though he feele no infirmities. Much more when a <hi>man</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues <hi>ſpontaneous laſſitude, heauineſſe</hi> or <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition</hi> in his <hi>body</hi> to the <hi>actions</hi> thereof, it is then high time by mature <hi>euacuation</hi> to preuent the ingruent and approaching <hi>ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> for thoſe are manifeſt <hi>ſignes,</hi> that the <hi>meſaraique veines</hi> (the double <hi>conduits, Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liducts</hi> from the <hi>bowels,</hi> and <hi>Sanguiducts</hi> from the <hi>Liuer</hi>) are repleniſhed with peccant <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors,</hi> which not timouſly euacuated will ſhortly bring forth <hi>fruits</hi> of ill <hi>effects.</hi> For the vitious <hi>matter,</hi> retained in the <hi>veines,</hi> at length putrifies, breathes forth ill vapours, and breeds <hi>diuturne Feuers,</hi> or elſe conuerted
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19071:30"/>
into a <hi>venemous nature,</hi> with ſodaine aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault, like a poyſonous <hi>Serpent</hi> coucht in <hi>am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſh</hi> for a miſchieuous <hi>deſigne,</hi> ſets vpon the principall <hi>parts (heart</hi> and <hi>braine,</hi>) producing grieuous <hi>accidents</hi> and <hi>effects</hi> of dangerous ſequell. Sometimes theſe vitious <hi>Humors</hi> powred forth into the <hi>bowels</hi> and other <hi>veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,</hi> doe cauſe the <hi>Cholick, Iaundice, Cachexia,</hi> and other <hi>maladies,</hi> &amp; other whiles elapſing forth of the greater <hi>branches</hi> into the <hi>habit</hi> of the <hi>body</hi> vnder the <hi>skin,</hi> they breed <hi>itches, ſcabs, botches,</hi> and other <hi>praeternaturall Tumors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next vnto the <hi>Spring</hi> is the <hi>fall</hi> of the <hi>leafe,</hi> or <hi>Autumne,</hi> which indeed is a <hi>ſecond Spring,</hi> though many <hi>degrees</hi> ſhort of the former; but here the <hi>crudities</hi> and <hi>reliques</hi> of <hi>raw fruits</hi> and <hi>Sommer-indigeſtions</hi> (the <hi>banes</hi> of <hi>health</hi>) ingeſted and heaped-vp in the <hi>veines</hi> and other <hi>veſſells,</hi> neceſſitate that <hi>medication,</hi> which there is inuited through conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencie.</p>
               <p>For <hi>time</hi> of the <hi>Moone</hi>; I hold it not amiſs for a conſtant Man, where occaſions may be accommodated for <hi>free choice,</hi> to elect the <hi>mids</hi> of the firſt <hi>Quartile,</hi> and continue the <hi>take</hi> of the firſt <hi>infuſion</hi> moſt part of the two next <hi>Quaternaries</hi> or <hi>Decreaſe,</hi> and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19071:31"/>
or altering <hi>potion</hi> the <hi>Increaſe,</hi> becauſe the <hi>bodie</hi> is then moſt animated by exaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Spirits,</hi> and thereby <hi>Nature</hi> moſt potent for any worke. But I would not be too punctuall in this point; there is no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the <hi>obſerue</hi> of ſuch preciſe <hi>termes,</hi> nor is it my meaning to confine vnto ſo ſtrict <hi>limits,</hi> ſith euery temperate <hi>ſeaſon</hi> doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently ſerue for this manner of Phyſicke, onely the <hi>vernall</hi> and <hi>autumnall</hi> are very meet to be ſelected for a continued <hi>courſe</hi> of the like, when the purpoſe is for <hi>preuention of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> or <hi>remouall</hi> of rooted <hi>diſeaſes,</hi> whoſe affects are not precipitate or of ſodaine dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. But in <hi>acute diſeaſes,</hi> where grieuous <hi>diſtempers,</hi> of <hi>violent motion</hi> or <hi>doubtfull iſſue,</hi> infeſt or faſten vpon the <hi>bodie,</hi> a man muſt neither dwell vpon the expectance of ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable <hi>weather,</hi> nor of the beneuolent <hi>aſpects</hi> of the <hi>Planets,</hi> but ſetting apart all dallying <hi>delayes</hi> (the <hi>Deluge</hi> which few men doe dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhod decline and quit) fall too and follow this familiar Helpe, be it <hi>Winter</hi> or <hi>Sommer,</hi> or other vnſeaſonable <hi>time,</hi> rather than, by deferring it to a more accommodate <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> ſuffer the <hi>ſickneſſe,</hi> confirmed by <hi>procraſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> to become incurable or of doubtfull conſequence. Prouided alwayes, that the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19071:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>extreames</hi> and <hi>iniuries</hi> of diſtempered wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bee mitigated or auoided by keeping within prepared <hi>roomes</hi>; the <hi>meanes</hi> and <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> of which preparation are laid downe in the <hi>dietetique part</hi> of this worke, in the <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections of the ayre</hi> vpon <hi>diſcourſe</hi> of that <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But our <hi>Sommers</hi> in this <hi>Northerne Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate</hi> giue no true <hi>cauſe</hi> nor ſcarce any <hi>colour</hi> of that generall nice curioſity fondly foſtred for <hi>decline of weather-health,</hi> for feare of incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſuppoſed ineuitable <hi>hazard</hi> tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough medling with <hi>phyſicall meanes,</hi> in ſo much that moderate and rationall <hi>medication</hi> may ſafely bee miniſtred euen in the <hi>Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes</hi> themſelues; which ſuperſtitious <hi>ſcruple</hi> (deriued from the <hi>Canicular aphoriſme</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſideration of the <hi>Authors Country,</hi> or indeed of his <hi>conceipt</hi>) of diſſoluing, diſtrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and diſſipating the <hi>Humidum Radicale</hi> with the <hi>calidum innatum,</hi> hath made ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruable, that the <hi>vulgus hominum</hi> (at leaſt) will rather cowardly crouch and proſtrate, bend the <hi>backe</hi> to beare the <hi>brunt</hi> of the inſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Foe,</hi> amating <hi>ſickneſſe,</hi> than draw the <hi>dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> of one medicinable <hi>Doſe</hi> to encounter the aſſault, much leſſe enter the <hi>Liſts</hi> (by any <hi>methodicall courſe</hi>) of a conſtant <hi>combat</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:19071:32"/>
to make good the <hi>Keepe</hi> of the <hi>Caſtle</hi> of his <hi>ſoule</hi> committed to his religious charge.</p>
               <p>In hazardous <hi>diſeaſes</hi> then, let no man be too preciſe in curious termes of choice <hi>Seaſons,</hi> nor yet ſtand too ſtrictly vpon <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction</hi> of <hi>Humors,</hi> but be the <hi>malady acute</hi> or <hi>diuturn, venienti occurrite Morbo,</hi> though you cannot, for lacke of ſpecificall <hi>Munition,</hi> giue appoſit <hi>encounter</hi> to the firſt aſſault or ſeiſure, yet haſt diligent cleering the <hi>common paſſages (<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>entricle</hi> and <hi>Inteſtines</hi>) of ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>recrements,</hi> and neuer permit the <hi>redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance</hi> of crude matter to regurgitate, fluctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and flow to and fro in the <hi>veines</hi> and <hi>veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells,</hi> or to ſettle and neſt vpon ſome <hi>principall part,</hi> to the <hi>ruine</hi> of it and all the <hi>reſt,</hi> nor <hi>diu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne</hi> or lingring affections to grow more ſtubborne or rebellious both againſt <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Phyſicke,</hi> to the vtter confuſion and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molition of the whole <hi>Fabrick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>generous Medicine</hi> and gentle <hi>Mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue,</hi> confidently taken and conſtantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, hath power to accelerate the <hi>concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>diſeaſes</hi> by helping <hi>Nature</hi> both by <hi>eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuation</hi> and <hi>alteration,</hi> and to make thoſe which eſſentially and of themſelues are of doubtfull and daingerous <hi>euent,</hi> to become ſalutary and ſafe, and others, of leſſe hazard,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19071:32"/>
but more lingring and tedious, more tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and much ſhorter,</p>
               <p>In <hi>diuturne diſeaſes</hi> it is profitable, and in <hi>acute</hi> very neceſſarie to make ſome euacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuperfluous <hi>humors</hi> before <hi>concoction,</hi> becauſe that ouer and aboue the continent chiefe <hi>matter</hi> of the <hi>Malady</hi> in the <hi>veines</hi> or in the <hi>intrals,</hi> or in the <hi>habit</hi> of the <hi>body</hi> requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to be concocted, there are many times vitious <hi>contents</hi> neſted in the <hi>ventricle,</hi> in the <hi>inteſtines,</hi> and about the <hi>precordiall parts</hi> (ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt by <hi>dolour, heat, nauſeous loathing, bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, diſtention,</hi> and other <hi>Dignoſtiques</hi>) the concoction whereof (eſpecially of the <hi>ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke recrements</hi>) is many times expected in vaine; and <hi>Patients</hi> thus affected may doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe profitably be purged, by ſuch familiar meanes, at all times of the <hi>diſeaſe,</hi> euen before any appearance of <hi>concoction.</hi> And were I called in ſuch <hi>caſes (caeteris concurrentibus)</hi> I ſhould aduiſe, firſt to prepare the <hi>Body,</hi> for <hi>receipt</hi> of ſo <hi>generous</hi> a <hi>Medicine,</hi> by <hi>St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique Pills,</hi> or by <hi>Emetique meanes,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vpon occaſion open a <hi>veine,</hi> for <hi>venti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> at leaſt: ſo ſhould this pretious <hi>Potion</hi> happily produce <hi>effects</hi> of excellent worth and ſecure aſſurance with more <hi>ſpeed</hi> and <hi>pleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:19071:33"/>Now touching the <hi>time</hi> of the <hi>day</hi> for <hi>drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> this <hi>Ale,</hi> although it be ſo milde and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar a <hi>medication,</hi> that it may, not much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe ſometimes (when tis compounded with <hi>Purgers</hi>) be carded with common <hi>Ale</hi> or <hi>Beere</hi> to make it a <hi>meal-drinke,</hi> eſpecially for the extenuating and much abating of groſſe and fat <hi>corpulency,</hi> by occaſioning more copious detraction of <hi>ſuperfluities</hi> and vnne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary <hi>iuices,</hi> yet when the <hi>intention</hi> is to make ſincere <hi>euacuation</hi> of vitious or ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous <hi>contents</hi> in other <hi>conſtitutions,</hi> it will be more proper and indeed the moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued and requiſite <hi>method</hi> to take it faſting (eſpecially to ſuch as vſe to drinke next their <hi>hearts,</hi> as they terme it) betimes in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that it may the more deeply penetrate and carry it ſelfe into the <hi>Humors</hi> and all the <hi>veines</hi> and <hi>parts</hi> of the <hi>Body,</hi> and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence more effectually produce all its ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue effects both of <hi>Euacuation</hi> and <hi>Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To others, not vſed to drinke faſting (as they call it) becauſe common drinke com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into their empty ſtomackes may affect and ſomewhat offend the head and nerues, a <hi>potcht Egge</hi> ſeaſoned with ſalt and three or foure drops of Vineger, or ſome other ſmall
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19071:33"/>
                  <hi>morſell</hi> of light or eaſie <hi>digeſtion,</hi> may conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently be premiſed or admitted. Not that any dammage or dainger depends vpon the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine entry and conuoy of this <hi>Potion</hi> into the empty <hi>cauity</hi> or <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of the <hi>ſtomacke:</hi> the <hi>body</hi> of <hi>Panala</hi> is an <hi>alimentary medecin</hi> ſo milde and benigne, there can bee neither cauſe nor colour to ſuſpect the <hi>concomitance</hi> or <hi>ſequence</hi> of any violent, ſiniſter, or offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue Effects, by or from the quality thereof, to the empty <hi>ventricle</hi>; but that the admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſo ſmall a <hi>pittance</hi> before the Potion, ſubſcribing to <hi>cuſtome of diet</hi> without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding of <hi>Art (Aëtius</hi> commends pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging <hi>medicaments</hi> giuen with <hi>meat</hi> in <hi>bodies</hi> naturally coſtiue) ſtirs-vp <hi>Nature,</hi> and awakes and quickens the <hi>mechanique ſpirits</hi> of the <hi>ſtomacke</hi> with pleaſurable delight to imbrace the approach of a greater <hi>Peregrine</hi> ſo vſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into the <hi>preſence</hi> by the aggrating prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of ſo welcome a well-knowne <hi>familiar.</hi> He that doubts, the <hi>medicine</hi> and the <hi>humors</hi> it moues will corrupt the <hi>Meat,</hi> precipitate crude indigeſtions, and conuoy an excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentitious <hi>Chylus</hi> into the <hi>Veines</hi> and <hi>Liuer,</hi> let Him, to auoid all colour of ſcruple, ſpare it at <hi>meales,</hi> and all manner of <hi>meat</hi> when He drinkes it; ſo ſhall the mixture nor worke
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19071:34"/>
vpon his <hi>ſtomacke</hi> nor <hi>conceipt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To conclude, the righteſt <hi>method</hi> is to drinke this <hi>Ale</hi> vpon an empty <hi>ſtomacke,</hi> and tis a very good order to take it betimes in the <hi>morning,</hi> and two houres before <hi>meales</hi> both <hi>dinner</hi> and <hi>ſupper</hi> alſo, if the <hi>ayme</hi> be to purge much.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Summer</hi> it may bee taken to <hi>bedward,</hi> and two or three houres alſo before you riſe onely, to the end moſt part of the <hi>purging</hi> may be paſt before the <hi>heat</hi> of the <hi>day,</hi> and that ſome <hi>ſleepe</hi> then vpon it may vnite <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heat,</hi> and promote the working of the <hi>Medicament.</hi> For though profound <hi>ſleepe</hi> may ſtay it a time, it neither quite ſuperſedes the euacuation, nor perturbs the <hi>action</hi> of the <hi>Ale</hi> more than it doth of <hi>Stomatique</hi> or other <hi>Pills ſine cuſtodia,</hi> which are cuſtomably and beſt ſo taken.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Winter</hi> take it onely before <hi>Noone</hi>; viz. one <hi>Doſe</hi> or <hi>Draught</hi> about 6 or 7 in the <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> in bed, and another when you are vp after ſome motion of the <hi>body,</hi> with a <hi>third</hi> (if need be) an houre or more before <hi>dinner,</hi> or the 2 laſt onely (if not all three in this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der where you like not that firſt) ſo ſhall you well accommodate the <hi>medication,</hi> and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily preuent the inconuenience of <hi>night-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:19071:34"/>Theſe <hi>Cautions</hi> are ſpecially for tender <hi>Bodies,</hi> and intemperate <hi>Seaſons</hi>; ordinarie <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> and <hi>ſeaſonable Times</hi> need no ſuch preciſe <hi>Rule</hi> of definite <hi>Drinking</hi> this familiar <hi>Liquor.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the Doſe, the manner of Taking and the Continuance of vſing this <hi>Ale.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He vſuall <hi>Doſe</hi> of <hi>purging Poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> ſeldome exceedes the meaſure or proportion of <hi>Three Ounces,</hi> leſt the <hi>Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity</hi> ſhould ſubuert the <hi>Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricle</hi> and cauſe <hi>Nauſeum</hi> or perhaps <hi>Caſting:</hi> But ſo ſmall a draught here is too little, it may <hi>movere,</hi> but not <hi>promouere,</hi> ſtirre the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor,</hi> but not extirpe or purge it forth: This <hi>Ale</hi> being moſt benigne and familiar to <hi>Nature,</hi> in <hi>Sight, Sauour, Taſte</hi> and <hi>Digeſt,</hi> a man may without errour or ſuſpition of any foule <hi>accident,</hi> take <hi>a full Draught</hi> to tenne or twelue <hi>Ounces:</hi> Some men drinke ſixteene <hi>Ounces</hi> or a <hi>whole pint</hi> at once, though halfe a Pint be a reaſonable <hi>Doſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:19071:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>For <hi>manner of taking the Ale</hi>; It is ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily drunke without <hi>Heating,</hi> according to the cuſtome of common <hi>Ale</hi> or <hi>Beere,</hi> and in winterly ſeaſons, it will doe very well, and indeed is very requiſite, to fright away the frigidity with the <hi>ſight of the fire,</hi> or with a <hi>browne Toſt</hi> attempered, if you will, with the <hi>Teſts</hi> of <hi>Suger</hi> and <hi>Nutmeg,</hi> to aggrate both <hi>palate</hi> and <hi>ſtomacke.</hi> Or you may ſcare off the <hi>Cold,</hi> by quenching in the <hi>cup</hi> a <hi>Gad</hi> of <hi>Steele,</hi> or rather ſome peeces of <hi>Gold</hi> made hot in a ſiluer ſpoone, (or the ſpoone alone) with a chafing-diſh, becauſe it leaues in the <hi>Liquor</hi> no aſtriction nor other <hi>Heterogene quality.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Touching the continuance</hi>; this hath refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Cauſe that occaſions the courſe of <hi>Medication,</hi> which muſt and beſt doth li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the ſame. <hi>Seuen daies</hi> will doe well for clenſing the <hi>Inteſtines, Liuer</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eines</hi> of the <hi>Colluvies</hi> of <hi>Humors,</hi> and to reſerate the <hi>veſſells</hi> and <hi>paſſages</hi>; but <hi>double</hi> that <hi>Time</hi> will effectually remoue many ſetled Affects, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme diſtempers, and produce good <hi>Rectifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> of all the parts of the <hi>Body:</hi> and one <hi>Fund</hi> or <hi>Bag,</hi> will vpon the firſt <hi>Infuſion</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently furniſh a temperate Patient for a <hi>Fortnight,</hi> and the like vpon the <hi>Second.</hi> And the taking of either of them may without
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19071:35"/>
errour or much inconuenience in many caſes aſwell <hi>Curatiue</hi> as <hi>cautionarie,</hi> bee a day or two omitted or diſcontinued to correſpond ſome vrgent occaſions, prouided the diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance bee redeemed with diligent purſuit for <hi>Reparation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this is moſt requiſite to bee done, if ſincere and exact. Evacuation be not already accompliſht. For the noxious humor, ſith it is an vnnaturall Alien, (<hi>alienus ac praeter nae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam</hi>) muſt bee wholly and abſolutely eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated and eiected, whether the counſell be <hi>precaution</hi> or <hi>profligation</hi> of the diſeaſe. I confeſſe, the <hi>Remaine</hi> of ſome minute ſmall portion of the peccant humour may by the <hi>ſpirituall force and fire of Nature,</hi> promoted and fortified with an exquiſite rule of <hi>Diete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Regiment,</hi> be ſo maſtred and vanquiſht, that ſafe and ſound health may ſometimes ſucceed without feare of <hi>Relapſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if the <hi>Reliques</hi> be many, except <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> (happily potent in all her Faculties) doe voluntarily ſubdue and avoid the ſame, the exacteſt order of Life cannot ſafe-guard the ſicke from the daingerous <hi>Machines</hi> of the <hi>Diſeaſe:</hi> for though hee may ſeeme in ſome ſort to haue receiued eaſe by the <hi>purging,</hi> He will relapſe into the former infirmity, ſooner
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19071:36"/>
or later, in more or leſſe latitude, according to the <hi>Copy</hi> or <hi>Malignity</hi> of the <hi>Reliques,</hi> and his <hi>strength</hi> and <hi>Diet,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Reliques</hi> of diſeaſes breed <hi>Relapſes, Quae à morbis relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur, recidiuos morbos facere conſueuerunt, Hipp. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Aph.</hi> 12. For when the <hi>part</hi> remaining, retaines the condition of the <hi>whole,</hi> which was altogether againſt <hi>Nature,</hi> that <hi>remaine</hi> can neuer be conuerted and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milated into the ſubſtance of the Body, but will in proceſſe of time corrupt the pure hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, together with the <hi>Aliments,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce <hi>morbid fruits</hi> like to the firſt. Hence it is, that <hi>the more you feed a foule body</hi> (not fully clenſed from impure humors) <hi>the more you offend, Impura corpora, quo magis nutris, hoc magis offendis, Aph.</hi> 10. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. For you nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh not the ſicke but the ſickneſſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to vindicate and cleere the Man from his <hi>Maladie,</hi> whatſoeuer noxious <hi>Humour</hi> neſts in the <hi>Body,</hi> it muſt bee abſolutely and totally taken away and eliminated.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Panala</hi> then in rebellions, maligne, ſtubborne, and diuturne diſeaſes, ſhould bee conſtantly continued a <hi>month</hi> or more with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermiſſion, or any other Drinke, onely the <hi>Meale-drinke</hi> may bee made of a <hi>Bagge,</hi> made vp without <hi>Purgers,</hi> or elſe the <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19071:36"/>
potion</hi> carded with other Drinks.</p>
               <p>The reaſon of extending the medication to ſo long a <hi>Time</hi> may bee, that <hi>Creationis morbi, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> curationis paria ſunt quodam modo Temporum Momenta.</hi> For as weedes are hardly hailed and pluckt out their <hi>Holds,</hi> when they are once deeply rooted, though quickly quit and rid the <hi>Plot</hi> when they are young; ſo diſeaſes long in breeding (though perhaps ſuddenly breaking forth by occaſion of <hi>Cold-taking,</hi> ill diet or other error, as newly bred) are for the moſt part long in <hi>curing.</hi> It is almoſt a <hi>Miracle</hi> to plow them vp in a moment, though ſuch <hi>Herculean helpes</hi> we find ſomtimes by ſpecifique Meanes.</p>
               <p>But they fondly run into a groſſe Errour, whoſoeuer in <hi>Diuturne Affects</hi> or inueterate deepe trenched Maladies giue ouer or negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently interrupt without reparation the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant courſe of Medication before the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors offending, being prepared by <hi>motion</hi> and <hi>flux,</hi> be fully avoyded, and the parts and <hi>Harmony</hi> of the body duly rectified by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent continuance of the Meanes.</p>
               <p>For although good Euacuation, from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe parts of the body, may in many caſes be effectually wrought and performed in few daies, <hi>deepe rooted Impreſſions</hi> doe neceſſarily
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19071:37"/>
require longer extent of Phyſicall helpes for due <hi>Eradication</hi> of peccant cauſes, and for true <hi>Rectification,</hi> as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>And let no man attempt nor imagine by extraordinary ingurgitation and qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing vp the whole quantity of the <hi>Ale</hi> in a few daies to accelerate the cures of long continued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities; It is the moderate and temperate vſe of Medicine, with regular cariage and conſtant perſeuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the ſame, that breeds and produces the beſt and readieſt effects and performance for remouall and riddance of the dolours and dire affects dimaning from deepe impreſſed diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>But the cuſtomary vſe and continuance of the ſame meanes (<hi>Meat</hi> or <hi>Medicine</hi>) breedes dulneſſe of <hi>Appetite</hi> or of <hi>Operation.</hi> Forbeare the Potion but a few daies (proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a good diet be in the interim obſerued) and you ſalue this <hi>Sacietie.</hi> For intermiſſion, aggrates in effect with the gratefull <hi>fruits</hi> of <hi>change,</hi> and we finde that in ſome ſort <hi>New,</hi> which hath for a reaſonable ſpace beene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termitted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:19071:37"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the Diet and Order obſeruable in the vſe of this medicinable Ale.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>head</hi> of this <hi>Chapter</hi> is the <hi>Subject</hi> of the <hi>Dietetique</hi> or <hi>Second Part</hi> of <hi>Panala:</hi> in which, beſides ſome large diſcourſe of the ſalutary vſe of the ſix <hi>Non-naturalls,</hi> the <hi>alimentation</hi> both of the <hi>Spirits</hi> and <hi>Body,</hi> is <hi>anatomically</hi> delinea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Yet that this <hi>Medique part</hi> may not in the meane time, bee poſted forth <hi>Pede primo claudicaens,</hi> with downe-right halt before, I held it vnfit to be altogether paſt-ouer here in ſilence, and haue therefore borrowed leaue for a touch or two in a few lines, before I goe about to trace out the whole <hi>Linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of that <hi>Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In diuturne, lingring and daingerous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes it is very conducible and requiſite in all ſorts of Phyſicall courſes ordained for their cures, to foſter and follow the conſtant <hi>keepe</hi> of regular ſtrict moderation, not in the <hi>qualities</hi> and <hi>quantities</hi> of <hi>Meats</hi> and <hi>Drinkes</hi> onely, but in the reſt of the <hi>Rerum non natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralium</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:19071:38"/>
likewiſe. But in the vſe of this <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camentum Alimentoſum,</hi> there is much leſſe need to preſcribe any ſo exact and preciſe Rules of <hi>Diet,</hi> be the Intenſion <hi>cautionary</hi> or <hi>curatiue,</hi> to ſecure or arme the Body in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention of ingruent infirmities, or to remoue or cure them when they haue made ſeiſure. Yet is it very commendable and conuenient too, in the vſe of this <hi>Ale,</hi> as of all other me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinable meanes, to obſerue and keepe a moderate <hi>abſtinence</hi> from <hi>food,</hi> of manifeſt ill condition at leaſt, and in all others to riſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery <hi>Meale</hi> from <hi>Table</hi> with good <hi>appetite,</hi> that <hi>Nature,</hi> being no way hindred or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt with meats of hard digeſtion or naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie iuice, or with too large proportion of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurgitation, may without impediment freely and happily produce her <hi>curatiue</hi> and <hi>ſalutary aymes</hi> and <hi>effects.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Generall Rule</hi> may well ſerue as all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient to the common ſort of <hi>People,</hi> to whom tis idle folly to preſcribe ſtrict orders, which they neither can nor will keepe. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mens Purſes are not furniſht for meats of fit iuice, and many robuſt and laborious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are happy in their habilities of ſtrong conſtitutions, accuſtomed to hardneſſe and to groſſe feeding, and meats of light digeſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19071:38"/>
are of ſleight eſteeme with <hi>ſtomackes</hi> inured to make full meales on ſolid ſtrong diſhes. One word more yet by the way, of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent fruits of full and ſpare feedings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repletion</hi> or too liberall feeding heaps vp abundance of <hi>excrements</hi> and ſuperfluous and vitious <hi>Humors</hi> (the <hi>Relicts</hi> of ouer-taxed <hi>concoctions</hi>) begets <hi>crudities</hi> and <hi>obſtructions,</hi> oppreſſes and ſuffocates the <hi>diuine</hi> and <hi>natiue heat,</hi> much hindring the laudable functions thereof <hi>ſpirituall</hi> and <hi>corporall,</hi> for it dulls all the <hi>Senſes,</hi> and diſanulls all dexterity, agility and actiue promptitude of the <hi>body,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides breeding all ſorts of <hi>maladies</hi> humor all, excrementitious, and ſuch as proceed from <hi>Plethora</hi> and <hi>Cachochymia,</hi> it cauſes many times <hi>recidiuation</hi> and <hi>returne</hi> of diſeaſes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe quit and cured, and ſeldome failes to fruſtrate the <hi>care</hi> and <hi>cure</hi> of the honeſt <hi>Artiſt,</hi> in that they obtunde, debilitate, and oft depraue the ſalutary <hi>operations</hi> of <hi>medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable meanes.</hi> For <hi>Nature</hi> being ouer-borne with the heauy load of abundance, ſinkes vnawares in the <hi>mid-way</hi> vnder her burthen.</p>
               <p>But contrariwiſe, the <hi>Innatum calidum</hi> (that <hi>diuine Opifex</hi> and <hi>author</hi> of all <hi>naturall functions</hi>) nor implicated, nor intricated with ingeſtions of viands offenſiue in <hi>Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:19071:39"/>
or <hi>Quality,</hi> but free to diffuſe it ſelfe into and through all parts of the <hi>body,</hi> ſhall bee able euerywhere to extend and execute its natiue <hi>power</hi> and <hi>ſtrength,</hi> to conuert good iuices and depurated blood by nutrition into the ſubſtance of the body and all its parts, to digeſt, rarifie and diſſipate by inſenſible <hi>tranſpiration</hi> all ſuperfluous Humors, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coct the crude, and change them into ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous nutriment, to attenuate the thicke, make fluent the tough, expedite <hi>obſtructions,</hi> make patent all the corporall <hi>Paſſages,</hi> and fortifie the <hi>expulſiue facultie.</hi> And by theſe meanes, the <hi>operation</hi> of this <hi>generous medicine</hi> ſhall be rectified, exalted, and more enhabled to produce and ſhew-forth its moſt exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite worthy effects, <hi>euacuatiue, alteratiue,</hi> and otherwiſe <hi>operatiue,</hi> with more <hi>ſpeed</hi> and <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility.</hi> Such and ſo great is the <hi>virtue, force and effects of Abſtinence or Spare-diet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To returne; After each <hi>morning draught</hi> of the <hi>Ale,</hi> you may to many good purpoſes eat a few <hi>Raiſons</hi> of the Sunne, and now and then make your <hi>Supper</hi> of them and a morſell of <hi>Bread</hi> if you will, for they leuigate, ſmooth and ſupple the roughneſſe of the rough Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery or <hi>Wind-pipe,</hi> by opening and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning they cure the <hi>torrifaction,</hi> or retardate
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19071:39"/>
the <hi>ſexilitie</hi> of the <hi>Liuer,</hi> clenſe <hi>Phleagme,</hi> ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorate and madifie the <hi>body</hi> with nutrient <hi>moiſture,</hi> and make the <hi>iuices</hi> thereof roſcid, leſſe diſſipable and more reparable, they breed good <hi>blood,</hi> and helpe infirmities of the <hi>Throat, Lungs, Cheſt, Milt, Kidneys,</hi> and <hi>Bladder.</hi> For forbearance of meat after pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation taken, ſome limit the ſpace of <hi>two houres</hi> after a ſtrong purging <hi>Potion,</hi> but in <hi>purges</hi> of <hi>ſolid forme,</hi> or in <hi>Pills,</hi> double that <hi>time</hi> ſhould bee interpoſed and paſt, before other Repaſt. And many admit of no meale vntill the <hi>Purge</hi> haue performed its <hi>Office,</hi> leſt the meat ſhould be corrupted by mixture with ſuch medicine, but it is all-ſufficient that the ſubſtance or body of the <hi>Purge</hi> hath ſo quit the <hi>ventricle</hi> that it hath paſt the <hi>Port Pylorus</hi> into the <hi>Inteſtines</hi>; of which there is aſſured <hi>teſt,</hi> when neither <hi>Belching,</hi> nor <hi>vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiding,</hi> nor <hi>loathing,</hi> nor <hi>ſenſe of gnawing</hi> at the <hi>ſtomacke,</hi> nor any <hi>ſent</hi> of the <hi>medicine</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines. Then moderate <hi>refection</hi> with meat of good iuice and eaſie digeſt may conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, and muſt neceſſarily bee taken to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh <hi>Nature.</hi> Yea tis a common practice (contrary to <hi>Auicen (Fen.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>doct.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 5.) to preſcribe the taking of a <hi>Meſſe</hi> of thinne <hi>Broth,</hi> after the firſt or ſecond <hi>ſtoole,</hi> to waſh-down
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19071:40"/>
the <hi>Reliques</hi> of the <hi>Medicine,</hi> to quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the tedious qualities thereof, to comfort the <hi>ſtomacke,</hi> and to promote the <hi>operation</hi> of the <hi>Phyſicke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this <hi>Ale</hi> is ſo milde and benigne a Medicine, it may ſafely be admitted a neerer <hi>neighbour</hi> vnto <hi>meales,</hi> though it hath no need of waſhing-downe by any other liquid meanes.</p>
               <p>For keeping the <hi>houſe</hi>; This <hi>Panala</hi> is <hi>phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke fine cuſtodia,</hi> neuer in reſpect of its owne <hi>nature,</hi> confining the <hi>patient</hi> to his <hi>Chamber,</hi> but be he of any indifferent hability of body, or that he intertaine it for <hi>caution</hi> or <hi>preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of ſickneſſe, hee may in the day-time, when the weather is any thing temperate, either walke or ride abroad, or follow his neceſſary field-occaſions. But if the <hi>day</hi> be immoderate in <hi>heat, cold, wet,</hi> or <hi>winde, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe</hi> will tell euery ſenſible man, that the ſtrong ought not in the vſe of this nor any other purging Phyſicke (how mildly ſoeuer euacuating) raſhly expoſe his bodie (of which neither <hi>diuine</hi> nor <hi>humane law</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits to make wilfull wracke) to the <hi>iniurie</hi> of ſuch diſtempered <hi>Skies,</hi> and that <hi>keepe-within-doores</hi> is the ſafeſt and ſureſt (and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed neceſſary) guard for the craſie in ſuch
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19071:40"/>
caſes. For the humors ſtirr'd vp and agitated by purge, are, in too hot ſeaſons (which de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bilitate the ſtrength, kindle hot diſeaſes) more or leſſe, according to the ſtrong or weake working of the Medicine, either drawne to the <hi>Superfice</hi> or <hi>skin,</hi> (a contrary courſe) or elſe over heated, doe kindle a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: thorow <hi>Cold</hi> they grow ſluggiſh and dull, and ſlowly deſcend and paſſe thorow the ſtraitned paſſages. The <hi>Ayre</hi> being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry moiſt, in wet weather, paſſing into the body through the dilated Pores, looſens the ſame, and occaſions defluxions, but a more vaſt and free <hi>Ayre,</hi> agitated with bluſtering <hi>winds,</hi> much trouble the <hi>Body</hi> with a ſhuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling confuſion of the <hi>Humors,</hi> and cauſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult Purging.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Matter of motion:</hi> It is verie requiſite and conuenient (<hi>viribus conſtantibus</hi>) to vſe moderate <hi>Exerciſe</hi> or <hi>Labour</hi> of the Body af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter taking the Potion to ſtirre vp and kindle the <hi>Fire</hi> of the <hi>Innatum Calidum</hi> (the mouer of all Medicines and <hi>Cauſa ſine qua,</hi> without which their <hi>ſpirituall faculties</hi> lie as it were conſopited, and produce no good Action) and before meat an houre or more to further <hi>Concoction, Digeſtion,</hi> and <hi>Diſtribution</hi> of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ands, to reſtore and corroborate all the <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19071:41"/>
Faculties,</hi> and rectifie the <hi>Actions</hi> of all the <hi>Senſes,</hi> but with this <hi>Caution,</hi> that it be continued <hi>ad Ruborem</hi> onely, in thin <hi>Tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> of Body, leſt it exhale, diſsipate and ſpend the <hi>Spirits,</hi> and debilitate the <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> yet in ſtrong corpulent and ſtuffy <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>textures</hi> it may well be extended <hi>ad ſudorem,</hi> and the rather if bee not vſed till ſome <hi>two houres</hi> after taking the <hi>Medicine.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the diuerſe and contemporarie Operations of <hi>Panala.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Vlta neſcientes</hi> (ſaith <hi>Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinus Danus) de multis dubitare neceſſe eſt.</hi> From much ignorance muſt needs iſſue a nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous brood of doubts: But a Man, that will needs be a great <hi>Maſter</hi> in <hi>Phyſicke,</hi> feares (or rather faines, tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>plaine Cavil, maine ſcruple,</hi>) the confuſed diſtracting of <hi>Nature</hi> with the various taske of meat, and this medicine ſet to work, if not tane at one time, and the <hi>contemporary Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of my <hi>Panala,</hi> from the <hi>Circumference</hi> to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19071:41"/>
the <hi>Center</hi> of the body by deiection or ſtoole, and from the <hi>Center</hi> to the <hi>Circumference</hi> by Evaporation or Sweat.</p>
               <p>Is it not <hi>Natures</hi> Innate Office and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Deuoire together and at once to ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and produce multiplicious and various effects in our bodies, to incide, attenuate, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oppilate, to aſtringe and corroborate, to rari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the groſſe, deterge the tough, condenſate the fluid and thinne, to digeſt all <hi>Ingestions,</hi> and by ſeparating the <hi>impure</hi> from the <hi>pure,</hi> to aſsigne and diſtribute this for <hi>Nutriment</hi> to all parts of the body (how diſsimilar ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in ſubſtance;) and that partly to ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and ſend vnto peculiar <hi>veſſells</hi> and <hi>recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacles,</hi> and partly to amandate and expell by <hi>Stoole, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine, Sweat,</hi> and by ſundry other <hi>wayes, meanes,</hi> and <hi>Emunctories?</hi> Doth Shee not <hi>ſimul et ſemel,</hi> at the ſame time, and in the ſame <hi>Meſaraique Veines</hi> cary the <hi>Chylus</hi> from the <hi>Guts</hi> to the <hi>Liver,</hi> and the <hi>Blood</hi> from the <hi>Liuer</hi> to the <hi>Guts?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the familiar benignity of <hi>Panala</hi> doth rather aſſociate and ſympathize with <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> in the diffuſing and imparting of her ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutary and wholſome Faculties, than any way affront or impeach their participation. For the contrary <hi>Qualities</hi> reſiding in one
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19071:42"/>
ſubſtance, worthy <hi>Fernelius</hi> ſaues my labour in his various attributes vnto <hi>Guaiacum,</hi> which ſaith he, if any man meruaile at, <hi>Vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res conſulat Artis proceres,</hi> Let him aduiſe and conſult with the writings of the ancient great <hi>Maſters</hi> of <hi>Phyſicke,</hi> who haue tryed and approued <hi>One</hi> and the ſame ſimple and ſingle Medicine to bee indued with, and preuaile in diuerſe faculties, as of <hi>Heating</hi> and <hi>Cooling,</hi> or of <hi>Drying</hi> and <hi>Humecting,</hi> or of <hi>thin</hi> and <hi>groſſe parts, &amp;c.</hi> And that this record of his may not to bee thought to be confined to the <hi>firſt Qualities,</hi> Headdes; and except thoſe <hi>Primarie Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> were confuſed and mixt together in one medicine, ſurely the <hi>ſecundarie,</hi> which dimane and proceed from them, could not bee likewiſe complicate in commixture. So <hi>Rhubarb,</hi> and <hi>Steele</hi> haue diuerſe parts deoppilatiue and aſtringent. <hi>Wormewood</hi> reſtraines Laxes, and relaxes bodies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtipate, it heates the <hi>cold Liver,</hi> and by accident through opening Obſtructions cooles the <hi>Hot: Saffron</hi> congregates and contracts the <hi>Spirits</hi> too much diffuſed, and yet expanſes and diffuſes them where it finds them contracted. <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> cures <hi>Contuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and <hi>Burnings:</hi> To conclude; is't not a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19071:42"/>
common practice amongſt the vulgar to helpe <hi>Hot griefes,</hi> with <hi>Hot meanes?</hi> Doe they not coole <hi>Feuer-heats</hi> with <hi>Hot purgers?</hi> Apply they not <hi>Wine</hi> and ſpirit of <hi>wine,</hi> to <hi>Heats</hi> and <hi>Inflamations</hi> of the <hi>Head?</hi> Yea, they fire out <hi>Feuers</hi> with <hi>Pepper,</hi> with Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditament of <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> many times.</p>
               <p>But what will you ſay to <hi>Mercurie,</hi> which is both <hi>moiſt</hi> and <hi>dry,</hi> the <hi>Hotteſt,</hi> the <hi>Coldeſt,</hi> and both rarifies and condenſates: The Chymiſt calls him a true <hi>Healer,</hi> a <hi>wicked Murderer,</hi> the <hi>Tobacco</hi> of <hi>Mineralls, Proteus, Magician, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to the Doubt; how <hi>One</hi> and the <hi>Selfe-ſame</hi> Medicine, ſhold at one &amp; the ſame time produce diuers effects of <hi>purging</hi> &amp; <hi>ſweating. Quercetanus</hi> is ſo full and pregnant in this point, He may be <hi>inſtar ommum,</hi> and ſerue for a <hi>Sea of witneſſes,</hi> for punctuall reſolution of the <hi>Quaere</hi>; Take therefore his Teſtimonie in his <hi>Pharmacopoea,</hi> vpon a <hi>Maceration</hi> or <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion</hi> (nothing diſſuiting this in the <hi>Genus</hi>) both <hi>Purgatiue</hi> and <hi>Sudatiue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Double Euacuations (ſaith He) are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at one and the ſame time (<hi>ſimul &amp; ſemel</hi>) performed by one and the ſame remedy, which will ſeeem ſtrange vnto ſome, as I my ſelfe, circumuented and tranſported with the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19071:43"/>
ſame errour, conceiued before Experience (<hi>Rerum optima Magiſtra</hi>) taught &amp; brought me into a contrary opinion.</p>
               <p>Nor is <hi>Foreſtus</hi> (in his <hi>Scholia</hi> vpon his 20. Obſeruation <hi>de Lue venerea</hi>) his diſauow of this double Euacuation, to bee taken abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely for a generall rule for the reaſon he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leages proues it not: <hi>Si multum ſudet, non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt alvus fluere; ſi fluit alvus, non poteſt ſudare</hi>; This <hi>multum</hi> ſurely caries no leſſe relation vnto the <hi>Flux</hi> than to the <hi>Sweat,</hi> to wit, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning both to bee profuſe, and <hi>Magnos effatu dignos,</hi> ſo that profuſe purging may ſuſpend and minorate, but not ſuperſede the <hi>ſweat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the ſame Author (<hi>Obſerv.</hi> 11.) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proues and preſcribes ſtronger <hi>Phyſicke</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending both <hi>purgatiue</hi> and <hi>diaphoretique Faculties</hi> in one Medicine, than this <hi>Panala</hi> is, with this Teſtimonie of the double work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame: <hi>Habebat plurimos ſeceſſus quotidie &amp; ſubinde egregie ſudebat</hi>; Hee had daily many Stooles, and therewithall alſo ſweat excellently well, and by theſe meanes was perfectly cured.</p>
               <p>But ſweating here by my Medicine exhales onely the <hi>rarified Humors</hi> not attracting the <hi>Faeces</hi> to the <hi>Skin,</hi> but leauing them <hi>in Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſito</hi> within their peculiar <hi>Receptacles,</hi> to be in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19071:43"/>
due time eiected. How can I then, without iniuſtice depriue the remedy of its iuſt rights, by iniurious concealing its ſpeciall Facultie of cauſing ſweat, ſith it doth with facilitie <hi>vtram<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> paginam abſoluere?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the <hi>Cumber</hi> or inconuenience of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery or expoſure of the open body to the cold Ayre by purging in <hi>Sweat</hi>; what great <hi>Dainger</hi> or <hi>Doe</hi> is it to conuey a lined Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole or warme <hi>Boll</hi> to the Patient, euen in the heat and height of the Exhalation, which no man can truly conceiue I intend ſhould be profuſe or exceſſiue from <hi>Panala,</hi> becauſe my declared ayme in the diſpenſation, is at temperate moderation in all tne <hi>Evacuating Attributes</hi> I giue vnto it? And aſſuredly, whoſoeuer, after his <hi>Morning-Stoole, ſweats</hi> in bed with this Potion (made hot as it muſt be) may ſecurely continue that Evacuation an houre or two (or more were it not too many at once) before hee need feare or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect prouocation to a <hi>Second Stoole.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If yet any Scruple chance to ſticke in ſome fond or froward Stomacke, the <hi>Fund</hi> without <hi>Purgers</hi> will aſſuredly evaporate all ſuch friuolous conceits from out his fancie; And the <hi>Second Infuſion</hi> will reaſonably worke ſuch like effects. But with which
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19071:44"/>
infuſion ſoeuer you ſweat, let the body bee well clenſed with 4 or 5 dayes continuance of purging by ſtoole, then take the morning potion ſufferable hot, but in bed and after a ſtoole, if it may be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <head type="sub">Obſeruations remarkable in the vſe and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Ale.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat Phyſicke workes not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like in all Seaſons and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all ſubiects, <hi>common ſenſe</hi> informes the moſt ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid poore Obſeruer; but ſometimes, though it bee methodically miniſtred by a good <hi>Artiſt,</hi> the expectation is illuded by <hi>exceſſiue</hi> or <hi>diminutiue operation</hi>; nor is it a matter of facile diſquiſition to beat out and diſcouer the certaine reaſon of ſuch incertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. For ſome bodies, by a ſecret <hi>propriety</hi> of their owne <hi>natures,</hi> are eaſily and plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully purged with milde medicines, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſcarce moued with very ſtrong Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:19071:44"/>But of <hi>occult cauſes</hi> it is not pertinent nor fit, either to the <hi>place</hi> or my <hi>pen</hi> to diſcourſe; onely a Touch or two of others, becauſe, though more euident, they are not ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous or manifeſt to <hi>vulgar notion,</hi> but that they may neceſſarily admit ſome particular demonſtration.</p>
               <p>The working of <hi>Cathartique medicines</hi> doth commonly vary (<hi>quoad majus &amp; minus</hi>) according to the variation of Seaſons, and the ſtates and conſtitutions of mens bodies.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>firſt:</hi> The <hi>hot</hi> and <hi>dry</hi> ſeaſon or diſpoſition of the Ayre extracts, euaporates, and waſts much of the humours of the body, &amp; by conſequence debilitates the ſame, and leaues leſſe matter to furniſh forth copious deiections; nor is it fit for purging Phyſicke which for moſt part heats and weakens.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cold weather</hi> and Northerne winde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract and ſtraighten the paſſages, binde the body, exiccate and thicken the humors, and make them rebellious, or leſſe obedient at leaſt, to Phyſicke, which in theſe caſes muſt needs be leſſe copious in euacuation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>South windes, moiſt Climates,</hi> and wet or Rheumatique weather, humect the body, looſen the humours, and occaſion plentifull deiections vpon due meanes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:19071:45"/>
                  <hi>Moderate ſeaſons,</hi> Southerne winde, (not boyſtrous) and temperate Regions are moſt accommodate to Purgations for production of beſt operations.</p>
               <p>Touching the <hi>ſtate</hi> of the <hi>Body; hot</hi> and <hi>moiſt conſtitutions</hi> with moſt eaſe and ſafety of all others doe beare and obey Cathartique medicines.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hot and dry bodies</hi> purge ſparingly for lack of matter and its vnaptneſſe to moue, and muſt with caution be purged with well qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified meanes, leſt they diſtemper with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and drying; to meet with which incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience let ſuch conſtitutions take this Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a little before meales.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The moiſt, the young,</hi> and thoſe who are accuſtomed to a ſedentary life, are eaſily mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by Purge, according to its ſtrength and the Patients ballaſt of humours and excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; the like may be ſaid of <hi>women,</hi> ſith they ate vſually of ſoft, looſe, rare and patent <hi>textures,</hi> yet none of theſe accord with ſtrong medicines, though <hi>pregnant women</hi> may in the third, fourth, and fift Months (the liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by which the child adheres to the wombe, being then more firme) admit of moderate euacuations in acute diſeaſes at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with turgent matter.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:19071:45"/>
                  <hi>Robuſt ſtrong bodies,</hi> and thoſe that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ured to laborious liuing, and conſtitutions indued with obtuſe ſenſe of the parts, doe ſlowly yeeld vnto deiectiue meanes, yet may they ſafely ſuffer plentifull euacuations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Corpulent bodies</hi> likewiſe, though they ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily endure purgations, doe purge with ſome difficulty, becauſe their conſtitutions are cold, their corporall paſſages ſtraight, and their ſpirits but few, and thoſe turbid and groſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The thinne, the leane,</hi> and the temperate, are eaſily moued by Phyſicke, yet purge but ſparingly, becauſe of the rarity of their <hi>tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> and tenuity of their humours, nor are ſtrong purges accommodated for them, by reaſon they weaken their languid virtue, and ſpend their diſſipable <hi>ſpirits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Note further; that <hi>Plethorique, full and foggie bodies,</hi> whoſe veſſells are ſtuft with tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid <hi>illuvies</hi> of copious and reſtagnant Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors (whether congeſted by ſurfet or other repletions) doe many times, vpon light and ſlight Purgations, powre one profuſe and copious deiections, with much perturbation of the Bowells many times. For the redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant humors long pent vp, and now finding the veines and veſſells reſerate, and the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19071:46"/>
of export expanſed by the purge, <hi>Qua data porta ruunt,</hi> ruſh and guſh out (like li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor forth of a full cask pierced and vented) in copious flux, without any effrenate or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridled force or effect of the medicine, but by reaſon that <hi>Nature,</hi> mouing to expulſion, now thus a little inhabled doth deonerate and eaſe her ſelfe of ouer-burthens. For whilſt <hi>Nature</hi> is vigorous, ſtrong and ſound, and mannages well her offices of gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ouer our bodies, ſhee excludes and driues out of them whatſoeuer is peccant and ſuperfluous; but when ſhee is ouer-bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened and ouer-borne with abundance, ſhee ſo attends and waits all occaſions and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of eaſement, that ſhee apprehends many times the firſt and leaſt <hi>hint of helpe,</hi> and ioynes her owne forces with the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine aid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet ſometimes profuſe deiections fall out contrary to <hi>Nature,</hi> when through imbecil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of her <hi>regent</hi> and <hi>retentiue faculty,</hi> ſhe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers defluxions.</p>
               <p>Or though ſhe be more valid and ſtrong, yet is ſhe ſometimes ſo much prouoked and moleſted with the <hi>copie and acrimony of the humor,</hi> that ſhee cannot retaine it, but muſt euen let and ſuffer it by its own force to ſluce
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19071:46"/>
and breake forth from out its veſſells and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacles.</p>
               <p>Both theſe euacuations are <hi>ſymptomaticall,</hi> vnnaturall and vſeleſſe, becauſe the benigne and ſalutary <hi>ſucci,</hi> together with the maligne and pernicious, doe promiſcuouſly and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly, without any election, burſt and ruſh out with violence.</p>
               <p>But theſe profuſe euacuations, whether <hi>ſymptomatique</hi> or <hi>legitimate</hi> (exterminating onely whats cumberſome, either in the <hi>kind</hi> or in the <hi>quantum</hi>) whether occaſioned through diſorder of the Patient, or procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from other cauſes (euident or occult) iumping and ioyning with the <hi>contemporary operation</hi> of a purgatiue medicine (though milde and moderate) caſt foule aſperſions vpon the <hi>Phyſician,</hi> where concurring cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are nor well conſidered or not duely weighed of the cenſurer.</p>
               <p>To leaue no <hi>colour of cauill</hi> to the carping <hi>Momus,</hi> and to meet with the many incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible ſecrets ſhut vp in <hi>Natures cloſet</hi>; my <hi>Panala</hi> neuer aſtoniſhes her with ſodaine, nor debilitates with vehement aſſault, but gently aſſayes her with medication of ſo <hi>mild allay</hi> and gradation, (<hi>facilitate non vi operan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi>) that it may ſecurely, without any endain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19071:47"/>
the patient, ſound and ſearch out the abſtruſe and vnknowne conditions of any conſtitution, euen of the commoderate and ſoundeſt in integritie of ſanitude, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Hippocrates (Aph.</hi> 3.37.) brookes not Purgations without difficulty and perill, becauſe by ſetting vpon the <hi>ſpirituall</hi> and <hi>bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamique Mumie,</hi> for want of vitious humors to worke vpon, they cauſe <hi>grindings</hi> in the <hi>guts, ſwoundings, vertiginous</hi> and other <hi>ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes,</hi> and by continuance <hi>colliquation</hi> and <hi>conſumption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obſerue further; that after foure or fiue dayes vſe of this <hi>Ale,</hi> much <hi>matter</hi> being therewith auoided, you cannot expect the daily continuance of like copious deiection, as you found at firſt (although by cleering ſome paſſages, which perhaps were blocked vp before, the wayes for free working be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more patent) if you bee temperate in <hi>meat and drinke,</hi> and the time in <hi>wind and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> except you extend the <hi>doſe</hi> or <hi>draughts</hi> in taking larger proportions of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine.</p>
               <p>Nor will the <hi>Second Ale,</hi> prepared by <hi>rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion</hi> of the ſame <hi>Fund</hi> or <hi>Bag,</hi> doe much more, for <hi>matter of purging</hi> by <hi>ſtoole,</hi> (though it will then effectually purge by <hi>vrine</hi>) than
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19071:47"/>
keepe the body ſoluble, by reaſon the <hi>purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue ſpirits</hi> of the ingredients, being more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluble and allectiue than the <hi>alteratiues,</hi> will be well-nigh exhauſted and drawne-out by former <hi>infuſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This orderly diſcent and paſſage, from purging by the <hi>firſt Infuſion</hi> to meere ſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility (which in moſt caſes, will then be all-ſufficient) by the <hi>Second,</hi> cuts off and preuents all occaſions of conſtipation or coſtiueneſſe (the vſuall ſubſequents to purgers) by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing the cutting of humors, deoppilating of the veſſells, and by ſtill ſtimulating or ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciting the <hi>excretiue facultie</hi> to the ordinate fit performance of its office. But the additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of two ounces of <hi>Sene</hi> with <hi>Rubarb</hi> and <hi>Mechoacan,</hi> of each halfe an ounce, vnto the ingredients in the <hi>bag,</hi> will now indifferently furniſh the <hi>ſecond Infuſion</hi> with purgatiue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, and for the alteratiue, it retaines ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient force in the firſt Compoſition, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.</p>
               <p>Note moreouer, that in ſome caſes, by competent continuance of this Medicin (as in other <hi>Dietetique Phyſicke</hi>) there follow and are brought forth excellent <hi>fruits</hi> and <hi>effects</hi> of Alteratiue working in the Bodie, long after ending and giuing-ouer the taking
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19071:48"/>
of the ſame, inſomuch, that many time a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth or more thence, you ſhall finde much more <hi>fruit</hi> and <hi>benefit</hi> by it (without any euill <hi>Diathaſis,</hi> or impreſſion of diſaffect co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tracted from the extended vſe thereof, than, during the continuance of drinking the <hi>Ale,</hi> you could well conceiue, or by any probable coniecture from preſent perſeuerance, expect or propound vnto your ſelfe, provided, that you doe not relapſe through manifeſt <hi>diſorder</hi> or groſſe <hi>diſtemper,</hi> the <hi>Patients ſcourge,</hi> and the <hi>Phyſitians ſcandall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The reaſon of ſuch <hi>Haruest of phyſicall fruits</hi> in expectance and future, rather than in Preſent, may well be, that <hi>Nature,</hi> being kept in continuall <hi>Action,</hi> and the <hi>Humours</hi> and <hi>Spirits</hi> in more motion than ordinarie, by the daily vſe of the Potion (though gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and moderate) the effects thereof cannot be ſo ſetled, nor ſo ſenſibly diſcerned, during the <hi>Machine</hi> of <hi>Medication,</hi> as it will bee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome competent repoſe and Ceſſation from the purging, for compoſing all agitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Beſides that, the plenteous ſtore of ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie <hi>ſpirits,</hi> deriued from ſo excellent a <hi>potion</hi> by an extended courſe of drinking, diffuſed and impreſſed into al the parts &amp; dimenſions of the body, doth with the <hi>Opifique ſpirits</hi> of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19071:48"/>
the body continue mutuall cooperations, many daies, or rather weekes, after the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ouer of the <hi>Ale,</hi> to the perfect maturati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the fruits.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <head type="sub">The excellent <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertues of <hi>Panala</hi> in Generall.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Anala</hi> is a true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Medicamentum A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limento ſum</hi>; miniſtring to the body both food and Phyſicke: It is a legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate <hi>Diacatholique,</hi> a generall happy Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue eliminating all humors offenſiue in qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie or in quantity, but working moſt on the moſt redunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, in that they are moſt affluent to Electiues, &amp; moſt obedient to expulſiues, though rebell tenants which Nature moſt endeuours to eiect, becauſe they infeſt <hi>Her</hi> with more frequent and more mortall <hi>Duels</hi> then all forraigne and other domeſtique <hi>Foes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a Generous and almoſt a Generall <hi>Vniuerſall Medicine,</hi> (not inferiour to any Galenicall Phyſicke whatſoeuer) happily
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19071:49"/>
performing all the parts of a good <hi>Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, Evacuatiue,</hi> and <hi>Alteratiue,</hi> and not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle participating of the <hi>Comfortatiue</hi> alſo, to the <hi>Naturall, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itall</hi> and <hi>Animall</hi> parts, the <hi>Liver, Heart</hi> and <hi>Braine,</hi> and their Powers or Spirits, and, being compounded according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is a <hi>Benedict remedy</hi> for any infirmity or defect in a manner, euen for <hi>Hunger</hi> it ſelfe, in that it participates of (if not exceeds) the Alimentary virtues of the <hi>Staffe of Life,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting the <hi>Stomacke</hi> and nouriſhing the whole body.</p>
               <p>It <hi>Concocts</hi> crude and raw humours, cuts, liquifies, attenuates and makes the <hi>thicke,</hi> the <hi>tough</hi> and <hi>Tartareous</hi> become plyant and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequious to <hi>Nature:</hi> the attenuated, the concocted, the ſerous and watery it digeſts and conſumes: it clenſes the <hi>Ventricle</hi> from ſlymie and <hi>Phlegmatique Crudities</hi> ſticking to its rugoſities and wrinklings, deterges the <hi>Lungs</hi> and <hi>Cheſt</hi> from viſcous and putrid <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours,</hi> which, cleauing vnto them and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in the ſlender Branches of the <hi>Aſpera Arteria,</hi> doe obturate and ſhut vp thoſe ſtraight paſſages and cauſe difficult brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
               <p>It diſſolues, diſſipates and rids terrene and gravelly concretions, it deoppilates, opens
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19071:49"/>
and mundifies the <hi>Lungs,</hi> the <hi>Inteſtines,</hi> the <hi>Liver,</hi> the <hi>Spleene,</hi> the <hi>Reines,</hi> the <hi>Matrix,</hi> and all the veſſells, Parts, and Paſſages of the body, euen the neruall conduits of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and by theſe meanes makes excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent way for further workings, both of this ſame, and of other Medicines, by <hi>Stoole, Vrine, Evaporation,</hi> and other Operations.</p>
               <p>It gently, ſafely, effectually and moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiouſly purgeth <hi>Choler, Phlegme, Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly,</hi> nor rudely, nor raſhly rouzing this ſleeping <hi>Lyon,</hi> (by agitating or ſtimulating the ſtubborne humor) from quiet <hi>Denn</hi> to furious <hi>Doo</hi> of daingerous dints, cauſing fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Paſſions or grieuous affects; ſo doth it alſo clenſe and cary forth all corrupt and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trid humours (Authors of wormes and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other woes) with other peccant and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous contents, ſincere and alone leauing the laudable for Natures ſtore.</p>
               <p>It is therfore more auaileable for <hi>Longaeuity</hi> &amp; length of life, than exerciſe and ſweat, for ſuch moderate <hi>purges</hi> worke chiefly vpon the humors, whereas ſucculent Iuices and good <hi>Spirits</hi> (not eaſily repaired) together with humors and excrementitious vapours are exhailed and conſumed by <hi>perſpirations</hi> and <hi>ſweats.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:19071:50"/>Particularly, it purges (without perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or ſhuffling of humours) firſt of all the firſt region of the body, to wit, the <hi>Ventricle,</hi> the <hi>Meſaraicke veines,</hi> (thoſe numerous roots of innumerable <hi>Symptomes,</hi> and <hi>Diſeaſes</hi>) the <hi>Cauities</hi> of the <hi>Liver,</hi> the <hi>Milt,</hi> the <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chondria,</hi> the <hi>Meſenterie</hi> and <hi>Pancreas,</hi> thoſe two <hi>Sinkes</hi> and <hi>Swallowes</hi> of all <hi>Illuvies</hi> and Impurities: yea, there is ſcarce any other Cathartique that doth ſo mildly and ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfully draw forth and eliminate corrupt thicke <hi>Humors</hi>; beſides that by continuance and conſequution it euacuates the other <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> the <hi>Convex</hi> or outer parts of the <hi>Liuer,</hi> the <hi>Vena caua</hi> &amp; its Concomitant the <hi>Great Arterie:</hi> and after its effectuall expanſure and purgature of the firſt two, it vndertakes the <hi>third</hi> alſo (the <hi>Taske</hi> of our <hi>Gigantine</hi> and moſt valid <hi>purgers</hi>) and effectually, by its <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie,</hi> promoted by extended perſeuerance, performes eradication of deepe-rooted <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies</hi> from the <hi>Muſcles, Membranes, Ioynts,</hi> the remote <hi>Extreames</hi> and whole <hi>Moles</hi> and <hi>habit</hi> of the <hi>Body,</hi> thereby cutting off and curing many ſtubborne diſeaſes able to beare the brunt of the ſtrongeſt remedy.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:19071:50"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ictibus innumeris cecidit Dodonia Quereus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The huge maine Oake, which <hi>Cannon</hi> cannot downe,</l>
                  <l>Hew'd through with many ſtroakes, ſtrikes th'Earth with's Crowne.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Nor doth it evacuate the <hi>Body</hi> by <hi>Stoole</hi> onely, but it is likewiſe both <hi>Diuretique</hi> and <hi>Diaphoretique,</hi> diſſoluing &amp; expelling ſerous thin humours, by <hi>vrine,</hi> and by inſenſible <hi>Tranſpiration,</hi> (eaſily breathing forth rarified exhalations through the dilated Pores) and effectually cauſes <hi>Sweat</hi> being taken hot, (eſpecially compou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded without <hi>purgatiues</hi>) and the <hi>Body</hi> well happed accordingly. For as it ſeparates and eliminates <hi>Heteragene</hi> and ſuperfluous Humors <hi>per ſeceſſum,</hi> by <hi>Stoole,</hi> ſo doth it alſo therewithall, and by Evapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration euacuate <hi>Fumes</hi> and <hi>vapours</hi> of malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant quality and vicious condition, without expenſe of the <hi>Humidum radicale,</hi> or <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genium</hi> (the Foundation and food of Spirit and heat, and by conſequence of Life and Beeing) thereby preſeruing <hi>Natures</hi> rich <hi>Treaſures Corporall</hi> and <hi>Animall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It corrects and remedies <hi>Crudities,</hi> carmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates <hi>Winde,</hi> and diſcuſſes flatuous <hi>diſcurſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:19071:51"/>
and wringings in the body, ſtayes <hi>vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings</hi> by diuerſion, excites the <hi>Appetite,</hi> quenches <hi>Thirſt,</hi> enlarges the <hi>Pectoralls,</hi> and cauſes eaſie <hi>Spitting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It cures long <hi>Feuers, Quotidians,</hi> all <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitters</hi> and <hi>peſtilentialls,</hi> the <hi>Greene Sickneſſe, (Albas virginum Febres) Cachexias</hi> and all lent, tough and lingring Infirmities, <hi>bredd</hi> of the impurity of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſcera</hi> or of inuete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate obſtructions.</p>
               <p>It deoppilates and extenuates the ſtuft and diſtented <hi>Spleene,</hi> abates obeſe and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulent <hi>Bodies,</hi> and is very conducible for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſting and curing of all <hi>Diſtillations</hi> and defluxions to any part: It is auailable for <hi>Tooth-Ach, Inflamations</hi> of the <hi>Eyes, Vvula,</hi> and <hi>Almonds</hi> of the <hi>Throat,</hi> for the <hi>vertigo,</hi> and all infirmities of the <hi>Head, wombe</hi> and <hi>Bladder,</hi> both new and old; for all <hi>Cephalique</hi> Dolors and diſturbances through fumes and vapours, and for all <hi>Fluxes, Dropſies,</hi> and the <hi>Falling Euill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It helpes all <hi>Colds, Coughs, Aſthmaes,</hi> or diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult breathings, the <hi>Iaundiſe</hi> blacke and yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; <hi>Ill habits</hi> of the body, <hi>Putrifactions,</hi> hard <hi>Tumors,</hi> and all other ſwellings, <hi>wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring paines,</hi> ſtinging and fixed <hi>Aches</hi>; the <hi>Cholicke,</hi> the <hi>Stone,</hi> all <hi>Gouts,</hi> both the run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19071:51"/>
and the impacted, hot and cold, <hi>Palſies</hi> and all ill-affections of the Sinewes. It helps <hi>Salt Rheumes, Itches, Scabs, Byles, Botches,</hi> the <hi>Scorbuto,</hi> the <hi>Leprie,</hi> and other contagious Maladies, and the cure of all curable <hi>wounds</hi> and <hi>vlcers,</hi> (inward and outward) with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other defects and deformations <hi>Intus &amp; in Cute. Foetet anima? deformat Hircus?</hi> Make <hi>Panala</hi> thy ſweet Companion if thou hopeſt for helpe.</p>
               <p>It rectifies the <hi>Stomacke</hi> and erecting the Digeſtiue Facultie, furthers the <hi>Concoction</hi> &amp; <hi>Diſtribution</hi> of meat, comforts the <hi>Lungs</hi> and all the <hi>Pectorall parts,</hi> corroborates the <hi>heart,</hi> ſtrengthens the <hi>Liuer,</hi> purifies it and the whole <hi>Maſſe</hi> of <hi>Blood,</hi> and breeding laudable <hi>Chylus,</hi> impinguates <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>qualid and ſtarueling <hi>Bodies,</hi> by inhabling them in future to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come fat or faire and much better-liking.</p>
               <p>It cleeres the <hi>Sight,</hi> flories the <hi>Complexion,</hi> cherries the pallid <hi>Cheeke,</hi> quickens the <hi>Memory</hi> and all the <hi>Senſes, Internall</hi> and <hi>Externall,</hi> refocillates and exhilerates the <hi>Mind</hi> and <hi>Animall Faculties,</hi> incites and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hables furtherance to conception, nouriſhes and maintaines the Balſamique <hi>Mumie</hi> of the <hi>Bodie,</hi> increaſes youthfulneſſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tardates and keepes backe the approach and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19071:52"/>
ſeiſure of <hi>Old Age.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the frequent vſe of evacuating and emaciating dyets is a ſpeciall meane to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote <hi>Prolongation of Life,</hi> for that after them, the body becomes plumpe faire and almoſt new, through pure ſound fleſh, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration of youthfull vigor in ſome degree, as Oxen wrought leane, regaine the fleſh of young beefes by good paſturage.</p>
               <p>Touching diſeaſes which are wholly <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable,</hi> or thoſe whoſe legitimate cure is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perillous, this <hi>Panala</hi> is a moſt approued helpe producing ſuch ſalutarie fruits of <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation,</hi> (the ſecureſt and moſt commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble courſe of medication in ſuch caſes) as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed all expectation; for without any <hi>Dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> and incumbring <hi>Doo</hi> of dayly newed diſpenſings, it alleviates and mitigates all <hi>Symptomes</hi> of the ſickneſſe, which diſturbe the Patient, if he be but patient, to perſevere in competent continuing the Potion.</p>
               <p>By diſſoluing coagulate blood, it diſcuſſes and ſcatters inward contuſions, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues the body from putrifaction, and other perillous <hi>Symptomes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some men may perhaps expect I ſhould capitulate and euidence all the particulars, and inſtance both the perſons and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19071:52"/>
aſwell touching their <hi>Symptomes,</hi> as the mediate operation of <hi>Panala,</hi> for abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or abating at leaſt of their baynings or oppreſſing burthenings. This I grant had not beene impertinent to the worke, but, were I ſo punctually ſatisfactory, I ſhould doubtleſſe of many people bee branded for a <hi>Matchleſſe Mandevill</hi> in <hi>Hyperbolizing,</hi> maulger the magnifique good applauſe of <hi>Myriads</hi> of <hi>Patients,</hi> extolling it beyond the furtheſt extent of my prayſing Attributes to the operation of its <hi>Mechanique Spirits.</hi> To avoyd ſuch <hi>Stygmatique Raſures,</hi> and that my intended <hi>Manuall</hi> (of both parts) might not grow voluminous in tedious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances (which might perchance incurre, with others ſuſpect of fiction and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture) I propounded to my ſelfe, rather then to preſſe too much vpon prouoked patience, curſorily to point at particulars for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, well knowing that a word is enough to a man of good meaning, eſpecially if any thing verſt in Phyſicke (though ſuch haue moſt cauſe of cauill at this Medication which benefits the Patient, but brings little or no profit to the <hi>Phyſitian</hi> and <hi>Apothecarie,</hi>) for he will eaſily grant, that ſuch a Remedy may well be available in all diſeaſes ſaue in <hi>Nude</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:19071:53"/>
diſtempers <hi>ſine materia,</hi> which are ſeldome found in our <hi>cold</hi> and <hi>full-feeding Climates,</hi> yet ſuch may eaſily bee met withall by this medicable Potion.</p>
               <p>For as all <hi>Geometrique Figures,</hi> may bee meaſured by Triangle, ſo all Infirmities materiall and immateriall, may be medicated by <hi>Panala:</hi> Will you haue an excellent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoratiue for Conſumptions and Bodies em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maciate and ſpent with long lingring ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes? the Bag compounded without Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger with the Ingredience of meat of nutrient iuice, perboiled vntill the blood be in effect decocted away, and minced very ſmall both fleſh and bones, preſents you with a cup little inferiour in degree to a <hi>Chylus,</hi> which ſhall exceed all other preparations of food for eaſie digeſtion, fine and facile diffuſion into the veines and members and for copious Nutrition with leaſt quantity of excremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titious Reliques. To conclude;
<q>
                     <l>Would'ſt lumpiſh Melancholy medicate,</l>
                     <l>And gloomy Fumes at once euaporate?</l>
                     <l>My Straines croſſe canuaſt by brisk-witty Criticks,</l>
                     <l>Change Moods dull-moody to cheer'd-merry Crickets.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:19071:53"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the excellent cautionary virtues of Panala.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ature,</hi> the beſt <hi>Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix</hi> of mans <hi>liuelihood,</hi> not ignorant, that <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cavere Morbis quam cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare melius eſt,</hi> that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture preuention of mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies is better than the beſt medication for cure, (<hi>Magis quippe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandum eſt, omnino non pati, quàm à paſſionibus liberari,</hi>) duly aymes by daily endeauours to conſtitute and continue the body <hi>temperatum ad pondus,</hi> (as in Mans firſt creation) that it may be intire and perfect in ſtate of health to the laſt <hi>period of life,</hi> or at leaſt to conſerue the ſame in ſuch <hi>latitude of ſanitude</hi> as it was produced.</p>
               <p>As therefore euery intelligent and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious <hi>Hortulan</hi> is euer carefully curious in diligent cleering and curing his Plot of irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularities, ſuperfluities, weeds, incumbers and vndue Ballaſts, and of ſtoring and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing it with all commendable and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:19071:54"/>
accommodates: So prudent and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Nature,</hi> adminiſtring all things the beſt ſhe can, doth ſtill, without intermiſſion, <hi>moliri</hi> and labour the excretion and quitting the <hi>Bodie</hi> of all excrementitious, ſuperfluous and peccant <hi>Humours</hi> and Contents, with the ſupplying of all defects, and reforming of all <hi>deformations,</hi> which good effects could ſhe alwayes happily attaine vnto and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh, according to her intention, there ſhould neuer need any <hi>Phyſicall meanes</hi> to rectifie the ſtate, or preſerue the health of the Body.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>rebellious quality</hi> and <hi>ouer-maiſtring quantity</hi> of many potent <hi>oppoſites,</hi> together with the repugnance of ſtubborne and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed <hi>parts</hi> and <hi>paſſages</hi> (contracted many times by erring or vndue deuiating from the right adminiſtration or due mannage of the <hi>Six Non-naturalls</hi>) doth often delude and fruſtrate theſe her carefull intendments of their worthy ends.</p>
               <p>Now this <hi>noble medicine,</hi> a moſt ſingular inſtrument of <hi>Phyſick,</hi> (Natures Hand maid) powerfully oppugnes and reſiſts her <hi>oppoſites,</hi> and ioining with her in her ſalutary deſignes ſubdues and reduces them to her <hi>obedience,</hi> reſerates the ports and paſſages of the body,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19071:54"/>
and amandates and expells whatſoeuer is aduerſe or incongruent, and by conſequence diuerts a world of diſeaſes, and conſerues the health in good latitude.</p>
               <p>A boyſtrous <hi>rouzing Purge,</hi> like a <hi>rude Ramp</hi> that raſhly pluckes-vp the <hi>Herbes</hi> with the <hi>Weedes,</hi> ſhuffles all ſorts of <hi>Humors</hi> into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and promiſcuouſly with much vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to <hi>Nature</hi> eliminates and voids both <hi>good and bad,</hi> as well <hi>Euchimique Balſamaries</hi> as <hi>Cacochymique Bayners,</hi> whereby <hi>Nature</hi> is defatigated and debilitated, and the ſtate of the body much endammaged.</p>
               <p>But milde <hi>Panala,</hi> like a diſcreet <hi>Damſell,</hi> which preſerues wholeſome <hi>Herbes,</hi> and weeds-vp hurtfull <hi>Weeds,</hi> doth by eaſie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees gently, pleaſantly, and ſafely, (nor ouer-heating the body, nor perturbing the Patient) raiſe and remoue the intrenched enemy, and disburthens <hi>Nature</hi> of ſincere and meere peccant <hi>Humours,</hi> thereby pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing the ſucculent and ſalutary <hi>Iuices</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire and exempt both from <hi>euacuation</hi> and from incident <hi>corruption</hi> and <hi>infection,</hi> which would neceſſarily bee contracted by their continued mixture with the vnnaturall, if ſtill retained.</p>
               <p>To giue ſome particular inſtances for the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19071:55"/>
neceſſity and vſe of this preuenting Phyſick, giue me leaue here, more fully than before, to preſent vnto your view and conſideration the <hi>three Grande Colonells</hi> which vſually with their many <hi>troopes</hi> of <hi>Miſcreants</hi> aſſault and batter our Bulwarkes of Health, againſt all whoſe infeſting forces <hi>Panala</hi> is furniſht with ſuch munition, that all their miſchieuous machinations and deſignes, to demoliſh and ruinate the whole fabricke of Mans Edifice, are countermined, daſht and diſanuld.</p>
               <p>The three Chieftaines encamping againſt our Cittadell, are <hi>Cruditie, Rheume, Obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> and vnder their Colours <hi>Bands of Sica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> bloody <hi>Bandetti,</hi> doe bandy themſelues to bane our Bodies at leaſt, yea many times with ſtupendious tortures they diſtune and deſtroy the Heauenly Harmony of the Soule.</p>
               <p>Vnder <hi>Crudities</hi> Colours are encamped <hi>Cachexiaes, Hydropicall Diſeaſes, Oedemata</hi> or <hi>phlegmatique</hi> and ſerous <hi>Swellings,</hi> flatuous <hi>diſcurſions,</hi> and painfull <hi>wringings</hi> in the <hi>Ilia</hi> and <hi>Colon,</hi> the <hi>Lienterie</hi> or <hi>flux</hi> of <hi>Excrements</hi> and indigeſted viands, with many other great and long griefes; <hi>Imo, Cruditas aſſidua Mater eſt omnium ferè aegritudinum Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:19071:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>Thoſe who liue not orderly (<hi>ſobriè</hi>) doe daily, according to <hi>Leſſius,</hi> in his <hi>Hygiaſticon,</hi> make ſome additament of <hi>Crude Humors,</hi> which attracted into the veines &amp; diffuſed into the whole <hi>moles</hi> and <hi>bulke</hi> of the <hi>Body,</hi> as into a <hi>Spunge,</hi> (to the quantity of 100 <hi>Oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> in one yeere,) doe in tract of time putrifie and breed mortall diſeaſes, which cut off moſt men before their time. For almoſt all that dye of ſickneſſe before <hi>Old Age</hi> dye of this Cauſe.</p>
               <p>Amongſt all ſickneſſes marching after <hi>Cruditie</hi> I beg licenſe not to forget that nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Fyle of ſecret, but forward foes, <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine Wormes,</hi> thoſe treacherous <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> of our <hi>Microcoſmique Caſtle,</hi> which come for moſt part of crude, ſuperfluous <hi>Chylus,</hi> and rauening for the like become <hi>Robbers</hi> of <hi>Reſt, Reſtauration</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Theſe petty, <hi>puny Pygmies</hi> (ſubterranean ſpirits bred of <hi>Corruption</hi> and <hi>humid Heat</hi>) theſe pernicious <hi>pyoners</hi> and <hi>pyners</hi> of the <hi>Body,</hi> feed-on, deuoure, and conſume the good <hi>Iuices</hi> prouided to nouriſh and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the whole <hi>Bulke,</hi> which hauing the <hi>conuoy</hi> of Nouriſhment continualll cut-off, doth neceſſarily become leane, meager, and miſliking, and the <hi>Appetite</hi> many times inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:19071:56"/>
by reaſon the <hi>famelique</hi> or <hi>eſurient ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> are robd of the <hi>foizon</hi> of <hi>food,</hi> which the <hi>Mechanique</hi> ſhould worke-on to furniſh all the parts with congruent and competent food.</p>
               <p>Oftentimes the nutrient <hi>Succi</hi> being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>competent to ſatiate and glut their nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Gorges,</hi> they moleſt and torment the <hi>inteſtines</hi> (the very <hi>Beds</hi> they were bred in) with corrodant ſucking, cauſe the <hi>Cholicke,</hi> paines like to the <hi>Hypochondrique flatus</hi> (the <hi>Girdle</hi> of the <hi>Spleene) flux</hi> of the <hi>Bowells, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenſion</hi> and <hi>Inflation</hi> of the <hi>Belly,</hi> and diuers times ſtupendious <hi>paſſions,</hi> and in fine, moſt dolorous <hi>death</hi> by perforating and eating-thorough the Guts.</p>
               <p>Though therefore theſe <hi>Lumbrici,</hi> bred and nouriſht in the ſmall Guts (eſpecially) of the <hi>Chylous Iuices,</hi> being crude and pitui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, doe oft continue and quietly containe themſelues therein a long time, in ſome bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, without any manifeſt dammage or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience, and at length, ſans former diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery, cure or care, deſcend with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements into the <hi>Craſſa Inteſtina,</hi> and are with the ſame from thence eiected and caſt out by ſtoole, yet oftentimes in their hungry hunting after food they aſcend, creepe and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:19071:56"/>
crawle vp into the <hi>Ventricle,</hi> (yet ſometimes produced there of putrid Ballaſts) defatigate and tire the <hi>Stomacke</hi> with tiring, pulling and lugging, hinder concoction, cauſe much <hi>Dolour, Nauſeam</hi> and <hi>loathing of Meat, Dry Cough, Thirſt, Hickup, Vomitings,</hi> and vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous other violent and perillous accidents, and by gnawing, crawling about &amp; peſtring the <hi>Mouth</hi> of the <hi>Stomacke,</hi> make difficult ſwallowing, and worſe Symptomes.</p>
               <p>Yea, ſo wofully fatall are theſe accurſed <hi>Miſcreants</hi> many times to our weale, that they wrecke vs in their owne wrackes; for lying dead in the <hi>Bowels,</hi> till they bee putrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they ſend vp ſtinking vapours, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant fumes, which affect and infect both <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Head,</hi> cauſing <hi>Suffuſions</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taracts</hi> in the <hi>Eyes, Falling Evills, Alienation</hi> of the <hi>Minde, Palpitation</hi> of the <hi>Heart, Faintings, Swoondings, Cold</hi> and ill-ſented <hi>Sweats,</hi> inordinate <hi>Feuers</hi> with horrour and rigour, <hi>Trembling</hi> and <hi>diſſolution</hi> of the <hi>Body, Convulſions</hi> and other fearfull <hi>Symptomes,</hi> and other <hi>Concomitants</hi> of daingerous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. This multiplicious <hi>Band</hi> of bane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Miſcreants</hi> are the moſt timous and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent infeſters of the Bodies fabricke, not onely aſſaulting tender <hi>Infancy</hi> and <hi>Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:19071:57"/>
but euen ſetting vpon <hi>Manhood</hi> alſo, with their peſtiferous <hi>Troopes</hi> of <hi>Torturess</hi> which are many times found to ſwarme in malignant Fevers. And I hold it very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that the vntimely <hi>Death</hi> of moſt <hi>Children,</hi> may truly be attributed to <hi>Wormes,</hi> and other <hi>dints</hi> and <hi>effects dimaining</hi> from ſuch ſuperfluous and crude Indigeſtions. But this dainger (ſaith <hi>Leſſius</hi>) by well pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the body yeerly at <hi>Spring</hi> and <hi>Fall,</hi> is preuented, and the Life produced to verie Old Age.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Children</hi> therefore and all <hi>Students</hi> and others of ſmall exerciſe or ill Diet, it is moſt requiſite to vſe ſuch temperate Evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation euery yeere at ſuch times, and for all others againſt euery <hi>Climaterique</hi> or <hi>Seuenth</hi> and <hi>Nynth</hi> yeere, according to the Counſell of <hi>Taiſnerus,</hi> from <hi>Marſilius Ficinus,</hi> ſhewing that by helpe of <hi>Astrology</hi> and <hi>Phyſicke,</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall <hi>Death</hi> may be deferred. <hi>Sed haec pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rerga:</hi> Theſe wormes haue made me weaue too large a <hi>Webbe</hi> of courſe <hi>raw Thread:</hi> therefore no more of Colonell <hi>Cruditie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rhume</hi> muſters <hi>Inflamations</hi> of the <hi>Eyes,</hi> of the <hi>Almonds,</hi> of the <hi>Throat,</hi> of the <hi>Vunla:</hi> the <hi>Angina, Tooth-Ach, paines</hi> in the <hi>Eares,</hi> and others parts of the <hi>Head, Coughs,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19071:57"/>
griefes</hi> and weakneſſe of the <hi>Stomacke; Exco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riations,</hi> and <hi>Apostumes</hi> of the <hi>Lungs, Liuer, Reines</hi> and <hi>Bladder,</hi> ſtabbing <hi>Pleuriſies,</hi> pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Conſumptions, Fluxes</hi> of the <hi>Belly</hi>; the <hi>Cholicke</hi> and the <hi>Sciatica, Gouts</hi> of diuerſe ſorts, and <hi>Tumors</hi> againſt <hi>Nature: Deafnes</hi> and <hi>Blindneſſe, Palſies</hi> and mortal <hi>Apoplexſies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For this Diſtillation (<hi>Catarrbus,</hi> deflluxion, or falling of ſupervacuous humors from the Head into the ſubiected parts) yſſuing from the ventricle of the Braine, and from its <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vex</hi> and encompaſſing <hi>Meninges</hi> when tis more exuperant into the Inwards of the body, ſtirres vp diuers miſchiefes in our <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crocoſme</hi>: For ruſhing into the <hi>Roots</hi> or O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginalls of the <hi>Nerues,</hi> it cauſes <hi>Stupors, Tremblings, Palſies,</hi> and <hi>Apoplexies:</hi> into the <hi>Organs</hi> of the <hi>Senſes,</hi> it cauſes tabring in the <hi>Eares,</hi> and dulneſſe of <hi>Hearing,</hi> and Dim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Sight:</hi> into the <hi>Noſe, Stuffings</hi> and loſſe of <hi>Smelling</hi>; into the <hi>Iawes</hi> and rough <hi>Arterie, Cough</hi> and <hi>Hoarſneſſe</hi>; into the <hi>Lungs,</hi> the <hi>Aſthma</hi> and <hi>Conſumptions</hi>; into the <hi>Ventricle, Cruditie</hi> and <hi>Indigeſtion</hi>; into the <hi>Intestines, Flux</hi> of the <hi>Bowels,</hi> and from hence if it inſinuate it ſelfe into the <hi>Liuer-Veines</hi> (by the Meſaraicks) it thickens there and ſtuffes both veines and <hi>veſſels</hi> with Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19071:58"/>
Sometimes it ſallies and comes from without and aboue the <hi>Cranium</hi> or <hi>Skull,</hi> eſpecially from vnder the <hi>Skin</hi> of the <hi>Crowne</hi> (where the Extreames of the veines, creeping and caried by and thorow the face and fore-head or Temples, are beſtowed and terminated in and about the <hi>Verticall point</hi>) and then it paſſes and diſperſes into the <hi>eyes,</hi> into the <hi>Mandibles,</hi> the <hi>Teeth,</hi> the <hi>Necke,</hi> the <hi>Shoulders, Armes, Sides, Backe, Loynes, Hyps, Thighes,</hi> and in concluſion into all the <hi>Ioints</hi>; inſomuch that all <hi>Arthritique</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all <hi>Externall paines</hi> dimane from this <hi>Outward Defluxion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The laſt, not the leaſt of the <hi>Three-Chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi> is <hi>Obstruction,</hi> a <hi>Potent Foe,</hi> vigilant in his deſignes and neuer vnfurniſht of one <hi>Machine</hi> or other, <hi>Fire-workes, water-workes,</hi> and other <hi>Munition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Liuer</hi> is a <hi>maine marke</hi> of his Ayme, both becauſe it furniſhes all parts with proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and for that it lies open to his Battries, by reaſon, that the numerous deriuation of <hi>Venulae,</hi> both from the <hi>Port</hi> and <hi>Hollow-veine</hi> (through which two all the Alimentarie Iuices haue their Paſſages) is in moſt exile and ſlender branchlets (apt to bee oppilated and ſtopt with viſcid Humours) diſſipated
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19071:58"/>
and obliterated into the ſubſtance of that <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuchyma.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here he commands ouer <hi>Scirrhoſities,</hi> hard <hi>Swellings, Inflammations</hi> (to the fortifying of the Liuer ſometimes) <hi>Feuers, Fluxes, Iaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe</hi>; There <hi>Hydropique, Cachectique, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chochymique affects,</hi> Greene <hi>Sickneſſe,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Diſcolorations, putrifaction</hi> of <hi>Humours,</hi> and <hi>Atrophia</hi> (ſnailie extenuation or ſlow pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning away of the body) with Battries many moe.</p>
               <p>Now he leuels at the <hi>Gall,</hi> turnes the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained <hi>Choler</hi> to ſtony concretion, and diuerts the affluent to the diffuſion of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruginous <hi>Tinctures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hemorrhages</hi> and naturall Evacuations of Blood are ſuppreſt in both Sexes through his deſignements vpon the great veines, and vpon the <hi>Meſaraiques,</hi> the <hi>Hemorrhoids</hi> are ſtopt, and <hi>Melancholique</hi> and feuerous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections ſet to broach.</p>
               <p>By ſetting vpon the <hi>Miſt,</hi> Hee obfuſcates the <hi>Mind</hi> with colid fumes, col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>quates and waſts the Body and <hi>defaedates</hi> the skin.</p>
               <p>By attempts in the Inteſtines, he hurts the <hi>Digestion</hi> (occaſioning crudity of Stomacke) and hinders <hi>Ejection:</hi> ſometimes though ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome hee indurates and euen lapifies the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19071:59"/>
Phlegme heapt vp in the Cells of the <hi>Caecum</hi> and <hi>Colon,</hi> but many times ſtirs vp and raiſes ſtupendious windie Paſſions in the <hi>Ilia</hi> and greater <hi>guts,</hi> as if he meant by <hi>Mines</hi> to blow vp the maine Bulwerke with violent blaſts.</p>
               <p>For impeaching the free Conuoy of the <hi>Spirits</hi> by obſtructing their Conduits the <hi>Nerues</hi> and thereby muſtering-vp <hi>Suffuſions</hi> of the <hi>Eye, Palſies, Convulſions, Apoplexies, Epilepſies</hi> or the like; becauſe it may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerted, whether the inrolment of theſe belong to this Band or to ſome Regiments muſtering-vp maligne vapours, or other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile meanes, I leaue it to the ſubtile diſputes of deeper ſtraines.</p>
               <p>But I may not omit his obturating or contracting the Pores of the skin (whether by muſtering the cold and open ambient <hi>Ayre</hi> againſt the Maine, or by calling-in ſome ayerie or windie Percolation againſt any one Member) whereby excrementitious matter rarified into fuliginous vapours for exhalation and evaporation is reverberated and driuen backe againe. For this <hi>Reverbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> ſhuffles the <hi>Humors</hi> and the <hi>Spirits,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to confuſed <hi>Combustions,</hi> and all the <hi>Intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke Faculties</hi> into mutinous and tumultuous Routs to the grieuous pervert and great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbance
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19071:59"/>
of the <hi>Oeconomie</hi> of the <hi>Microcoſme</hi> and many times to the vtter ſubuerſion and ruine of the <hi>Fabricke.</hi> Beſides; who hath not heard of the <hi>Holla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Baliue</hi> &amp; of the <hi>Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>life</hi> of the <hi>Hundreds (Popular Agues, Plagues</hi> of thoſe parts) how frequently they infeſt theſe <hi>Fenny</hi> &amp; <hi>Mooriſh Flats?</hi> Neither of theſe walkes (and they are euer reſtleſſe) his <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ambulation</hi> (chiefly the <hi>Autumnall</hi>) but hees furniſht with a thouſand <hi>Warrant Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mants,</hi> to attach with <hi>Arreſt</hi> that will daunt the <hi>daring courage</hi> of the ſtouteſt <hi>Heart</hi> with ſhiuering cold, and trembling rigour; yea, more, before he leaue <hi>fingring him on whom</hi> he once faſtens his hold, he will amate his <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> melt his <hi>marowie</hi> and <hi>brawnie ſtrength,</hi> and powre out his haughty <hi>Spirits</hi> in ſordid <hi>Sweats.</hi> And doth the <hi>Vp-land</hi> Countries ſcape and goe Scot freee from ſuch bainfull <hi>Arreſts?</hi> ſhew me the Towne can truly tell and auow it ſmells not of the <hi>Summons</hi> of a <hi>Trienniall <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſitation</hi> (at leaſt) by ſome <hi>Epedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mique Diſeaſe</hi> or other? If the <hi>blacke Ague</hi> (ſo the Country calls her frequent but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome gueſt, <hi>Synochum putridam maligna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi>) the <hi>Meaſils, ſmall Pocks, Tertian</hi> or <hi>Quart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> feuer wil be ſure to haue a fling amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: And few or none goe about to aske or once
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:19071:60"/>
to queſtion them, but let them paſſe <hi>impune</hi> as too potent or too maſterfull to be dealt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. For all theſe miſcreants this mild medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a dainty &amp; deliuer <hi>Superſedeas,</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the <hi>Arreſt,</hi> &amp; ſeldome fails of an authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique <hi>Liberate,</hi> to deliuer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all <hi>dures</hi> of ſuch <hi>fellon faitors.</hi> Nay, though hee's no right <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> nor a true <hi>Arrant Bailiffe,</hi> that loues not a <hi>Cup</hi> of nappy <hi>Ale,</hi> yet whoſoeuer's perfumed with a <hi>Fortnight-ſent</hi> of my <hi>Ale,</hi> hees ſped of a <hi>Spell</hi> that will not fail to <hi>fright-away</hi> all ſuch <hi>Miſcreant ſpirits</hi> from neerer approach.</p>
               <p>For noble <hi>Panala (Pentheſilea</hi> like armed at all points) paſſing corporally by <hi>veines</hi> and other <hi>veſſells,</hi> and <hi>ſpiritually</hi> by inviſible <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirations</hi> into all the members and dimenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the body (<hi>per totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> transfluxilis et perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabilis</hi>) tufts and hunts out al ſuperfluous and vitious contents, and ſerrits them forth from out their lurking <hi>Holds</hi> and <hi>Dens,</hi> by means whereof no matter being left for putrifaction nor for obſtruction, the whole body actuates in free perſpirability, and the <hi>Calidum Inna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> no way obrute but freed from extincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yeeldes to no forraigne contagion, nor ſtoopes to inbred corruption, but ſtoutly and ſtrongly marches againſt, encounters, foiles and eliminates all <hi>malignities.</hi> For by
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:19071:60"/>
attenuating, abſterging and euacuating, it quits all the <hi>materiall cauſes</hi> of thoſe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther morboſities, intercepts and cuts-off their conuoyes of Munition (whether con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in vitious or ſuperfluous Humors, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition or exceſſe of nutrient iuices, or other contents, or ſtraightneſſe of the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges) and by rectifying and roborating the <hi>principalls,</hi> remedies the diſtemper and imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility of the <hi>parts,</hi> and diuerts or quaſhes their miſchieuous deſignes, and laſtly by congruent <hi>aſſociation</hi> to <hi>Nature</hi> and by equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and proportionate <hi>contrarietie</hi> to <hi>Sickneſſe,</hi> it conſerues and maintaines the <hi>ſtate</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> in good latitude of <hi>Health,</hi> repells in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congruent diſeaſes, and effectually repaires lapſed and impaired ſanitude.</p>
               <p>Such and ſo manifeſt, with many more, howſoeuer theſe attributes may ſeeme to many men to be too many, are the virtues and effects of this duly compoſed and truly impregnated <hi>Panala,</hi> eſpecially if it be (as it alwayes ought to be) miniſtrred <hi>Medica manu, quae vniuerſalia particularibus, ordinata &amp; rationali methodo, accommodata, adhibet</hi>; otherwiſe, it is (like euery other Medicine) but a <hi>Caruers toole</hi> in a <hi>Carters hand,</hi> whoſe wooden workmanſhip quickly marres, but
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19071:61"/>
neuer makes a good <hi>Sculpture.</hi> Tis not the inſtrument but the knowledge and dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity of the Artiſt, which makes-vp the <hi>Maſter-piece</hi> in euery <hi>Artifice: Argus</hi> his <hi>eares</hi> had kept-open his <hi>eyes</hi> to keepe-on his <hi>head,</hi> if better <hi>fingring</hi> than <hi>Parts</hi> rude hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, though vpon <hi>Apollos Harpe,</hi> had not charmed them with harmonious melodie to betray their double charge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of the cheape and preſt accommodations of Panala.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any <hi>irrationall creatures,</hi> led by the meere <hi>Inſtinct of Nature,</hi> doe, vpon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of need, betake themſelues to th'uſe of medicinable meanes for recouery of health and cure of hurts: But <hi>Man,</hi> illuminated with the Diuine Beames of a reaſonable Soule, is many times (more than onely the <hi>hominum vulgi</hi>) much more ſottiſh and more abſurdly conceited in this kinde, than meere bruits, (<hi>Birds, Beaſts, Fiſh, Reptilia &amp; Inſecta etiam</hi>)
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19071:61"/>
which we know doe vſually vſe (with much labour many times to finde or fetch) Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call helpes for their hurts and infirmities, where he is ſo farre from the intertaine of the Practicke or approue of the Art, that hee condemnes the <hi>ſacred ordinance,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> himſelfe created (and gaue to our firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents) diuine Oracles ſo much and ſo oft commend, and prophane Authors of all ſorts (<hi>Philoſophers, Hiſtorians, Orators, Poets</hi>) cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laud; in ſo much that <hi>Donzellin</hi> holds them worthy to be abandoned of all mankind (<hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticyras relegandos</hi>) which dare <hi>ſeens ſentire,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine an ill thought of it, and doubtleſſe would hold him vnworthy the comfort of any creature that ſhould <hi>collinire</hi> brand or beſmeere this heauenly gift of the Creator with the foule clouted terme of Impoſture or Iuggling. Yet for all this fond fancy againſt <hi>Phyſicke,</hi> the ſillieſt <hi>Man</hi> of a <hi>million,</hi> when he ſees his <hi>Iade</hi> tainted with the <hi>Yellowes,</hi> or his <hi>Beaſt</hi> infected with the <hi>Murren,</hi> will haſte for helpe to ſome <hi>Horſleach,</hi> and count it fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality, and good gaine too, to recouer a Cart-horſe with a Crowne coſt (ſometimes) in hope to recouer ten. Oh, but to beſtow fiue ſhillings in <hi>Phyſicke</hi> vpon his owne <hi>kar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſe,</hi> tis a peſlance expenſe, the quarter
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:19071:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>
charge will goe farre in <hi>Ale-berries</hi> and <hi>Caw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dells,</hi> and a few pence will furniſh the whole <hi>Manie</hi> with <hi>Treacle</hi> and <hi>Aquavitae:</hi> if theſe and a pepperd <hi>Poſſill</hi> with a <hi>Head-bind</hi> helpe not, then farewell my neighbour <hi>Hide-bound,</hi> he'le rather dye thrice, than deale once with other Drugs than ſuch as his <hi>Maud</hi> can maſh, and his fore-fathers vſed to meddle with for their <hi>Medeale.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus many people, euen whole <hi>Myriads</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> through their ſuperſtitious aduerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt <hi>Phyſicke,</hi> or penurious pedling with <hi>paltry traſh,</hi> or idle tempering with tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerlie <hi>Phyſmicaries,</hi> doe ordinarily, in their <hi>penny wiſe wiſedomes,</hi> exhauſt and conſume both <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Goods</hi> in long languiſhings, which might haue beene eaſily remedied and redeemed by the timous counſell of an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt <hi>Artiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For inſtance; Is it not a world of wonder, to ſee, what palpable poore neglect is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly caſt-vpon the curatiue care euen of <hi>Furie Feuers,</hi> chiefly <hi>Quartanes?</hi> doth not almoſt euery <hi>Man</hi> (though nigh mated with ſtupendious <hi>ſymptomes</hi> and <hi>paſſions</hi>) feed his fond fancy with this <hi>Selfe-ſoothed Sooth-ſay,</hi> Tis but an <hi>Ague</hi> and muſt haue the Courſe; <hi>Incurſu nimirum ſuo Quartanam non eſſe impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diendam,</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:19071:62"/>
this miſconceiued <hi>Tenet</hi> muſt blanch and roborate their ſorry Conceipts, which further alſo to colour, one foiſts a piece of <hi>Piſo,</hi> ſnatcht from the Sequence, for his plea, and boldly auowes from <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> that of all <hi>Feuers</hi> the <hi>Quartane</hi> is the eaſieſt and the ſafeſt, and vindicates from other great Diſeaſes, as <hi>Convulſions</hi> and <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepſies.</hi> Another dights-vp <hi>Auiſoes</hi> Doore with the <hi>Ding-dong Prouerb, Pro Febre Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tana ràrò ſonat Campana,</hi> He flatly tells you, the <hi>Bell</hi> ſeldome tolls for a <hi>Quartane,</hi> neuer conſidering that <hi>Erratique</hi> and <hi>Quotidian Agues</hi> deriued from groſſe and pituitous <hi>Humors,</hi> putrifying (whether turning <hi>atribi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary</hi> or otherwiſe) doe for moſt part turne <hi>Baſtard-Quartanes,</hi> and that <hi>Quartanes</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitant with vitious <hi>Liuer</hi> and other <hi>veſſells</hi> ill affected doe often lapſe the <hi>Loath-Phyſick</hi> into <hi>Scyrrhoſities</hi> of <hi>Liuer, Spleene, Reines,</hi> and breed <hi>Dropſies, Iaundiſe, Hypochondriaque Melancholly,</hi> or ſome other ſcuruy Diſeaſe, of which euer and anon diuers are dropping away, or elſe drooping in deſperate languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, to teach them and all ſuch <hi>Selfe-ſoothing heretiques</hi> in this kind, that this <hi>Opprobrium Medicorum</hi> (the <hi>Quartane</hi>) ſpringing from the impatience of inconſtant <hi>Patients,</hi> nor
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:19071:63"/>
brooking nor abiding any regular courſe for due cure, can quickly turne to a ſharpe and a tough <hi>Scourge</hi> to ſchoole them with a <hi>Pay-Home</hi> by attourney, ſhall make them cry <hi>pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caui</hi> for ſo fond ſleighting ſalutary <hi>Caues</hi> and medicinable <hi>Cautions</hi> for due Cure.</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Men</hi> are no markes for the bent of my aymes, I am well contented my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition ſuits none of their humours; why ſhould a man ſtudy the cure or the care of them, who are ſo careleſſe of themſelues? <hi>Fatuitatis ſuae poenas luent,</hi> let them reap the rotten-ripe bitter fruits of their owne follies, and poſt to anticipated ends before their times for contempt of the meanes, or ling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring miſerably dye to ſaue charges, if it bee ſauing to be diſhabled, by long <hi>languors,</hi> of following their Callings which call for their perſonall mannage, without medication, for moſt part, very ſlowly made compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible.</p>
               <p>For ſuch as blow-vp <hi>Trifle-Fees</hi> with tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid <hi>put-off</hi> of wind-puft Complement, let their empty bladders freely float-on their dung-hill puddles and turne ayrie Bubbles, till their glitterand ſelfe-ſwolne greatneſſe, with the Launce of inward Pride (not of my Pen) burſt into <hi>Hally-water</hi> to beſmeare their
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:19071:63"/>
browes in their baſe bowes to <hi>Mammon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For thoſe who once aſſured of cure, by honeſt care of the carefull Phyſitian, doe ſtraight grow <hi>ſight-ſicke, eare-ſicke, thought-ſicke</hi> of him, and in ſtead of remunerating his merits, doe nauſeate his <hi>Face, Name, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory</hi>; let their penance bee daily to be verſt in publique profeſſion of this foure-fold ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, till ſhame, conſcience, or dread of Duell with the laſt auerſion, worke his conuerſion from penurious baſeneſſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Deus.</speaker>
                     <l>Vm nigris aegrum propè Mors circumu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lat alis</l>
                     <l>Funeſtamque aciem funera jamque parat,</l>
                     <l>Tum me promiſſis beat &amp; domus omnis adorat,</l>
                     <l>Me<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſalutiferum clamitat eſſe Deum.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Angelus.</speaker>
                     <l>Paulò vbi conualuit, paulum de numine noſtro</l>
                     <l>Ceſſit, &amp; in noſtris auribus iſt a ſona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>,</l>
                     <l>Tu Caelo nobis demiſſus es Angelus alto,</l>
                     <l>Praemia quae veſtri quanta laboris erant?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Homo.</speaker>
                     <l>Iam<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Machaonia magis &amp; magis arte leuatus,</l>
                     <l>Cum ſedet ante focum progreditur<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> tripes,</l>
                     <l>Oh Homo non fruſtrà, tantos ſubijſſe labores</l>
                     <l>Noſces, quod reſtat tu modò tolle malum.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:19071:64"/>
                     <speaker>Daemon.</speaker>
                     <l>Aſt ego, ſi penitus jam ſanum praemia poſcam,</l>
                     <l>Ille Deus pridem, mox Cacodaemon ero;</l>
                     <l>Aurea verba vola<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, mala vox ciru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>volat aureis,</l>
                     <l>Limine me, torvo lumine, pellis onus.</l>
                  </sp>
               </q>
               <p>I haue transformed the laſt lines of the Doctors gradarie Diſreguard, and tranſlated it thus;
<q>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>God.</speaker>
                        <l>Whilſt ore thy down-ſick Head pale Death doth houer,</l>
                        <l>And's eager Stoops to truſſe thy Soule affright thee,</l>
                        <l>Faire Heights of Bounty bleſſe Me, all doe honour,</l>
                        <l>All Dei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ie, all God of Health doe height Me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Angell.</speaker>
                        <l>Streight as thy State to better plight inclines,</l>
                        <l>I'me ſtyl'd an Angell ſent from Heauen to cure Thee,</l>
                        <l>My Deitie to Demi-God declines,</l>
                        <l>Yet ô, what golden words thou giu'ſt t'allure me!</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                        <l>Still, as thy ſtrength doth wax, my worſhip waines,</l>
                        <l>Chaire, Staffe and Stomacke, all things gin to eaſe thee;</l>
                        <l>Good Sir now ſaiſt, yet happy are thy paines,</l>
                        <l>Root out the Reliques and Ile richly pleaſe Thee.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Deuill.</speaker>
                        <l>But to full freedome bayl'd from bayn-full Euill,</l>
                        <l>If then my carefull Viſits ſpeake due prize,</l>
                        <l>God-Head, Gold-Heights forgot, thou dubſt me Deuill</l>
                        <l>And (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                              <desc>••••</desc>
                           </gap>uie) con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ures forth with toruie Eyes.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thus, whom with painfull Care J'ue cur'd my Patient,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The Sicke this muſt I perſonate, turne Patient.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:19071:64"/>To meet with ſome miſconceiuings of better minded people, who, willingly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace <hi>Gods Ordinance,</hi> and the vſe of ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry meanes of cure by <hi>Phyſicke,</hi> but not well apprehending, heeding or remembring their directions for vſage of the medicines pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed or giuen vnto them, wrong them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and croſſe the <hi>Phyſician</hi> in their prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous applications, I haue ſelected and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon the compoſition of <hi>Panala,</hi> the preſcript of whoſe Adminiſtration and vſage is ſo plaine and familiar, no man, of any braine, need fall into any miſpriſe or miſtake, much leſſe commit the palpable groſſe Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, which many runne into in moſt other medicable courſes, in which euery Practiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner finds <hi>miſtakings</hi> to be as vſuall as <hi>Eating</hi> and <hi>Drinking.</hi> Here's one champes his <hi>Pils,</hi> and for diſguſt ſpits them out with an <hi>out, out,</hi> another ſtuphes or bathes with his <hi>potion,</hi> a <hi>Third</hi> drinkes his <hi>Clister-ſtuffe,</hi> or eates his <hi>Suppoſitarie</hi>; and there's one turnes <hi>Electua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> to <hi>vnguents, Injections</hi> to <hi>Gargariſmes, &amp; vice verſa</hi>; but he that's ſo warie, hee will not turne th'other furniſhment to the Task of his <hi>Teeth,</hi> yet miſtakes the <hi>morning-Draught</hi> for the <hi>Euenings,</hi> and either doubles or diuides th'appointed <hi>Doſe.</hi> But in th'vſe and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:19071:65"/>
of <hi>Panala,</hi> there are nor curioſities, nor varieties of the Medication, to beget miſpriſions, only a conſtant <hi>Courſe,</hi> without any <hi>Cumber,</hi> to drinke a <hi>Cup</hi> of <hi>Ale</hi> twice or thrice a day, as is ſhewed <hi>Cap.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Panala</hi> alſo happily preuents and cuts off the fond irreſolution which ordinarily poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſes many <hi>Patients,</hi> who hauing taken a <hi>Doſe</hi> or two of any <hi>Preſcript,</hi> and not finding manifeſt preſent-eaſe thereby, doe ſtraight entertaine a ſtrong and a reſolute aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning of all further progreſſe in <hi>Phyſicke,</hi> when that they tooke was perſcribed but in <hi>Nature</hi> of a <hi>preparatiue</hi> to the maine Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, either onely to prepare the <hi>veſſells</hi> or the <hi>Humors,</hi> or to comfort the <hi>Spirits,</hi> and enha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Nature</hi> to hold out for the cure. For com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the <hi>Port</hi> and cuſtomable <hi>Habit</hi> of meere <hi>Ale</hi> or common Drinkes, what <hi>Man</hi> amongſt a <hi>Million</hi> will be ſo wilfull or incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate, as, hauing paſt the <hi>Pykes</hi> of <hi>pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>preparation</hi> of the <hi>Potion,</hi> that he will euer entertaine a thought of refuſing or gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ouer ſo preſt, ſo familiar and ſo freindly a <hi>Companion,</hi> before the laſt <hi>Cup</hi> conclude and ſtrike the <hi>parting blow</hi> of a comfortable kind <hi>Farewell?</hi> And the reſolued <hi>Patient</hi> by conſtant perſeuering in propining and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:19071:65"/>
following the <hi>Medicine,</hi> may with good aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance propound and promiſe to himſelfe truly to reape the ripe and wholſome <hi>fruits</hi> of the principall Intention by beneficent <hi>Medication,</hi> which ſo many daily miſſe of through impatient and prepoſterous haſt to reach and reape them before <hi>Maturitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For thoſe therefore that in <hi>Heart</hi> doe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the honeſt <hi>phyſitian</hi> as the <hi>Inſtrument</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> ordained for their <hi>Health,</hi> and like good <hi>Tenants</hi> for <hi>Terme</hi> of <hi>Life</hi> cary conſcionable minds, to keepe the <hi>Edifices</hi> of their <hi>Bodies</hi> committed to their care and cuſtody, in good and ſound plight, and to repaire <hi>dilapidations</hi> and <hi>decayes</hi> reſpectiuely, although perhaps neither very able to beſtow much coſt, nor in caſe to ſpare much time in <hi>Quest</hi> and <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit</hi> of ſuch their care, haue I publiſhed the benefique operation of this moſt accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date Medicine, that I may in ſome reaſonable meaſure gratifie ſuch their ingenuous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects: And for further gratification, I haue at all times <hi>Funds</hi> or <hi>Bags</hi> of the <hi>Ingredients</hi> in readineſſe made vp compleat (as well without <hi>purgatiues,</hi> as with them) and fitted for <hi>Infuſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Bag</hi> is <hi>portable</hi> (in <hi>pocket</hi> or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies) many <hi>Hundred Miles,</hi> and durable in
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:19071:66"/>
full vigor and virtue, thirty or forty dayes at leaſt, yea many Moneths, being made vp without <hi>Raiſons,</hi> ſo that any man may furniſh himſelfe therewith in his trauell or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and at his pleaſure and leaſure, when he comes home, infuſe and vſe it without <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity</hi> or <hi>Incumber.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the <hi>Body</hi> thereof, let that bee no Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of Imputation to any Impeach of the Reputation, ſeeing, as I haue ſaid, it <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedes</hi> the Additaments which many famous Medicines of other Formes need Bodying with all for apt taking and <hi>vehieulation,</hi> in that being compoſed into potable Liquor, impregnated with the <hi>Eſſentiall parts</hi> and <hi>Spirits</hi> (no whit evaporated with forraigne heat) of euery <hi>Ingredient</hi> diffuſed in and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated with ordinarie Drinks, there can be no vehicle or better Conuoy of medicina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble qualities into the <hi>Members</hi> &amp; <hi>Remotes</hi> of the <hi>body.</hi> The purchaſe of <hi>Panala</hi> is too cheap for ſo precious a medicine; for the <hi>price</hi> is but fiue ſhillings (with directions for the vſe) and the ſame ſeruing for two Gallons of <hi>Ale</hi> will furniſh two Patients for ſeuen, or One 14. daies <hi>Phyſicke,</hi> as aforeſaid: ſo that a man may haue two <hi>Doſes</hi> or <hi>Draughts</hi> for a <hi>Tester,</hi> which in other Medications is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:19071:66"/>
doubled and many times trebled for one <hi>Purge:</hi> but compounded without <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> you haue it for the moitie of the charge, and this makes a moſt delicate Drinke (of like quantity) of much more true worth than <hi>Bragat</hi> or <hi>Metheglin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Panala</hi> alſo ſupercedes and ſaues the charge of <hi>preparations,</hi> for cutting of humors and of <hi>vehiculums,</hi> for diffuſion and cariage into all parts of the body, both which helps are neceſſarily required in moſt other <hi>ſorts</hi> and <hi>formes</hi> of <hi>Phyſicke.</hi> Beſides that, this ſparing or temperate <hi>Diet,</hi> requiſite in the vſe hereof, ſaues more money in <hi>meat</hi> and <hi>Drinke,</hi> then the coſt this Phyſicke comes vnto: and for the ſecond <hi>Infuſion</hi> of the ſame <hi>Bag,</hi> it laſts no leſſe time, and coſts no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing you know but new <hi>Raiſons,</hi> and <hi>Ale,</hi> yet is it of excellent vſe, either for <hi>Meale-Drinke</hi> in th'vſe of th'other, or after th'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is ſpent for rectifying and confirming the <hi>State</hi> of the <hi>Body.</hi> For the new and Nude <hi>Infuſion</hi> compounded without <hi>Purgers,</hi> the proportion finds a man altering Phyſicke for a matter of two pence <hi>per Diem,</hi> (beſides <hi>Ale</hi>) except it bee made a <hi>Meal-drinke,</hi> which in moſt caſes is needleſſe.</p>
               <p>Touching the <hi>Time</hi> taken-vp in continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:19071:67"/>
the take of this Phyſicke, I may ſay, <hi>Sat cito, vt ſat ſcite, fit Medicatio, quae ſat bene: Good ſpeed</hi> is euermore <hi>beſt ſpeed.</hi> But this ſalue may well be ſaued, here's ſeldome any <hi>Soare</hi> to need it. For in <hi>Cautionare courſes,</hi> for Prevention of Infirmities, it ſpends time, but loſes none, becauſe it interrupts no bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, ſaue when the Inclemencie of the Heauens giue <hi>Caueat</hi> of <hi>Keepe-in,</hi> to auoyd the iniuries of ill weather, which no wiſe man will vpon any <hi>Naturall Flux</hi> expoſe his body vnto: and in the <hi>Arreſt</hi> of <hi>Sicknes</hi> 'tis the Infirmity, not the <hi>Phyſicke,</hi> that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines him within Doores, not ſo much for ſhelter and couert from the frownes and worſe effects of the Skye, as for the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated <hi>Dures</hi> enforced by the <hi>Diſeaſe</hi>: beſides, that if vrgent occaſions call forth into in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate weather from <hi>Cautionary courſes,</hi> he may intermit a day or more, as in <hi>Cap.</hi> 6. is laid downe.</p>
               <p>Nor doth the medicine giuen ouer, or ended after moderate continuance, conſtipate or leaue the body Coſtiue, ouer-dryed, heated, debilitated or exhauſted of <hi>Balſamique iuices,</hi> nor affected with any diſtemper, ill <hi>Impreſſion</hi> or deprauing affects co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tracted or dimaning from the ſame (as is already declared <hi>Cap.</hi> 9.)
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:19071:67"/>
but well diſpoſed, vigorous, actiue and full of <hi>Spirits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that is any thing verſt in the <hi>Practique</hi> of <hi>Phyſicke,</hi> may eaſily obſerue and find, that <hi>Nature</hi> euermore beſt accords and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>operates with Medicines which aggrate and oblectate the <hi>Senſes,</hi> but ſhewes her ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe in refractary reluctation againſt the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant, ſo that euen <hi>Stomatiques,</hi> giuen for comfort and fortification, if they be very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grate, doe bring forth little <hi>Good,</hi> but in ſtead of ſubuening and helping, they ſubvert and hurt the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>entricle:</hi> what <hi>fruit</hi> then can bee expected from <hi>Phyſicke,</hi> whoſe <hi>Diſgust</hi> and auerſneſſe to <hi>Taſt</hi> and <hi>Stomacke</hi> breed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s that nauſeous loathing in <hi>Nature</hi> which peruerts her operatiue Faculties in all parts of the Body?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beſt practitioners</hi> therefore, to preuent all incongruences, and to gratifie the <hi>patient,</hi> do clarifie, color, edulcorate, acidulate &amp; aroma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>Syrupes, Iulapes, Apozemes, Electuaries,</hi> and other <hi>Formes</hi> of <hi>phyſicke,</hi> reſpectiuely, palliating <hi>pills</hi> with gilding, when they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not paliate their bitterneſſe. For when fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar <hi>Obiects</hi> delight the <hi>Eye,</hi> recreate the <hi>Senſory</hi> of <hi>ſmelling,</hi> pleaſe the <hi>Pallate,</hi> comfort the <hi>Stomake,</hi> and exhilerate the <hi>Heart,</hi> (that
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:19071:68"/>
                  <hi>Fountaine</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi>) they Sympathyze and ſide with <hi>Nature,</hi> eleuate the <hi>Spirits,</hi> ſtimulate and ſtirre vp the languiſhing <hi>Appetite,</hi> rouze her drowſie <hi>Forces</hi> and <hi>Faculties (vitall</hi> and <hi>Animall</hi>) ſopite in ſickneſſe, and reſuſcitate and refreſh the <hi>Natiue Heat</hi> which alone concocts, digeſts and calmes <hi>Diſeaſes,</hi> and by extenuating the <hi>Thicke,</hi> and clenſing the viſcous <hi>Humors,</hi> and by expediting <hi>Obstruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> faciliates and promotes the operations both of <hi>Food</hi> and <hi>phyſicke,</hi> inſomuch that <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> compounded of ſome <hi>Ingredients</hi> which of themſelues would ſubuert or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbe the <hi>Stomacke,</hi> if they be condited, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and accommodated with good <hi>Aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiques,</hi> they are little or nothing offenſiue to the <hi>principall</hi> parts, and more ſafely purge excrementitious <hi>Humors</hi> by <hi>Stoole,</hi> as alſo by <hi>vomit</hi> reſpectiuely.</p>
               <p>My care therefore was ſo to compound my <hi>Panala,</hi> that beſides the little <hi>Coſt</hi> and leſſe <hi>Cumber,</hi> it neither offends the <hi>Eye</hi> with the loathed <hi>Obiect</hi> of a muddy <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> nor the <hi>ſmell</hi> with ill <hi>vapor</hi> or <hi>ſauor,</hi> nor <hi>palate</hi> nor <hi>ventricle</hi> with diſguſt or ingrate <hi>Reliſh,</hi> but it is a depured, cleere, ſweet, delicate and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular <hi>Extract</hi> impregnated with the ſuccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Iuices,</hi> ſincere <hi>Spirits</hi> and ſingular <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues</hi>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:19071:68"/>
of <hi>Specifique Ingredients.</hi> Moreouer, 'tis of a moderate <hi>Temperature</hi> indifferently accommodable to euery <hi>Age, Sex,</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,</hi> and ſo familiar and pleaſing to the <hi>Sight, Smell, Taſte</hi> and <hi>Stomacke,</hi> and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the <hi>principall Members,</hi> that the moſt curious <hi>palates</hi> and daintieſt <hi>Bodies</hi> may and doe <hi>drinke</hi> it, and <hi>digeſt</hi> its operations with <hi>Delight</hi>: yet for all this will I not arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate the title of a <hi>Purum Putum Areanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> vnto my <hi>Panala,</hi> though conſidering the whole progreſſe of <hi>preparations</hi> of the <hi>Potion</hi> (from the growing of the <hi>Graine,</hi> to the drawing of the <hi>Drink</hi>) it may well merit the eſteeme of a ſingular <hi>Extract</hi> and <hi>Spagyrique Medicine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Much leſſe will I bee ſo abſurd an Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to attribute vnto one and the ſame In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, founded vpon irrationall <hi>Empiricie</hi> or other confuſed <hi>Intention,</hi> the potent Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede of all other <hi>Phyſicke,</hi> and ſo to gull the world or beget an opinion, that my ſingle <hi>Panala</hi> is ſimply an abſolute <hi>Panacea,</hi> which <hi>inſtar vniuerſalis cujuſdam vniuerſaliſſimi,</hi> is able to cure all <hi>diſeaſes</hi> in all <hi>Perſons,</hi> and at all <hi>Times</hi> promiſcuouſly without other <hi>meanes.</hi> One <hi>Laſt</hi> fits not the <hi>Size</hi> and <hi>Shape</hi> of euery <hi>Foot,</hi> nor can any one Medicine bee of that admirable efficacie, that it can alone perform
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:19071:69"/>
all the Intentions of Medication in all <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions</hi> and <hi>Complexions</hi> (no leſſe nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and variable than <hi>Faces</hi>) and in all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of <hi>Sicknes</hi> without diſtinction: yet thus much giue me leaue to affirme and ſay of it, though I doe intirely honour the <hi>Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls</hi> of <hi>Phyſicke</hi> found in the moſt exact ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations of our <hi>Fore-Fathers</hi> (the <hi>Grandees</hi> of <hi>Medicine</hi>) that for virtues &amp; accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, this <hi>Potion</hi> it is not eaſily paralleld; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, it hath this ſpeciall <hi>prerogatiue,</hi> that it is in a manner a <hi>Compendium</hi> for all cures, the <hi>baſe</hi> &amp; <hi>perpendicular</hi> that meaſure all <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angles</hi>; or rather the <hi>Triangle</hi> which meaſures (euen without either of them) all <hi>Figures,</hi> and may eaſily be reduced to the equivalence of a <hi>Circular Scale,</hi> or <hi>Sector</hi> accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable and applicable to euery <hi>Chart</hi> or <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſion,</hi> ſith it is richly ſuited with <hi>prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, evacuatiues, cordialls</hi> and <hi>Rectifyers,</hi> and may eaſily be impregnated with the ſpirits of <hi>Spaw Waters,</hi> with more ſalutary preualence than can bee deriued from crude ſprings, whoſe farre blazed fame ſuperſtition rings ſo loud.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:19071:69"/>
               <head>A ſummary plaine Direction for the Patients preparation and vſage of Panala, with the Coſt and virtues thereof in generall.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Bag</hi> of <hi>Ingredients</hi> is commonly here to be had of me ready bound vp for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient <hi>carriage</hi> to any <hi>place</hi> in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the weight and <hi>bulke</hi> ſmall, the <hi>coſt</hi> little, for I afford it for <hi>fiue ſhillings</hi> with Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, (for halfe the <hi>money</hi> without) yet haue I enlarged it for a bottle more of <hi>Liquor</hi> than ordinary to laſt and ſerue one <hi>man</hi> a full <hi>fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night,</hi> that it may bee continued two whole <hi>Quarters</hi> of the <hi>Moone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With a <hi>pebble ſtone,</hi> a forked <hi>ſticke</hi> or other <hi>force,</hi> ſinke and keepe downe the <hi>Bag of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients</hi> to the <hi>bottome</hi> of a ſmall <hi>Rundlet,</hi> vſuall <hi>Steane, Stand</hi> or <hi>Ale kanne,</hi> and tunne vnto it two <hi>Gallons</hi> of <hi>New-ale,</hi> and put looſe into the Veſſell <hi>three ounces</hi> of <hi>Raiſons</hi> of the Sunne (if there be none in the <hi>Bag</hi>) cleane waſht and ſlit halfe through, yet not opened nor ſtoned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yeſt</hi> the <hi>Liquor</hi> very well and bung it vp cloſe, or, with a cloth couer the <hi>Stand</hi> or <hi>open veſſell,</hi> and ſhift the <hi>yeſt</hi> of this once in 6 or 7 dayes to continue the <hi>Ale</hi> quicke and ſweet,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:19071:70"/>
keeping it from extreame <hi>cold</hi> in winter, and from <hi>heat</hi> in ſummer.</p>
               <p>The beſt <hi>time</hi> of the yeere to take this <hi>poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> is the <hi>Spring</hi> and the <hi>Fall</hi> of the <hi>Leafe,</hi> yet it may conueniently bee vſed at any other <hi>Seaſon,</hi> ſo that the <hi>Patient</hi> keepe himſelfe from the <hi>iniuries of Winde, Raine, Heat and Cold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is commonly drunke after <hi>three dayes infuſion,</hi> but if the <hi>drinking</hi> of it bee deferred twice ſo long it will be clearer and better.</p>
               <p>Take it faſting in the <hi>morning,</hi> (halfe a <hi>pinte</hi> or more at once) or after a potcht <hi>Egge,</hi> or ſome other little repaſt, and two <hi>houres</hi> before <hi>Supper:</hi> you may likewiſe drinke it one or two houres before <hi>Dinner,</hi> and two or three houres after <hi>Supper</hi> alſo, if you would purge much in few dayes: but milde working for many dayes by moderate <hi>drinking</hi> is the beſt <hi>order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Winter</hi> ſcarre off the <hi>cold</hi> with a <hi>Toſt,</hi> and <hi>Nutmeg</hi> and <hi>Sugar</hi> if you will: to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent <hi>Night-riſing</hi> and taking <hi>cold,</hi> it is not amiſſe to take it an houre before you riſe, when you are vp and readie, and an houre or two before <hi>dinner</hi> alſo if you pleaſe, and none after noone, and at meales the beſt is to forbeare it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:19071:70"/>In <hi>faire weather</hi> and temperate Seaſons, if the body be of ability, neuer intermit or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare your <hi>ordinarie buſineſſe,</hi> but rather, to further the operation of the Potion, follow your outward or field affaires or exerciſe, but both theſe muſt bee moderate and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Sunne and Sunne: Nor is it amiſſe to exerciſe the body in vnſeaſonable weather alſo, prouided this be done euermore in this caſe within doores.</p>
               <p>Let your <hi>meals</hi> be moderate, and alwayes end them before your <hi>appetite</hi> bid you, euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more riſing with a good <hi>ſtomacke</hi> and deſire of eating more, and, ſo much as, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience of your <hi>calling</hi> and <hi>occaſions,</hi> may well be, refraine meats of <hi>ill iuice</hi> and <hi>hard di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion:</hi> yet ſtrong conſtitutions and bodies, inured and accuſtomed to much labour, coorſe fare or groſſe food, may vſe their ordinary <hi>Diet</hi> for the qualitie or kinde of meats, ſo that they exceed not in the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie: but raw fruits and very ſalt meats may not be admitted.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Panala</hi> is a nouriſhing <hi>Potion,</hi> yet a gentle purger and clenſer of the Body of all ill <hi>Humors</hi> and <hi>Superfluities,</hi> by <hi>Stoole,</hi> by <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine,</hi> and by <hi>Sweat,</hi> a pleaſant <hi>Curer,</hi> and a ſingular good <hi>preuenter</hi> of <hi>Crudities, Rheums,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:19071:71"/>
obſtructions,</hi> (three maine fountains of infinit Infirmities) and moſt other maladies where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto the body of man is ſubiect.</p>
               <p>It may with ſafe and good ſucceſſe be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of young children, tender women, and weake bodies, both in ſickneſſe and before; for it is a comfortable <hi>rectifier</hi> of the whole ſtate of the Body.</p>
               <p>But in <hi>Conſumptions</hi> of the <hi>Spirits</hi> and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid parts, it cannot ſafely bee continued if it be made vp with <hi>purging Ingredients,</hi> though without them it may be compounded to bee of excellent vſe for ſingular comfort and ſtrength in ſuch waſtings, and all other weakneſſe.</p>
               <p>This is the Summe and Subſtance of the whole Booke.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:19071:71"/>
            <head>Ad Beneuolos.</head>
            <l>If Hackney-hoſts prate lip-laſh (humor-pleaſings)</l>
            <l>Gueſts t'intertaine, may freely vent ſans Gages,</l>
            <l>Then why not I word-gawdies, ſith non-leaſings?</l>
            <l>Coy chamber-chats to court quaint garb for pages?</l>
            <l>For youngsters ſpruce terſe rolls of rhet'rick writ?</l>
            <l>Strong lines to line th'weak texture of my warks?</l>
            <l>Plaine Fuſtian here the Freſh-mans Cappe to fit,</l>
            <l>There Inkhorne termes for Pedants puny Clarks;</l>
            <l>Here Ale-froth (Turgent ſtyle) for barmy vains,</l>
            <l>There Linſey-woolſey Stuffe for Trauelliers,</l>
            <l>Here phraſes phalerate for Courtly Streines</l>
            <l>There briske Embelliſhments for Cauelliers:</l>
            <l>Cramb biſcoct for carps, for Momes muſhro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cold</l>
            <l>For palate puffe-paſte, bumbaſt for the Braine,</l>
            <l>New coin for new-comes, for Eld th'antick mold,</l>
            <l>For learned Lads Colours of richer Graine:</l>
            <l>For ſhallows ſhails, fumes and Mercuriall flaſhes,</l>
            <l>Preſt ſulphur-fancies for quicke vapouriſts,</l>
            <l>Subſtanciate ſalts (extracts from lighter aſhes)</l>
            <l>And kernels for Sophian Centraliſts:</l>
            <l>Hug, ſhrug, fleere, jibe &amp; jeere, ſo th'umor pleaſe you,</l>
            <l>The bent of my ambition is to eaſe you,</l>
            <l>And ſend you iocund Health</l>
            <l>To ioy your louiall Wealth.</l>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:19071:72"/>
               <head>Ad Zoilum &amp; Sciolum.</head>
               <l>Art'lumpiſh, muddie, dull? doe Spirits groſſe</l>
               <l>Damp &amp; bemould thy mind with muſty dumps?</l>
               <l>Aſſociate's congregate, Comrades in Groſſe</l>
               <l>But Lit'rates all, elſe ill the Turba jumps;</l>
               <l>Then take <hi>Panala,</hi> Booke I meane, not Broth,</l>
               <l>(tho this doth bruſh th'unfurbiſht duskie braine)</l>
               <l>And let Mas mime or Mome with Gobar-tooth</l>
               <l>Read-out ſome lines, quite Byas natiue ſtraine:</l>
               <l>Odcombian muſicke ſtreight wil crown the crowd</l>
               <l>With jocund mirth &amp; glee; There's not a page</l>
               <l>But canvaſt thus diſpels each moodie clowde</l>
               <l>With garbe Sardonian, yea laughes Stentor gage</l>
               <l>Will ſtretch thy Hypochondriques, if in Cue,</l>
               <l>By d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſing on the Text, thou Criticize,</l>
               <l>And curious words, with Countenance a-skue</l>
               <l>With quibs and quaeres fond Anatomize;</l>
               <l>Thus ſcurui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> brows, this better cloers fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clouds</l>
               <l>Than crauing ſcrapes of many fidling Crowds.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:19071:72"/>
               <head>A Iove principium.</head>
               <l>The Reins of Life and Death are in the Lord</l>
               <l>Almighties hand, without his prouidence</l>
               <l>Sparrow nor Hayre doth fall, (tis Chriſts owne word)</l>
               <l>Much leſſe doth Man, the lucid Euidence</l>
               <l>And patterne of his daily patronage:</l>
               <l>Hath Griefe or Sickneſſe then thee proſtrate laid,</l>
               <l>And for reliefe wouldſt (prouident) engage</l>
               <l>Thy reſolution for Phyſicke ayde?</l>
               <l>True-humbled firſt vnder Gods mighty Hand</l>
               <l>With contrite penitence thy ſinnes agnize,</l>
               <l>His mercies craue, with conſcience well ſcand</l>
               <l>To him in Chriſt (the Lambe, bleſt Sacrifice)</l>
               <l>Thee reconcile: The Meanes then pray him bleſſe,</l>
               <l>And ſtraight to Phyſicke doe thy ſelfe addreſſe.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Flectere ſi nequeu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſuperos Acheronta mouebu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</head>
               <l>Of ſecret ſickneſſe when ſome ſeiſure rare</l>
               <l>Or Symptomes ſtrange doe plunge the iudgment poore,</l>
               <l>Blinde ſuperſtition then ſuggeſts deſpaire</l>
               <l>Of phyſickes ayd from graue or learned lore;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Look-forth</hi> rings in the eare, rules in rude hearts</l>
               <l>Some planet ill hath ſtrucke, Fayries haue tane,</l>
               <l>Or miſcreant Tongues, accurſed Eyes, damn'd Arts,</l>
               <l>Haue plung'd man in ſuch plight to worke his bane.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:19071:73"/>The wiſe man ſtraight, or warped mother Mumble</l>
               <l>Muſt be conſulted with in this hard caſe:</l>
               <l>To chatter Charmes, or colour'd Cups to jumble</l>
               <l>Their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ocator to fetch them trots a pace.</l>
               <l>Thus fancies fond God and his good meanes ſlight</l>
               <l>And Troth imply'd with Beliall doe plight.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Vna cadem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> manus vulnus opem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> feret.</head>
               <l>Doth ſpirit-griefe, or ſickneſſe corporall</l>
               <l>Thy troubled mind or craiſed Body cumber,</l>
               <l>With dints deriu'd from cauſes naturall</l>
               <l>Or ſupernaturall in waight or number?</l>
               <l>To phyſicke flying if thou doſt confide</l>
               <l>Simply in Simples, drugs of rare eſteeme,</l>
               <l>Or learn'd <hi>Higaeias</hi> Art, Thou art cleere wide,</l>
               <l>But wider far and wicked, if thou deeme</l>
               <l>That any Wizard with his Saintiſh, ſhow</l>
               <l>Of meanes, words, writings, colourably pure,</l>
               <l>Or woman wiſe with ſuperſtitious Doo,</l>
               <l>Of ſenſleſſe ceremonies can thee cure:</l>
               <l>Gods hand that gaue the wound, or way vnto it,</l>
               <l>Muſt giue thee help, 'thout him no power can do it.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Ne Hercules contra duos.</head>
               <l>The Patient, Phyſician and Diſeaſe</l>
               <l>Doe conſtitute a three-fold combatance,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:19071:73"/>Each couplet ſiding euer doth diſſeiſe</l>
               <l>And quell th'Opponent with concomitance.</l>
               <l>When Patients ioyne in body and in mind</l>
               <l>With Doctors Art, ſickneſſe is put to flight.</l>
               <l>When ill Phyſicians, or in iudgement blind,</l>
               <l>Or careleſſe, carry not their cures aright,</l>
               <l>But erring'gainſt Nature, with ſickneſſe ſide,</l>
               <l>Such double force not able to ſuſtaine,</l>
               <l>Naught ſaue deſtruction can the ſicke betide.</l>
               <l>But if the Patient fond through fancie vaine</l>
               <l>Side with the ſickneſſe, downe then goes ſir Doctor,</l>
               <l>Gainſt Infamy no Innocence gets Proctor.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Impar congreſſus Achilli.</head>
               <l>Sole Nature, with ſelfe-Faculties (at firſt</l>
               <l>By th' Naturant infus'd) of Actiue Spirits,</l>
               <l>Diſeaſes potent in Mans bulke imprest</l>
               <l>Encounters, combats, forceth, foyles, forth-ferrets:</l>
               <l>Yet recrudeſcence oft her troope disbands,</l>
               <l>Vneath concoct they what rebellious lurke;</l>
               <l>And when impact ore-Ballaſts all their hands</l>
               <l>Doe manicle, to weale how ſhould ſhe worke?</l>
               <l>But lighten ſtraight her load, and breake her Bands,</l>
               <l>Shele grapple with Gigantine griefes, repeale</l>
               <l>Deaths menac'd doomes, where Artles-idle ſtands,</l>
               <l>Expecting th' aydleſſe force, which Time doth ſteale,</l>
               <l>Till Nature nill, and Phyſicke will not, worke,</l>
               <l>Bieres meerly build to beare the corps to th'kirke.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:19071:74"/>
               <head>Bis orat, qui benè laborat.</head>
               <l>When prest Obedience and induſtry pace</l>
               <l>Concomitants cloſe ſiding faithfull prayer,</l>
               <l>Prayer then (ſure) purchaſeth th'entrusted Grace</l>
               <l>Of health and heauenly helpes which man doth ſhaer.</l>
               <l>But th'idle verbaliſt, whoſe addle braine</l>
               <l>Thinkes for bare labour of a lip of babel</l>
               <l>At Gods immediate hand ſupplies to gaine</l>
               <l>Sans meane and ſelfe deuoire (grant-ſeale and label)</l>
               <l>To pine or periſh in his want deſerues</l>
               <l>For diſobedience to his Ordinance,</l>
               <l>Who his beſt boones and bleſſings choice reſerues</l>
               <l>For dooers, the Induſtrious to aduance.</l>
               <l>He double prayes, who lab'ring well purſues</l>
               <l>Due meanes for good, ordain'd of God to vſe.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Plus Vltra.</head>
               <l>He that with Clyster can the Costiue eaſe,</l>
               <l>The ſtufe Intestines ſcoure with rouſing purge,</l>
               <l>The ſtomacke and confining parts releaſe</l>
               <l>Of Ballasts, which with greivances them vrge,</l>
               <l>Can ſlice a veine, and by the trifid ſluce</l>
               <l>Of ſanguiſuge diminiſh peccant blood,</l>
               <l>Can doſe a Dormatiue ſhall driue a Truce</l>
               <l>To vagrant ſpirits, when want of ſleepe make wood,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:19071:74" rendition="simple:additions"/>Thinkes himſelfe worthy of the Doctor Chayer</l>
               <l>Cauſe thus he Trots the road they daily plod;</l>
               <l>But there's <hi>Plus vltra,</hi> ere he can repaire</l>
               <l>The craiſed Bower of the ſoules abode;</l>
               <l>Treaſures of blood and Radique humide ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re,</l>
               <l>From depredation ſhield, Life balſm reſtore.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Natura non facit-ſaltum.</head>
               <l>The ſicke are way-farers (with cumber loaden</l>
               <l>Of traſhie reliques) bound for pilgrimage,</l>
               <l>Phyſicke an Angel, that lends wholeſome Leaden,</l>
               <l>Lightens their burthens, yeelds kind aequipage,</l>
               <l>Cleers, plains, makes paſſable, ſafe guards their waies,</l>
               <l>With brizes coole correcteth ſoultrie Heats,</l>
               <l>Shades with vmbrels from <hi>Phoebus</hi> torrid Rayes,</l>
               <l>Cold, wet and wind, and durt and duſt defeats,</l>
               <l>With cord'al food and rich Borachios Armes,</l>
               <l>Thirſt, hunger, faintings, wearineſſe auerts,</l>
               <l>From bainfull Cates, falſe baites, ſly Syren charmes,</l>
               <l>The Appetite, Senſes, Fancy, all diuerts:</l>
               <l>Thus with more eaſe, leſſe time &amp; toyle they trip i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Yet at an inſtant looke not they ſhould skip it.</l>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
